[{"question":"The dimensions of momentum are","options":["MLT","ML<sup>-1<\/sup>T<sup>-1<\/sup>","MLT<sup>-1<\/sup>","ML<sup>-1<\/sup>T",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"A student measures the volume of a liquid using a measuring cylinder. What else needs to be measured by the student in order to determine the density of the liquid?","options":["depth of the liquid in the cylinder","mass of the cylinder","mass of the liquid","tempersture of the liquid",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"A ball is dropped from the top of a tower. Due to air resistance,it reaches terminal velocity. Which of the following statement(s) about its motion is\/are correct? i. The acceleration of the ball is zero.  ii. The net force on the ball is zero.  iii. The velocity of the ball increases.","options":["i only","i and ii only","ii and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following substances lowers the surface tension of water?","options":["metal","sand","detergent","paper",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"An object of volume 400cm<sup>3<\/sup> and 2.5gcm<sup>-3<\/sup> is suspended from a spring balance with half its volume immersed in water. Determine the reading on the spring balance. (Density of water = 1gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>)","options":["1200g","1000g","800g","400g",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The two person of a body undergoing a uniformly accelerated motion are (10s, 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup>) and (30s, 50ms<sup>-1<\/sup>). On the velocity-time graph pf the body.","options":["0.5ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.0ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","10.0ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","40.0ms<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"At a birthday party, the celebrant pops a corked fruit wine. If the cork shoots out of the bottle at an angle of 40<sup>o<\/sup> to the horizontal and travels a horizontal distance of 4.50m in 1.25s. Calculate the initial speed of the cork.","options":["4.2ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.7ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.6ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","7.1ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"A uniform metre rule is balanced on a fulcrum placed at the 35cm mark by suspending a mass of 120g at the 10cm mark. Calculate the mass of the metre rule.","options":["60g","80g","120g","200g",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"When a body is thrown vertically upwards, its velocity at the maximum height is","options":["maximium","zero","double its initial value","half its initial value",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Resonance occurs when one vibrating object causes a second object to vibrate at its own natural","options":["amplitude","speed","frequency","intensity",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The mouth piece of a telephone handset converts","options":["electrical energy to sound energy","sound energy to electrical energy","sound energy to radiowave","radiowave to sound energy",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"In the clinical thermometer, the function of the kink is to   i. Prevent the back flow of mercury after use.  ii. Ensure the back flow of mercury after use.  iii. Maintain the thermometric property of mercury. iv. Allow the temperature attained to be read.","options":["i only","i and ii only","i and iv only","iii and iv only",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following statements correctly defines the boiling point of a liquid? The temperature at which the","options":["saturated vapour pressure equals the atmospheric pressure","molecules leaves the liquid at a rate equal to the rate at which they return","molecules leave the liquid at a rate higher than that at which they return","molecules leave the liquid at a rate lower than the rate at which they return",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"An aluminium rod of length 1.8m at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C is heated to proceed produce a difference in length of 0.007m. Calculate the temperature to which it is heated. (Linear expansivity of aluminium = 2.3 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","options":["155<sup>o<\/sup>C","160<sup>o<\/sup>C","169<sup>o<\/sup>C","179<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"A mercury-in-glass thermometer read 4cm at ice point and 29cm at steam point. Calculate the temperature when the mercury level is at 9cm","options":["13<sup>o<\/sup>C","20<sup>o<\/sup>C","33<sup>o<\/sup>C","38<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The continuous stirring in the method of mixtures to determine the specific thermal capacity of a substance ensures","options":["continuous dissipation of heat to the room","uniform distribution of thermal energy to all parts of the mixture","that the thermal energy is confined to the mixture","that there is rapid heat exchange",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct about the effect of dissolved salt on the freezing point of water?","options":["the freezing point is lowered","the freezing point is increased","there is no change in the freezing point","the change in the freezing point depends on the temperature of the surrounding",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"A pressurized perfume bottle is left on the window pane of a room. What happens to he gas molecules of the perfume on a sunny day? They","options":["expand","collide less often","move more rapidly","contract",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Given that v, f and \\(\\lambda\\) are the velocity, frequency and wavelength of a wave respectively. Which of the following equations is correct?","options":["v = f<sup>2<\/sup>\\(\\lambda\\)","f = \\(\\frac{v}{\\lambda}\\)","f = \\(\\frac{v}{\\lambda^2}\\)","\\(\\lambda = \\frac{f}{v^2}\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The distance between two successive trough of a wave is 0.4m. If the frequency of the source is 825Hz, Calculate the speed of the wave","options":["165.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","330.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","41.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","85.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The image formed by a concave mirror is real, inverted and magnified, when object is placed","options":["at the focus","at the centre of curvature","beyond the centre of curvature","between the centre of curvature and the focus",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Total internal reflection.  i. is a phenomenon of refraction of light.  ii. occurs when light rays travel into a denser medium.  iii. occurs when the critical angle is just exceeded.  iv. is a phenomenon of reflection of light. Which of the statements above are correct?","options":["i and ii only","i and iii only","i, ii and iii only","i, iii and iv only",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Complementary colours are those which","options":["have the same refractive index","have the same wavelength","add-up to produce black light","add-up to produce white light",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The pair of musical instruments that works on the vibration of air in pipes is","options":["piano and the organ","guitar and the flute","trumpet and the violin","flute and the trumpet",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"An astronomical telescope has objectives and eye-piece lenses of focal length 3.5m and 5cm respectively. Determine the magnifying power of the telescope when in normal adjustment","options":["70.0","17.5","7.0","0.7",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"An aluminium cable of diameter 4 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>m and resistivity 3.0 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>\\(\\omega\\)m has a resistance of 21\\(\\Omega\\). Calculate the length of the cable. (\\(\\pi = 3.14\\))","options":["8.0 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>m","8.8 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>m","8.0 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>m","8.8 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The electricity meters in houses measure energy unit consumed in","options":["kilowatt-hour","volt","ampere","coulomb",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"A man and his friend have masses 70kg and 60kg respectively. If they are seated 1.0m apart, calculate the gravitational force of attraction between them. (G = 6.67 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup> Nm<sup>2<\/sup> kg<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["1.59 x 10<sup>-14<\/sup> N","2.80 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup> N","1.30 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup> N","6.30 x 10<sup>13<\/sup> N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The p.d across a parallel-plate capacitor is 10<sup>3<\/sup>V. If the distance between the two plates is 10cm. Calculate the magnitude of the electric field strength between the plates.","options":["1.0 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>Vm<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>Vm<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.5 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>Vm<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>Vm<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Two different materials, rubbed against each other acquired opposite charges when separated. This is an example of charging by","options":["induction","friction","conduction","convection",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Two different materials, rubbed against each other acquired opposite charges when separated. This is an example of charging by","options":["induction","friction","conduction","convection",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following factors does not affect the e.m.f of a primary cell? Its","options":["size","internal resistance","operating temperature","duration of usage",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"In storing magnets, keepers are used to","options":["reduced self-demagnetization","cancel the effect of the earth's magnetic field","protect the magnet from stray electric field","increase the strangth of the magnets",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"A 10\\(\\mu\\)C charge moves with a velocity of 1.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup> ms<sup>-1<\/sup> at right angle to a uniform magnetic field of flux density 5.0 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>T. Calculate the force on the charge","options":["5.0 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>N","5.0 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>N","5.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>N","5.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct about steel and soft iron?","options":["steel is more magnetized than soft iron","permanent magnets are usually made of steel","soft iron is more readily magnetized than steel","soft iron more readily loses its magnetism than steel",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"What determines the polarity at the ends of an electromagnet? The","options":["magnitude of the current passing through the wire","material of the core of the magnet","material of the coil","direction of current in the wire",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"How many beta particle(s) are emitted in the radioactive decay of \\(^{198}_{79}Au  \\leftarrow ^{198}_{80}Hg\\)?","options":["1","2","3","5",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"The phenomenon by which two light atomic nuclear combine to form a heavy nuclide with the release of energy is known as","options":["radioactivity","nuclear fusion","nuclear fission","chain reaction",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"In a p-type semiconductor, the","options":["number of holes are equal to the number of electrons","electrical resistivity increases","electrons are the majority charge carriers","holes are the majority charge carriers",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Let \\(\\Delta\\)x be the uncertainty in the measurements of position and \\(\\Delta\\)p the uncertainty in measurement of momentum. The uncertainty principle relation is given as","options":["\\(\\Delta\\)x . \\(\\Delta\\)p = h","\\(\\Delta\\)x . \\(\\Delta\\)p \\(\\leq\\) = h","\\(\\Delta\\)x . \\(\\Delta\\)p \\(\\geq\\) = h","\\(\\Delta\\)x . \\(\\Delta\\)p > h",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2016"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about mass and weight are correct? i. Weight is the force of gravity on a body.  ii. The mass of a body is the quantity of matter in the body. iii. The weight of a body is greatest at the equator. iv. The mass of a body is greatest at the poles","options":["i and ii only","i and iii only","ii and iv only","iii and iv only",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Materials that can be stretched and still return to their original forms when the stresses are removed are said be","options":["elastic","elastomer","plastic","thermoplastic",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following units is derived?","options":["kg","m","K","N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The barometric reading at a place is 73.5m Hg. Calculate the pressure at a point 30m below the surface of water contained in a reservoir at the place. [g = ms<sup>-2<\/sup>, density = 1.2 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>kg m<sup>-3<\/sup>, density of water = 1.0 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>m<sup>-3<\/sup>]","options":["4.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup> Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","3.0 x 10 <sup>5<\/sup> Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup> Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","1.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup> Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"An object floats in a fluid when it displaces it's","options":["volume of liquid in which it floats","mass of fluid in which it foats","weith of fluid in which it foats","density of fluid in which it foats",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The resultant  force  in a couple is","options":["zero","infinite","the sum of the forces","thr product of the forces",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The slope of a straight-line velocity-time graph represents","options":["uniform acceleration","uniform speed","total distance travelled","workdone",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A body is projected with an initial velocity U at an angle O to the horizontal. The time taken by it to reach its maximum height is given by the expression","options":["\\(\\frac{2u \\text{sin}\\theta}{g}\\)","\\(\\frac{u^2 \\text{sin}^2\\theta}{2g}\\)","\\(\\frac{u \\text{sin}\\theta}{g}\\)","\\(\\frac{u \\text{sin}\\theta}{2g}\\)",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following statements  describes a body in a stable equilibrium correctly?","options":["a person walking on a tight-rope","ball on a smooth horizontal table","ball resting on an inverted hemisphere bowl","ball in the middle of a nemispherical bowl",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"In a school compound a girl walks 40km due east from the laboratory to the staff room to submit her report. Then she returns and walks 30m due north to her classroom. Determine  the magnitude of her displacement from the10m laboratory","options":["10m","35m","50m","70m",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Two strings each inclined at an angle 30<sup>o<\/sup> to the horizontal are used to hold a bucket of water weighing 20N. Calculate the tension i n each string.","options":["20\\(sqrt{3}\\)N","20N","10\\(sqrt{3}\\)N","10N",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A bullet fired vertically upwards reaches a height of 500m. Neglecting air resistance, calculate  the magnitude  of the initial velocity of the bullet. [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["500.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","100.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","70.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","50.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A uniform bar AB is balanced on a knife-edge which is 60cm from B by a mass of 22g which hangs at C 10cm from A. Calculate the mass of the bar.","options":["133.2g","66.0g","60.0g","22.0g",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A body of mass 1000kg is released from a height of 10m above the ground. Determine its kinetic energy just before it strikes the ground .[g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["10J","10<sup>3<\/sup>J","10<sup>4<\/sup>J","10<sup>5<\/sup>J",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The crackling noise produced by aluminum roofing sheets on a house during a hot sunny day is a result of","options":["thermal equilibrium of the sheets","conduction of heat by the sheets","contraction of the sheets","expansion of the sheets",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Water is unsuitable for use as a thermometric liquid because it","options":["expands unevenly between 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 40<sup>o<\/sup>C","has narrow temperature range","has a concave meniscus","msintsin s fixed density",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A quantity of hot water at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C is added to 400g of water at 10<sup>o<\/sup>C until the temperature of the mixture is 60<sup>o<\/sup>C.<br>\r\n<br>\r\nCalculate the mass of the hot water added. [Specific heat capacity of water =4200JKg<sup>-1<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["200g","320g","400g","500g",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following concepts is a method of heat transfer that does not require a material medium?","options":["conduction","radiation","diffusion","convection",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following units is the S.I. unit of heat capacity?","options":["Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>","Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup>","JK<sup>-1<\/sup>","Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The pressure applied to an enclosed fluid to one end id transmitted equally throughout the fluid and to the container walls. This statement is","options":["Archimede's principle","Bernoulli's principle","Pascal's principle Heisenberg's","Heisenberg's uncertainty principle",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"What type of wave is emitted by  a loud speaker?","options":["Transverse","Longitudinal","Gamma","Radio",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"An object is placed 15cm from a diverging lens of focal length 1cm. The image of the object formed by the lens in","options":["real and 6.67cm from the lens","virtual and 6.67cm from the lens","real and 60.00cm from the lens","virtual and 60.00cm from the lens",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A swimming pool is .1m deep. If it contains water of refractive index 1.3, calculate the apparent depth of pool","options":["3.4m","2.7m","1.6m","0.8m",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"When an air column is set into vibrations, the distance between two consecutive nodes of the resultant wave is","options":["one quarter of the wavelength","half of the wavelength","the wavelength","twice the wavelength",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A girl standing some distance from the cliff claps her hands and hears the echo 0.8s later. calculate her distance from the cliff. [speed of sound in air = 320 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["23m","128m","288m","298m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Red light travels faster than blue light when both of them pass through a glass prism because the","options":["refractive index of red light is grester than that of blue light","refractive index of blue light is greater than that of red light","red light is more intense than the blue light","blue light is more intense than the red light",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"An object is placed 20cm from a concave mirror of focal length 15cm. Calculate the linear magnification of the image formed","options":["0.5","1.5","2.0","3.0",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"All electromagnetic waves in a vacuum have the same","options":["wavelength","frequency","speed","amplitude",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"An alternating current supply is connected to an electric lamp which lights with the same brightness as it does with direct current source emf 6v. The peak potential difference of the a.c supply is","options":["4.6v","6.0v","8.5v","12.0v",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"An electric generate rated 12kw, 2kv distribute power through a capable of resistance 0. Calculate the power loss in the cable","options":["120 w","360 w","720 w","2400 w",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct? When capacitors of different values are connected in series","options":["the same charge flows through them","the same voltage appears across each capacitor","different quantities of charges flow through them in different voltages across them","different quantities of charges flows through them with the same voltage across them",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about a three-pin plug is\/are correct. i. The brown wire is the live wire. ii. The fuse is connected to the live wire. iii. The earth wire is coloured blue","options":["i only","ii only","i and ii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A wire of cross-sectional area 0.60mm<sup>2<\/sup> has a restivity of 7.2 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup> \\(\\Omega\\). Calculate the length of wire that will have a resistance of 3\\(\\Omega\\).","options":["0.25m","2.50m","3.60m","36.00",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The mass of the earth is 6.0 x 10<sup>24<\/sup>kg and that of the moon is 7.0 x 10<sup>22<\/sup>kg. If the distance between them is 4.0 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>m, calculate the force of attraction between them. [G = 6.7 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>Nm<sup>2<\/sup>kg<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["1.8 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>N","1.8 x 10<sup>10<\/sup>N","1.8 x 10<sup>15<\/sup>N","1.8 x 10<sup>20<\/sup>N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"The angle which the direction of the earth magnetic field makes with the horizontal at a palace is know as.","options":["angle of contact","angle of dip","angle of declination","magnetic meridian",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"When current flows through a moving-coil galvanometer, the force exerted on the pointer depends on the: i. strength of the current. ii. magnetic field strength. iii. length of the coil. Which of the statement(s) above is\/are correct?","options":["i only","ii only","i and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"in a nuclear fission process, the mass defect was 1.2 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>kg. Calculate the energy released. [speed of the light in vacuum = c = 3.0 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["1.08 x 10<sup>11<\/sup>J","5.20 x 10<sup>11<\/sup>J","1.08 x 10<sup>12<\/sup>J","2.50 x 10<sup>13<\/sup>J",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about diode is correct?","options":["reverse bias diodes have low resistance","forward bias diodes have high resistance","forward bias diodes produce high current","forward bias diodes function as a result of heat",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"Which of the following radiations constitutes a stream of electrons?","options":["Ramma rays","X-rays","Cathode rays","Radio waves",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"\\(^{226}_{88}Ra\\) emits two alpha particles to produce polonium(po) nuclide. The correct formula for the nuclide?","options":["\\(^{224}_{86}po\\)","\\(^{222}_{86}po\\)","\\(^{222}_{84}po\\)","\\(^{218}_{84}po\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"A ball falling through a viscous liquid is acted upon by","options":["upthrust only","upthrust and the ball's weight","the ball's weight and viscous force","upthrust, the ball's weight and viscous force",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"An object of mass m moves with a uniform speed v round a circular path of radius. If its angular speed is \\(\\omega\\), the magnitude of the centripetal force acting on it is","options":["\\(m \\omega^2 r\\)","\\(\\frac{mv^2}{r}\\)","\\(m \\omega r\\)","\\(\\frac{mv^2}{r^2}\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"When an elastic material is stretched by a force, the energy stored in it is","options":["kinetic","potential","thermal","electrical",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"When the linear momentum of a body is constant, the net force acting on it","options":["is zero","increases","decreases","remains constant",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"If no net force acts on an object, the object maintains a state of rest or constant speed in a straight line. The above is a statement of Newton's","options":["first law of motion","second law of motion","third law of motion","law of universal gravitation",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Which of the following pairs of physical quantities is made up of vectors?","options":["speed and displacement","mass and force","dislacement and acceleration","momentum and length",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The knowledge of surface tension is applied in the following areas except in","options":["manufacturing of rain coats","production of palm oil","floating of a needle on water","washing of plates with soapy water",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A body is projected vertically upwards with a speed of 10 ms<sup>-1<\/sup> from a point 2m above the ground. Calculate the total time taken for the body to reach the ground. [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["1.00s","2.00s","2.18s","3.00s",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A car starts from rest and covers a distance of 40m in 10s. Calculate the magnitude of its acceleration","options":["0.25ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","0.80ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","3.20ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","4.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The period of a simple pendulum X is 5s. What is the period of a simple pendulum Y which makes 50 vibrations in the same time it takes X to make 20 vibrations?","options":["12.5s","2.5s","2.0s","1.2s",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Alcohol of mass 21g and density 0.7g cm<sup>-3<\/sup> is mixed with 10g of water. Determine the density of the mixture [density of water = 1.0gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>]","options":["0.775gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.875gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.780gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>","0.880gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A device that converts mechanical energy into electrical energy is","options":["a dynamo","an electric motor","an induction coil","a transformer",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The S.I unit of power is","options":["N","Pa","W","J",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A screw-jack has the distance between its successive threads as P and the length of its tommy bar as r. Its velocity ratio is given by the expression","options":["\\(\\frac{2 \\pi r^2}{P}\\)","\\(\\frac{2 \\pi r}{P}\\)","\\(\\frac{2 \\pi}{rp}\\)","\\(\\frac{P}{2 \\pi r}\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Heat transfer by conduction is similar to wave motion because","options":["there is increase in temperature","transfer of naterials is involved","xharged particles vibrates at right angles","no transfer of materials is involved",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The temperature at which the water vapour in the air saturates the air and begins to condense is known as","options":["dew point","critical point","boiling point","tripple point",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The change of state from solid to liquid occurs","options":["at constant temperature","when temperature is lower than the boiling point","when temperature is just near freezing point","when teemperature is equal ro the boiling point",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"which of the following types of thermometers can be used to measure a range of temperature from -50<sup>o<\/sup>C to 50<sup>o<\/sup>?  i. Clinical  ii. Mercury  iii. Alcohol-in-glass","options":["i only","ii only","iii only","i and ii only",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A body of mass M kg rests on a plane inclined at an angle \\(\\theta\\) to the horizontal. The component of the weight of the body parallel to the plane is","options":["Mg sin \\(\\theta\\)","Mg cos \\(\\theta\\)","Mg tan \\(\\theta\\)","Mg sec \\(\\theta\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A quantity of water at 20<sup>o<\/sup>C is mixed with another quantity of water at 70<sup>o<\/sup>C. The final steady temperature of the mixture is 40<sup>o<\/sup>C. Determine the ratio of the mass of the cold water to that of the hot water","options":["7:2","3:2","2:5","1:2",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The mass of an empty density bottle is 30g. When filled with a liquid, the mass reduces to 38g. Calculate the apparent cubic expansivity of the liquid","options":["6.25 x 10K<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.25 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.50 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.50 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"a ca travelling at 30m<sup>-1<\/sup> overcomes a frictional resistance of 100N while moving. Calculate the power developed by the engine. [1 hp = 0.75 kW]","options":["0.23hp","0.40hp","4.00hp","4.40hp",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The quality of a note depends on its","options":["frequency","pitch","overtones","amplitude",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A transverse wave can be distinguished from a longitudinal wave by","options":["diffraction","relection","refraction","polarization",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Refraction of lights differs from reflection in that, in refraction  i. at least two media are involved  ii. there is a change in the direction of the ray  iii. the speed of the ray changes. Which of the statements above is\/are correct?","options":["i only","i ad ii only","ii and iii only","i and iii only",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Which of the following relations about the focal length f<sub>o<\/sub> of the objective and focal length f<sub>e<\/sub> of the eye piece of a compound is correct?","options":["f<sub>o<\/sub> = f<sub>e<\/sub>","f<sub>o<\/sub> < f<sub>e<\/sub>","f<sub>o<\/sub> > f<sub>e<\/sub>","f<sub>e<\/sub> = 2f<sub>o<\/sub>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The functional difference between a lens and a mirror is that a lens","options":["reflects a beam of light while a mirror refracts it","refracts a beam of light while a mirror reflects it","absorbs incident rays while a mirror transmit them","transmits incidents ray whle a mirror absorbs them",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A fish inside a pond appears to be at a depth of 1.5m when viewed vertically from above. The refractive index of the water in the pound is 1.3. Calculate the apparent displacement of the fish","options":["2.50m","1.95m","1.50m","0.45m",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"an observer hears an echo 1.26 seconds after blowing a whistle near a cliff. calculate the distance of the observer from the cliff. [speed of sound in air = 330ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["104.4m","207.9m","415.8m","523.8m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"An object is placed in front of two plane mirrors inclined at 60<sup>o<\/sup> to each other. Determine the number of the images formed","options":["2","3","5","7",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"An ammeter can be adapted to measure potential difference by using a","options":["shunt","multiplier","rheostat","resistance box",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The region around a magnet in which magnetic force can be expressed is known as","options":["declination","flux density","field","flux",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"In an ac circuit when the supply voltage frequency is equal to the resonant frequency, the current","options":["leads the supply voltge by 90<sup>o<\/sup>","lags behind the supply voltage by 90<sup>o<\/sup>","leads the supply voltage by 45<sup>o<\/sup>","is in phase with the supply voltage",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The energy stored in a simple cell is","options":["electrical","nuclear","thermal","chemical",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Which of the following conditions occur at resonance in a series RLC circuit?  i. Impedance equal resistance  ii. Current is maximum  iii. Reactance are maximum   iv. Current and voltage are 90<sup>o<\/sup> out of phase","options":["i and ii only","i and ii only","i, ii and iii only","i, ii, iii and iv",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"An electric motor converts","options":["electrical energy to mechanical energy","mechanical energy to electrical energy","mechanical energy to chemical energy","electrical energy to thermal energy",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A 15 \\(\\mu F\\) capacitor is connected to a 240V, 50Hz ac. source. Calculate the reactance of the capacitance [\\(\\pi = 3.142\\)]","options":["16\\(\\Omega\\)","68\\(\\Omega\\)","106\\(\\Omega\\)","212\\(\\Omega\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Two identical charges situated 20cm apart in vacuum repel each other with a force of 1.0N.Calculate the value of each other with a force of 1.0N. Calculate the value of each charge. [(14 \\(\\pi \\varepsilon_o)^{-1}\\) = 9 x 10<sup>9<\/sup>Nm<sup>2<\/sup>C<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["21\\(\\mu C\\)","3.6\\(\\mu C\\)","4.0\\(\\mu C\\)","4.4\\(\\mu C\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A wire of length 100 cm has a resistance of 10\\(\\Omega\\). If its cross-sectional area is 0.005cm<sup>2<\/sup>, determine its resistivity","options":["0.0005\\(\\Omega\\)cm","0.0015\\(\\Omega\\)cm","0.0016\\(\\Omega\\)cm","0.0700\\(\\Omega\\)cm",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"A transformer has 400 turns of wire in the primary coil and 40 turns in the secondary col. If the input voltage is 150 volts. Calculate the magnitude of the output voltage","options":["150V","55V","36V","15V",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The energy required to separate the nucleus in an atom completely is known as","options":["mass defect of the atom","electron binding energy","excitation energy","nuclear bnding energy",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is the major advantage of nuclear fusion over nuclear fission?","options":["nuclear fusion releases more energy","more neutrons are released in fusion than in fission","fussion does not release as much dangerous radiation as fission","fusion reactions occur more readily than fission",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"An aluminum foil is placed across a beam of radiation from a radioactive source. Which of the following types of radiation will be stopped by it?","options":["alpha and beta particles","alpha and gamma particles","beta and gamma particles","gamma particles only",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"An element of nucleon number P and atomic number Q emits an alpha particle from its nucleus. The resultant numbers of the new element formed are respectively","options":["P - 4 and Q + 2","P - 4 and Q - 2","P + 2 and Q + 2","P + 2 and Q - 2",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2014"},{"question":"The rising of a liquid in an open and ended glass tube of narrow bore is","options":["osmosis","adhesion","capillarity","surface tension",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about pressure in a liquid is correct?","options":["the pressure in a liquid increases with depth","the higher the density of a liquid, the lower the pressure it exerts","pressure in liquid act only in a direction perpendicular to the sides of the containing vessel","pressure is independent of the acceleration due to gravity",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Solid friction, like viscosity is","options":["independent of the surface area in contact","independent of the relative motion between layers","dependent on normal reaction","in opposition to motion",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The slope of a linear distance-times graph represents","options":["acceleration","displacement","speed","velocity",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"A body of mass 2kg is released from rest on a plane inclined at an angle of 60<sup>o<\/sup> to the horizontal. Calculate the acceleration of the body down the plane.[g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["3.1ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","5.2ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","6.0ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","8.7ms<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The total area under a force-velocity graph represents","options":["energy","momentum","power","pressure",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"A body of mass 20g projected vertically upwards in vacuum returns to the point of projection after 1.2s. [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]. Calculate the speed of projection","options":["1.2ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","12.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.6ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"A body of mass 20g projected vertically upwards in vacuum returns to the point of projection after 1.2s. [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]. Determine the potential energy of the body at the maximum height of its motion","options":["0.36J","0.72J","360.00J","720.00J",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The maximum displacement on either side of the equilibrium position of an object in simple harmonic motion represents","options":["period","amplitude","wavelength","frequency",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"From Newton's first law of motion,","options":["a body can only undergo translational motion","once a body remains at rest no force acts on it","the net force acting in uniform linear motion is zero","a body's inertia is its weight",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"A body of mass 11kg is suspended from a ceiling fan by an aluminum wire of length 2m and diameter 2mm. Calculate the elastic energy stored in the wire [Young's modulus of aluminum is 7.0 x 10<sup>10<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>, g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>, \\(\\pi\\) = 3.142]`","options":["1.1 x 10<sup>-1<\/sup>J","5.5 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>J","1.1 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","5.5 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>J",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The velocity ratio of an inclined plane","options":["increases with increase in the angle of inclination","increases with decrease in the angle of inclination","decreases with decrease in the angle of inclination","is independent of the angle of inclination",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following types of thermometer is used for the calibration of other thermometers?","options":["liqud-in-glass thermometer","constant volume gas thermometer","optical pyrometer","thermocouple",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The magnitude of the expansion or contraction of a substance depends on the   i. temperature change  ii. nature of the substance  iii. size of the substance. Which of the statements above are correct?","options":["i and ii only","ii and iii only","i and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Highly polished silvery surfaces are","options":["poor absorbers and poor emitters of radiation","poor absorbers and good emitters of radiation","good absorbers and poor emitters of radiation","good absorbers and good emitters of radiation",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The volume of a given mass of gas at 27<sup>o<\/sup>C and 800 mmHg is 76cm<sup>2<\/sup>. Calculate its volume at s.t.p","options":["100.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","72.8 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","60.0 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","36.4 cm<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Ice of mass 10g at 5<sup>o<\/sup>C was completely converted to water at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C, calculate the quantity of heat used. [specific heat capacity of ice = 2.1 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>, specific latent heat of fusion of ice = 336 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["105J","3255J","3265J","16821J",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"An electric heater has a resistance of 50\\(\\Omega\\). When it is immersed in water and connected to mains source, it draws a current of 4.0A. Calculate the heat gained by the water if the heater is switched on for 2 minutes, assuming no heat losses to the surroundings","options":["400J","1600J","24000J","96000J",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"When salt is dissolved in water, the freezing point of the water","options":["increases","decreases","remains the same","increases and later decrease",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"the equation of a certain progressive transverse wave is y = 2 sin 2 \\(\\pi ( \\frac{1}{0.01} - \\frac{x}{30})\\), where x and y are in cm and t in seconds. Calculate the period of the wave","options":["0.001s","0.010s","10.000s","100.000s",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"At which position should an object be placed in front of a concave mirror in order to obtain an image which is of the same size as the object?","options":["at the centre of curvature","at the principal focus","between the pole and principal focus","between the centre of curvature and principal focus",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Images formed by a convex mirror are always","options":["magnified","behind the mirror","real","inverted",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The refractive index of a material is 1.5. Calculate the critical angle at the glass-air interface","options":["19<sup>o<\/sup>","21<sup>o<\/sup>","39<sup>o<\/sup>","42<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"A diverging lens of focal length 30cm produces an image 20cm from the lens. Determine the object distance","options":["10cm","12cm","50cm","60cm",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the Galilean telescope is not correct?","options":["the final image is inverted","it is shorter than terrestial telescope","the final image is erect","it has a small field of view",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following radiations has it's frequency lower than that of infrared radiation?","options":["Utra-violet rays","gamma rays","x-rays","radio waves",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"a string under tension produces a note of frequency 14Hz. Determine the frequency when the tension is quadrupled","options":["14Hz","18Hz","28Hz","56Hz",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about waves in pipes is correct?","options":["for open pipes, there is only one end correction to be accounted for","for closed pipes, there are two end corrections to be accounted for","only odd harmonics are possible in closed pipes","all harmonics are possible in closed pipes",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"When a person holds a negatively charges metal rod and stands bare-footed on the ground, how will the charges leak?","options":["negative charges flows to the ground through the person's body","positive charges flow from the ground through his body to neutralize the negative charges","positive charges in the air neutralizes the negative charges the person is holding","negative charges will leak through the air",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"a charge of 2.0 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>C experiences a force of 80N in a uniform electric field. Calculate the magnitude of the electric field intensity","options":["8.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup> NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup> NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.0 x 10<sup>4<\/sup> NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0 x 10<sup>4<\/sup> NC<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"A potential difference of 12V is applied across the ends of a 6\\(\\Omega\\) resistor for 10 minutes. Determine the quantity of heat generated","options":["720J","1200J","14400J","43200J",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following instruments is used to determine the accurate value of the electromotive force of a cell?","options":["voltmeter","meterbridge","voltameter","potentiometer",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The capacitance of parallel plates capacitors varies","options":["inversely as the square of the distance between the plates","directly as the square of the distance between the plates","inversely as the distance between the plates","directly as the distance between the plate",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following devices does not makes use of eddy current for its action? A\/An","options":["galvanometer","speedometer","induction furnace","speedometer",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"A coil of inductance 0.12 H and resistance 4\\(\\Omega\\), is connected across a 240V, 50Hz supply. Calculate the current through it. [\\(\\pi\\) = 3.142]","options":["6.3A","33.3A","37.2A","40.0A",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The work function of a metal is 2.56 x 10<sup>-19<\/sup>J. Calculate the frequency of a photon whose energy is required to eject from the metal an electron with kinetic energy of 3.0ev. [1 eV = 1.6 x 10<sup>-19<\/sup>J, h = 6.6 x 10<sup>-34<\/sup>Js]","options":["5.56 x 10<sup>19<\/sup>Hz","1.66 x 10<sup>19<\/sup>Hz","1.12 x 10<sup>15<\/sup>Hz","8.42 x 10<sup>14<\/sup>Hz",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The minimum energy required to cause photoelectric emission when the surface of a metal is irradiated with electromagnetic radiation of suitable frequency is called","options":["critical energy","ionization energy","work function","planck's constant",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following particles are termed nucleons in a neutral atom?","options":["protons and neutrons","neutrons and electrons","protons and electrons","protons, electrons and neutrons",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the use of radioisotopes is not correct? They are used to","options":["induce mutations in plants and animals to obtain new and improved varieties","trace the paths of metabolic processes in plants and animals","estmate the age of rocks","locate broken bones",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"Which of the following phenomena supports the theory that waves have a particle nature?","options":["electron diffraction","photoelectric effect","diffraction of light","x-ray interference",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2013"},{"question":"The derived unit of pressure can be expressed as","options":["kgms<sup>-2<\/sup>","kg m<sup>-1<\/sup>s<sup>-2<\/sup>","kg m<sup>-2<\/sup>s<sup>-2<\/sup>","kg m<sup>-1<\/sup>s<sup>2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following devices is used to determine the relative density of an acid?","options":["manometer","hydrometer","hypsometer","hygrometer",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A block of wood of density 0.6 gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>, weighing 3.06N in air, floats freely in a liquid of density 0.9 gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>. Calculate volume of the portion immersed (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["510cm<sup>3<\/sup>","340cm<sup>3<\/sup>","254cm<sup>3<\/sup>","170cm<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A metal ball of weight W falls through a column of glycerine of viscosity V. If the ball experiences an upthrust U and terminal velocity is attained is attained, then","options":["W > U + V","W = U + V","W = U - V","W < U + V",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The movement of fluid up or down a narrow tube is","options":["osmosis","brownian motion","capillarity","diffusion",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following substances is the most volatile at room temperature?","options":["water","diesel","petrol","kerosine",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"a bird flies at 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup> for 3s, 15ms<sup>-1<\/sup> for 3s and 20 ms<sup>-1<\/sup> for 4s. Calculate the bird's average speed","options":["4.5 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","15.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","15.5 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","51.7 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The time of flight for a projectile motion is given by the expression","options":["\\(\\frac{U sin \\theta}{g}\\)","\\(\\frac{U sin \\theta}{2g}\\)","\\(\\frac{2U sin \\theta}{g}\\)","\\(\\frac{U sin 2\\theta}{g}\\)",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An object is dropped from the top of a tower. If it takes 4s for it to reach the ground, calculate the height of the tower.(g = 10 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>, ignore air resistance)","options":["20m","40m","80m","160m",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"When a body is slightly titled, it is found that its centre of gravity s slightly raised. What is the state of equilibrium of the body?","options":["unstable","stable","neutal","cannot be detrmined",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A simple pendulum makes 50 oscillations in one minutes. Determine its period of oscillation","options":["0.04s","0.83s","1.20s","50.00s",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The tendency for a stationary body to continue to remain at rest when a force is applied to it is known as","options":["friction","impulse","inertia","momentum",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A resultant force of magnitude 15N acts on a body of mass 250g. Calculate the magnitude of the acceleration","options":["0.06 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","3.75ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","16.67ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","60.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A girl stands on a scale in a lift. If the reading on the scale is less than her weight, then the lift is moving","options":["upward at uniform speed","upward with uniform acceleration","downward with uniform speed","downward with uniform acceleration",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The S.I unit of heat is","options":["joule","kelvin","watt","ampere",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A body is pulled through a distance of 500m by a force of 20N. If the power developed is 0.4kW, calculate the time for which the force acts","options":["250.0s","25.0s","2.5s","0.5s",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A metal sheet of area 100cm<sup>2<\/sup> was heated through 70<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate its new area if the linear expansivity of the metal is 0.000017k<sup>-1<\/sup>","options":["100.06 cm<sup>2<\/sup>","100.12cm<sup>2<\/sup>","100.24cm<sup>2<\/sup>","100.36cm<sup>2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The thermopile is a device for detecting","options":["radioactive radiations","adiant energy","x-rays","the presence of electrons",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"In the formation of sea breeze. wind blows from","options":["sky to land","sea to sky","land to sea","sea to land",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A piece of copper of mass 20g at a temperature of 110<sup>o<\/sup>C was dropped into a mixture of ice and water at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C. If the final steady temperature of the mixture is 0<sup>o<\/sup>C . Calculate the amount of ice that melted [Specific heat capacity of copper = 0.4 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>k<sup>-1<\/sup>, specific latent heat of fusion of ice = 330Jg<sup><\/sup>]","options":["0.37g","0.60g","2.40g","2.70g",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following factors decreases the rate of evaporation of a liquid?","options":["increase in pressure over the liquid","lowering the boiling point","decreasing in humidity","wind",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"When two waves are superimposed on each other, the following occurrences are possible, except","options":["nodal lins","anti nodal lines","stationary waves","dispersion",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following properties of waves is exclusive to transverse waves?","options":["reflection","interference","diffraction","polarization",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An object of height 2.5cm is places 20cm from a convex mirror of focal length 10cm. Calculate the height of its image","options":["2.5 cm","3.0cm","5.0cm","25.0cm",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A to eater to glass to air to water to glass to air. Given that the refractive index for light passing from air to water is \\(\\frac{4}{3}\\) and air to glass is \\(\\frac{3}{2}\\), calculate the refractive index of glass relative to water","options":["0.50","0.67","0.75","1.13",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An object is placed at a point X between the focal point F and the optical centre C of a diverging lens. If F is the focal point on the other side of the lens, the image of the object is formed between","options":["F and X","X and C","C and F","F and 2F",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An object is placed 10cm from a converging lens of foal length 15cm. Calculate the magnification of the image formed","options":["3.0","1.5","0.6","0.3",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A telescope is said to be in normal adjustment when the","options":["focal length of he objective is greater than that of the eyepiece","focal length of the eyepiece is greater than that of the objective","focal length of the eyepiece is equal to that of the objective","objective focal point coincides wih that of the eyepiece",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The sound heard by a person after the reflection of the sound generated by him is called","options":["reverberation","resonance","echo","audibility",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following sets of coloured light is\/are secondary colours  i. Red, Blue and green  ii. Blue, cyan and magneta  iii. Green, Magenta and yellow, IV Yellow, Cyan and Magenta","options":["i and ii only","ii and iii only","iv only","i, ii and iv only",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"When two like charges are brought together, the potential energy of the system formed will","options":["increase because work is done against the field","increase because work is done by the field","decrease because work is done by the field","decrease because work is done against the field",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Two capacitors, each of capacitance 2\\(\\mu F\\) are connected in parallel. If the p.d across them is 120V, calculate the charge on each capacitor","options":["6.0 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>C","1.2 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>C","2.4 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>C","4.8 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following properties is an advantage of lead-acid accumulator over an alkaline accumulator?","options":["possesses low internal resistance","can be recharges","has shorter life span","possesses high e.m.f",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Six dry cells each of e.m.f. 2.0 and internal resistance of 1.0\\(\\Omega\\) are connected in parallel across a load of 3.0\\(\\Omega\\). Calculate the effective current in the circuit","options":["0.63A","0.50A","0.31A",".22A",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A 120\\(\\Omega\\) resistor dissipates 8 kJ of heat in 20s. Calculate the current through the resistor","options":["5.8A","6.9A","30.0A","33.3A",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"The magnetic relay is a device used for","options":["timing in sports","storing magnetic field","readin the magnitude of magnetic flux","controlling another circuit carrying larger current",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"the core of a transformer is usually laminated in order to","options":["reduce magnetic leakage","reduce eddy current","prevent vibration of the transformer","make magnetic reversal in the core much easier",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following modes is the most economical method of transmitting electrical power over long distances?","options":["alternating current at low voltage and high current","alternating current at high voltage and high current","alternating current at high voltage and low current","direct current at low voltage and high current",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An inductor is connected to a 24V, 50Hz mains supply. If the current through the inductor is 1.5A, calculate the inductance of the inductor (\\(\\pi = \\frac{22}{7}\\))","options":["8.0 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>H","7.5  x 10<sup>o<\/sup>H","1.6  x 10<sup>o<\/sup>H","5.1  x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>H",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"In a R-C circuit","options":["I<sup>rms<\/sup> leads V<sup>rms<\/sup> by 60<sup>o<\/sup>","I<sup>rms<\/sup> slags V<sup>rms<\/sup> by 60<sup>o<\/sup>","V<sup>rms<\/sup> lags I<sup>rms<\/sup> by 90<sup>o<\/sup>","V<sup>rms<\/sup> leads I<sup>rms<\/sup> by 90<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"An atom in an excited state is one whose","options":["potential energy is minimum","potential energy is maximum","electron are in the conduction band","electron have moved to higher energy level",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"A metal with a work function of 3.0ev is irradiated with ultraviolet light of energy 4.0 ev. The kinetic energy of the ejected electron is","options":["1.0eV","3.0eV","4.0eV","7.0eV",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about X-rays is correct? X-rays","options":["are produced when a metal surface is irradiated with ultraviolet light","are produced when a metal target is used to block fast miving electrons","have long wavelengths and are therefoer very penetrating","are not part of the electromagnetic spectrum",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following arrangements of radiations is in the order of decreasing penetrating power?","options":["\\(\\alpha, \\beta, \\gamma\\)","\\(\\alpha, \\gamma, \\beta\\)","\\(\\gamma, \\beta, \\alpha\\)","\\(\\beta, \\gamma,  \\alpha\\)",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following radiations emitted in radioactive decay has momentum, a fairly high penetrating power and is deflected by a magnet?","options":["alpha particles","beta particle","gamma radiation `","X-radiation",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2012"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct?","options":["molecules of ice, water and water vapour have equal intermolecular distances","molecules of ice, water and water vapour do not differ in the structure of their molecules","molecules of water vapour attract each other with forces far less than the forces of attraction between water molecules","water is less compressible than water vapour",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The density P of a spherical ball of diameter d and mass m is given by","options":["P = \\(\\frac{3m}{4 \\pi d^3}\\)","p = 4\\(\\pi md^3\\)","p = \\(\\frac{6m}{\\pi d^3}\\)","p = \\(\\frac{3m}{2 \\pi d^3}\\)",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A metal rod of density 7000 kgm<sup>-3<\/sup> and cross-sectional area of 0.001257m<sup>2<\/sup> has a mass of 1.76kg. Calculate its length.","options":["0.20m","0.25m","0.40m","0.50m",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The pressure in a liquid","options":["is the same at all points in the liquid","decreases with depth","is the same in all directions at a given point","is equal to the atmospheric pressure",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The property of a fluid that is used to determine its suitability as a lubricant is its","options":["capillarity","viscocity","surface tension","relative density",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The area under a velocity-time graph represents","options":["final velocity attained","distance covered","acceleration","workdone",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"In the absence of gravitational force, the weight of the body is","options":["its mass","zero","its density","its volume",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following propeties is not considered in choosing mercury as a thermomemetric liquid?","options":["density","expansivity","conductivity","opacity",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A stone of mass 300g is released from rest from the top of a bulding of height 100m. Determine the kinetic energy gained by the stone when it is a quarter way down from the point of release.[g = 10 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["750.0J","225.0J","75.0J","22.5J",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A body of mass 120g placed at the 10cm mark on a uniform metre rule makes the rule settle horizontally on a fulcrum places at 35cm mark. Calculate the mass of the rule","options":["60g","80g","120g","200g",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Two simple pendulum A and B of equal lengths and of masses 5g and 20g respectively are located in the same environment. The periods T<sub>A<\/sub> and T<sub>B<\/sub> of their respective oscillations are related by the equations","options":["T<sub>A<\/sub> = 4T<sub>B<\/sub>","T<sub>A<\/sub> = \\(\\frac{1}{4} T_B\\)","T<sub>A<\/sub> = T<sub>B<\/sub>","T<sub>A<\/sub> = 5T<sub>B<\/sub>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"An object of mass 5.0 kg moves with a velocity of 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Calculate its momentum.","options":["50.0 kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","15.0 kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0 kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.5 kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A coin is pushed from the edge of a laboratory bench with a horizontal velocity of 15.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. If the height of the bench from the floor is 1.5m, calculate the distance from the foot of the bench to the point of impact with the floor [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["0.75m","2.25m","8.22m","15.00m",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following statements correctly defines a simple machine? A device","options":["that can produce electric current","which can only carry people from one place to another","with which work can be done easily","which changes the state of rest or of uniform motion of an object",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The radius of a wheel is 30.0 cm and that of its axle is 6.0cm. Calculate the effort required to lift a load of 120.0N using this machine. Assuming 100% efficiency","options":["600.0N","40.0N","24.0N","20.0N",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A hypsometer is used for determining","options":["steam point","relative humidity","ice point","relative density",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following equations shows how how the linear expansivity (\\(\\alpha\\)) and the cubic expansivity (\\(\\gamma\\)) of a material are related?","options":["\\(\\gamma = \\alpha\\)","\\(\\gamma  = 1 - \\alpha\\)","\\(\\gamma  = 2 \\alpha\\)","\\(\\gamma  = 3 \\alpha\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about anomalous expansion of water are correct?  i. There is contraction between 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 4<sup>o<\/sup>C.  ii. There is expansion between 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 100<sup>o<\/sup>C.  iii. The volume is minimum at 4<sup>o<\/sup>C.  iv. The volume is maximum at 4<sup>o<\/sup>C","options":["i and ii only","ii and iii only","i and iii only","ii and iv only",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following assumptions is not valid for an ideal gas ?","options":["molecules of a particular gas are identical","molecules moves freely throughout the volume of the container","force of attraction between molecules is negligible","molecules move at constant speed between collisions",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A body is pulled over a distance of 500m by a force of 20N. If the power developed is o.4 kW, calculate the time interval during which the force is applied","options":["0.2s","2.5s","25.0s","250.0s",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A metal of mass 200g at a temperature of 100<sup>o<\/sup>C is placed in 100g of water at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C in a container of negligible heat capacity. If the final steady temperature is 30<sup>o<\/sup>C, calculate the specific heat capacity of the metal. [specific heat capacity of the water is 4200 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["150 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","300 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","320 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","1960 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Ether produces a cooling effect when it is poured on the hand because it has","options":["low conductivity","high conductivity","high latent heat of vaporization","low latent heat of vaporization",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the image formed by a plane mirror is not correct?","options":["it is laterally inverted","it has unit magnifiation","it is formed by actual intersection of rays","its distance from the mirror is equal to that of the object from the mirror",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The image formed by a convex mirror is always","options":["real, erect and diminished","real, inverted and diminished","virtual, inverted and diminished","virtual, erect and diminshed",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A ray undergoes a minimum deviation at 40<sup>o<\/sup> when it is incident on equilateral triangular glass prism. Calculate the refractive index of the prism","options":["1.48","1.50","1.53","1.67",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Total internal reflection occurs in an optical prism when light rays","options":["travel from the prism into an optically denser medium","are incident in the prism at an angle greater than the critical angle","are incident normally in the prism","travel from the prism to the air",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The speed of light in a certain medium is V while its speed in a vacuum is C. The absolute refractive index of the medium is","options":["C + V","\\(\\frac{C}{V}\\)","\\(\\frac{V}{C}\\)","C - V",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"An object is placed 20.0cm in front of a converging lens of focal length 15.0cm. Calculate its image distance","options":["1.3cm","8.6cm","35.0cm","60.0cm",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Presbyopia is a defect of the eye resulting from","options":["weak ciliary muscles","short eyeball","loss of sphericity of the lens","long eyeball",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The focal length of the eye-piece of an astronomical telescope is f<sub>1<\/sub>, while the focal length of the object is f<sub>2<\/sub>. Fro normal adjustment, the angular magnification is given by","options":["\\(\\frac{f_2}{f_1}\\)","1 - \\(\\frac{f_2}{f_1}\\)","\\(\\frac{f_2}{f_1}\\) - 1","\\(\\frac{f_1}{f_2}\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"two sound waves have frequencies of 12Hz and 10Hz. Calculate their beats period","options":["0.5s","1.0s","1.2s","2.0s",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The main difference between echo and reverberation is that","options":["reverberation is reflected sound while echo is refracted sound","the time interval between incident sound and reflecte sound is shorter for reverbration","the amplitude of an echo is greater","reverberation is from acoustic speakers while echo comes from clifts",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the electromagnetic waves is correct?","options":["radio waves have longer frequencies than x-rays","x-rays have the longest wavelength","some of the waves travel at 3.0 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","white light occupies a region beyond ultraviolet rays",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The correct relationship between \"G\" and \"g\" in a gravitational field is given by the equation (Where the symbols have their usual meanings)","options":["g = \\(\\frac{GM}{R}\\)","g = \\(\\frac{GM}{R^2}\\)","g = \\(\\frac{GM^2}{R}\\)","g = \\(\\frac{GM^2}{R^2}\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The capacitance of a parallel-plate capacitor","options":["decreases when the seperation between the plate decreases","increases when the optential difference between the plates is increased","is greater without a dielectric material between the plates than with a dielectric","is greater with a dielectric between the plates than without a dielectric.",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"When the pointed end of an uncharged optical pin is brought near the cap cf a positively charged electroscope, it is observed that the gold","options":["collapse slowly","vibrate","are not affected","diverge rapidly",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following substances does not conduct electricity?","options":["graphite","glass","sulphuric acid","table salt solution",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The unit of capacitance is","options":["farad","coulomb","henry","ohms",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"An ammeter with a full scale deflection of 10mA has an internal resistance 0.5\\(\\Omega\\). calculate the resistance of the shunt required to adapt it to read up to 3A","options":["0.0167\\(\\Omega\\)","0.0130\\(\\Omega\\)","0.0250\\(\\Omega\\)","0.1000\\(\\Omega\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The resistivity, \\(\\mathit{P}\\), of a material of length l, cross-sectional area A, resistance R, is given by the equation","options":["\\(\\mathit{P} = \\frac{RA}{l}\\)","\\(\\mathit{P} = \\frac{l}{RA}\\)","\\(\\mathit{P} = \\frac{Rl}{A}\\)","\\(\\mathit{P} = \\frac{R}{Al}\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"A wire of length 30cm is moved with a speed of 2ms<sup>-1<\/sup> at right angles to a magnetic field of flux density 0.4T. calculate the emf induced in the wire","options":["0.15V","0.24V","2.70V","24.00V",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following practices will lead to losses in electrical power transmission?","options":["using transmission cables of large diameter","transmitting at high voltage and low current","transmitting at relatively low voltage and high current","using a set-up transformer at the production end",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"For photoelectric emission, the threshold frequency is the","options":["maximum frequency of incident radiation that will eject elecrons","minimum fraquency of incident radiation required to eject elecrons","frequency which results in the emission of the greater number of electrons","fraquency whch impacts greatest kinetic energy to emitte electrons",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following properties is not applicable to X-rays? They","options":["travel in straight lines","travel with the speed of light","are deflected by magnetic field","affect photographic films",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Uranium-234 disintegrated to form Thorium-230 by emitting","options":["alpha particles","gamma rays","beta negative rays","beta positive rays",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"The change in mass of fuel during a nuclear reaction is 2.0 x 10<sup>-27<\/sup> kg. Calculate the amount of energy released. (Speed of light = 2.0 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["1.8 x 10<sup>-10<\/sup>J","9.0 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>J","6.0 x 10<sup>-19<\/sup>J","1.2 x 10<sup>-45<\/sup>J",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Nuclear fusion is not used as a source of enegy because","options":["very high temperature is needed for the reaction","the fuel for the reaction is not easy to obtain","less energy is released","the reaction is too slow",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"Which of the following properties of a long steel bar would alter if the bar were melted, recast into a cube and allowed to cool to its original temperature?","options":["sensity","volume","specific heat capacity","electrical resistance",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following instruments is best for measuring the diameter of a thin constantan wire?","options":["callipers","metre rule","micometer screw guage","vernier callipers",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"What is the density of a fuel of relative density 0.72? [Density of water = 1000kg m<sup>-3<\/sup>]","options":["72 kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>","720 kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>","7200 kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>","72000 kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The types of motion which a cylindrical drum rolling down an inclined plane undergoes are","options":["circular and translational","rotational and translational","rotational and circular","rectilinear and circular",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about static friction is correct? It","options":["is independent of the nature of the surface in contact","depends on the area of surface in contact","depends on the relative motion between the surface in contact","depends on the weight of the moving body",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about moving particle is correct?","options":["if the resultant force acting on the particle is zero, then it is in dynamic equillibrium","If the resultant force acting on the acting on the particle is greater than zero, then it is moving with a uniform velocity","the rate of change of its momentum with time tales place in a direction opposite to that of its motion","the particle falling freely covers equal distances in equal time interval",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Two cars X and Y travelling in opposite directions along the same high way at uniform velocities 110 kmh<sup>-1<\/sup> and 90kmh<sup>-1<\/sup> respectively pass each other at a certain point. The velocity of X relative to Y at the time they pass each other is","options":["200 kmh<sup>-1<\/sup>","100 kmh<sup>-1<\/sup>","40 kmh<sup>-1<\/sup>","20 kmh<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The average speed of an object is determined by dividing the sum of its initial and final speeds by two only when the acceleration is","options":["changing","uniform","increasing","decreasing",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"a body is projected horizonatlly from the top of a cliff 45m above the ground. if the body lands at a distance 30m from the foot of the cliff, calculate the speed of projection. [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["10ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","15ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","20ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","30ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following statements best describes a rigid body? A body which","options":["is not equally deformed","when deformed regains it shape","is brittle","when deformed remains deformed",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"simple harmonic oscillator has a period of 0.02s and amplitude of 0.25m. Calculate the speed in ms<sup>-1<\/sup> at the centre of the oscillation","options":["125\\(\\pi\\)","25.00\\(\\pi\\)","100.00 \\(\\pi\\)","400.00\\(\\pi\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A vertical string, suspended from a fixed point and having a small mass attached to the free end is set into oscillations. Which of the following statements about the system are correct?  i. The potential energy of the mass is a minimum at the middle of the swing   ii. Its kinetic energy is a maximum at the middle of the swing   iii. The sum of the potential and kinetic energies is constant throughout the swing","options":["i,ii and iii","i and ii only","ii and iii only","i and iii only",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A moving body of mass 25.0kg undergoes a uniform retardation of 20.0ms<sup>-2<\/sup>. Calculate the magnitude of the retardating force","options":["1.25N","8.00N","45.00N","500.00N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following sources of energy is\/are exhausible?  i. Solar  ii. Fossil fuels  iii. Tidal power","options":["i, ii and iii","i and ii only","i and iii only","ii and iii only",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"a machine is said to be a third class lever when the","options":["load is between the fulcrum and effort","fulcrum is between the effort and the load","effort is between the fulcrum and load","fulcrum is directly below the load",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"a thermometer records 680 mmHg at steam point and 440 mmHg at ice point. The temperature it records at 380 mmHg is","options":["-25<sup>o<\/sup>C","-20<sup>o<\/sup>C","20<sup>o<\/sup>C","25<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The advantages of the thermoelectric thermometer include the following characteristics except that it","options":["can measure rapidly changing temperatures","can measure high and low temperature","can measure high and low temperature almost at a point","is fairly sensitive",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In a thermos flask, heat loss by radiation is minimizes by the","options":["silvered surfaces","vacuum within the doubled walls","plastic stopper","cork support",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The pressure P, volume V, and absolute temperature T of a given mass of an ideal gas change simultaneously. Which of the followng equations is correct about the gas?","options":["PV = \\(\\frac{constant}{T}\\)","\\(\\frac{P}{T} = Constant\\)","\\(\\frac{P}{V} = \\frac{constant}{T}\\)","\\(\\frac{I}{T} = \\frac{constant}{PV}\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Specific heat capacity 36.4 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup> of a body means that when 26.4J of heat energy is supplied to a body of","options":["mass 100kg the temperature rises by 1k","mass 1kg, the temperature by 1000K","mass 1kg, the temperature rises by 1kg","mass 100kg, the temperature rises by 1000k",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"An electric drill rated 400W is used to drill a hole in copper of mass 400g in 20s. Calculate the rise in temperature if all the heat produced is absorbed by the copper. [specific heat capacity of copper = 400Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["100<sup>o<\/sup>C","75<sup>o<\/sup>C","50<sup>o<\/sup>C","45<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A solid of mass 0.5kg initially at 50<sup>o<\/sup>C melts at 60<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate the quantity of heat required to melt it completely. [specific heat capacity of the solid =2.0KJ kg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>][Specific latent heat of fusion of solid =1.0 KJ kg<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["1500J","10000J","10500J","15000J",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Dew point is not affected by","options":["temperature","wind","the amount of water vapour in the atmosphere","atmospheric pressure",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A certain wave has a speed of 20ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. If the frequency of the wave is 0.25Hz, calculate the distance between successive crests of the wave","options":["5.0m","40.0m","50.0m","80.0m",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The ability of a wave to spread around corners is called","options":["polarisation","dispersion","diffraction","reflection",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The following devices use plane mirrors in their operations, except","options":["periscope","sextant","kaleidoscope","binoculars",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"When an object is placed at the principal focus of a concave mirror, the location of the image formed is","options":["between principal focus and pole","between principal focus and centre of curvature","at infinity","at centre of curvature",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A ray of light travels from air to water. The refeactive index of water is given by the expression","options":["\\(\\frac{\\text{velocity in water}}{\\text{velocity in air}}\\)","\\(\\frac{\\text{sine of angle of refraction}}{\\text{sine of angle of incidence}}\\)","\\(\\frac{\\text{apparent depth}}{\\text{real depth }}\\)","\\(\\frac{\\text{wavelength in air}}{\\text{wavelength in water}}\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A lens that is thinner at the middle and thicher at the edges is","options":["diverging","converging","plano-convex","converging meniscus",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following electromagnetic wave has the longest wavelength?","options":["radio-waves","gamma rays","infrared waves","ultraviolet rays",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The amplitude of a sound wave determines its","options":["frequency","quality","loudness","pitch",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"As the air column of length L in an air pipe decreases, the frequency of the sationary wave emitted","options":["decreases","increases","varies as L<sup>2<\/sup>","varies as \\(\\sqrt{L}\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A positively charged glass rod is placed near the cap of a positively charged electroscope. The divergence of the leaf is observed to","options":["decrease","increase","remain the same","increase and collapse immediately",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Capacitors are used in the following devices, except","options":["water pumping machines","ceiling fans","electric irons","television sets",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A galvanometer of internal resistance 50\\(\\Omega\\) and full scale deflection of 20 mA is converted into a voltmeter by connecting a resistor of resistance 1950\\(\\Omega\\) in series to it. Calculate the maximum voltage that can be read by the voltmeter","options":["20V","30V","38V","40V",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In the wiring of houses, the fuse is connected to the wire coloured","options":["blue","brown","yellow","yellow and green",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following factors does not affect the electric resistance of wire?","options":["length","mass","temperature","cross-sectional area",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Which of the following factors will increase the sensitivity of moving coil meter?","options":["strong spring","low numbers of turns","small area of coil","soft iron core",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In order to prevent bar magnets from losing their strength, they are stored wih keepers such that the two bars are placed with","options":["like poles facing each other and the keepers placed between them","like poles facing each other and the keepers placed between them","unlike poles facing each other and the keepers placed at their ends","unlike poles facing each other and the keepers placed between them",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The energy, E stored in an inductor of inductance L when current I passes through it is given by the equation","options":["E = \\(\\frac{1}{2} LI^2\\)","E = LI<sup>2<\/sup>","E \\(\\frac{1}{2}LI\\)","E = \\(\\frac{1}{2} L^2I\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"The resonant frequency of an a.c circuit is 1000 kHz. If each of the capacitance and inductance in the circuit is reduced by 50%, and no other changes are made, the resonant frequency will become","options":["250kHz","750kHz","1000kHz","2000kHz",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Eddy currents can be reduced by","options":["using coil of high resistance","winding the coil on a soft iron core","creating holes in the metal plates","using coil of low resistance",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"an electron moves with a speed of 2.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup> in a straight line. Calculate the wave length of the electron wave. [mass of an electron = 9.1 x 10<sup>-31<\/sup> kg][Planck's constant = 6.6 x 10<sup>-34<\/sup>Js]","options":["3.63 x 10<sup>-19<\/sup>m","6.51 x 10<sup>-9<\/sup>m","4.24 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>m","7.25 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>m",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Oxidation of the filament in a light bulb is prevented by the introduction of","options":["hydrogen","oxygen","argon","mercury vapour",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In a cathode ray tube, the function of the x-plates is to","options":["deflect the electron beam horizontally","deflect the electron beam vertically","reflect the electron beam","generate sinusoid waves",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"A nuclide represented as \\(^{70}_{32}X\\) has a neutron-proton ratio of","options":["0.5","0.8","1.2","1.5",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"Neutrons are used to induce artificial radioactivity because they","options":["are energetic","have no charge","have no mass","are ionizing",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"In which of the following states of matter do the molecules vibrate about their mean positions?","options":["liquids only","solids only","liquids and gasses only","solids, liquids and gases",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following properties of a steel bar can be measured in terms of the dimension of length only?","options":["weight","density","pressure","volume",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"In a hydraulic press, a force of 40N is applied to the smaller priston of area 10cm<sup>2<\/sup>. If the area of the larger piston is 200cm<sup>2<\/sup>, calculate the force obtained","options":["800N","500N","80N`","50N",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A body of volume 0.046m<sup>3<\/sup> is immersed in a liquid of density 980kgm<sup>-3<\/sup> with \\(\\frac{3}{4}\\) of its volume submerged. Calculate the upthrust on the body. [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["11.27N","33.81N","112.70N","338.10N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following types of types of motion will be produced when a pair of equal and opposite non-collinear parallel forces acts on a body?","options":["vibrational motion","random motion","translational motion","rotational motion",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A body moving in a circle at constant speed has  i. a velocity tangent to the circle  ii. a constant kinetic energy  ii. an acceleration directed towards the circmference of the circle  ii. an acceleration directed towards the circumference of the circle. Which of the statements above are correct?","options":["i and ii only","ii and iii","ii and iii only","i and iii only",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A moving body accelerates when it","options":["changes its direction at constant speed","mauntains a constant linear speed","covers equal distances in equal times in a straight line","is acted upon by balanced forces",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The following properties of a solid are measured on earth  i. weight  ii. specific heat capacity  iii. density. Which of the properties will hav a different value if measured in space?","options":["i only","ii only","iii only","ii and iii only",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Two forces 6N and 8N, act eastwards and northwards respectively on a body. Calculate the magnitude of their equilibrant","options":["2N","7N","10N","14N",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The period of a simple pendulum of length 80.0cm was found to have doubled when the length of the pendulum was increased by X. Calculate X.","options":["26.7cm","40.0cm","160.0cm","240.0cm",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A body of mass 5kg movimg with a velocity of 30ms<sup>-1<\/sup> due east is suddenly hit by another body and changes its velocity to 50ms<sup>-1<\/sup> in the same direction. Calculate the magnitude of the impulse received.","options":["100Ns","150Ns","250Ns","400Ns",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Electric energy is measured in","options":["ampere","coulomb","kilowatt-hour","kilowatt",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A stone of mass 0.5kg is dropped from a height of 12m. Calculate its maximum kinetic energy. [g = 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["3.0J","6.0J","30.0j","60.0J",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A machine of efficiency 80% is used to lift a box. If the effort applied by the machine is twice the weight of the box. Calculate the velocity ratio of the machine","options":["0.50","0.63","0.80","1.60",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A faulty thermometer registers 102.5<sup>o<\/sup>C t 100<sup>o<\/sup>C. If the thermometer has no zero hour, what will it register at 55<sup>o<\/sup>C?","options":["54.6<sup>o<\/sup>C","55.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","56.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","56.4<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A rod of initial lenght 2m at a temperature of 25<sup>o<\/sup>C is heated to 80<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate the increase in length of the rod if its linear expansivity is 4.0 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","options":["0.26m","0.44m","0.53m","0.84m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"as a bicycle Tyre was being pumped up, it was noticed that contrary to Boyle's law the volume increased as the pressure increased. The best explanation of this is that Boyle's law is only true for","options":["ideal gases","a fixed mass of gas","a mixture of gases","a gas at variable temperature",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"It takes 4 minutes to boil a quantity of water using an electrical heating coil. How long will it take to boil the same quantity of water using the same coil if the current is doubled? [Neglect any external heat losses]","options":["8 minutes","4 minutes","2 minutes","1 minute",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"When table salt is added to ice, the melting point of the ice","options":["is raised","is lowered","remains unchanged","is first raised, then lowered",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following is used to measure relative humidity?","options":["hydrometer","barometer","hypsometer","hygrometer",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following factors affect the rate of evaporation of a liquid?  i. Exposed surface area  ii Temperature of the surroundings  iii. Thermal capacity of the liquid  iv. Relative humidity of the surroundings","options":["ii and iii only","ii, iii and iv only","i, iii and iv only","i, ii amd iv only",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The maximum displacement of a vibrating tunning fork is its","options":["amplitude","frequency","period","wavelength",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A boat is rocked by waves of speed 30ms<sup>-1<\/sup> whose successive crest are 10m apart. Calculate the rate at which the boat recieves the waves","options":["30s<sup>-1<\/sup>","10s<sup>-1<\/sup>","3s<sup>-1<\/sup>","1s<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following waves is not transverse","options":["light waves","sound waves","sea waves","radio waves",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Light travelling through a small pinhole usually does not make a shadow with a distinct sharp edge because of","options":["diffraction","inteference","reflection","refraction",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The angle of incidence of a ray of light on a plane mirror is 55<sup>o<\/sup>. Determine the angle between the reflected ray and the mirror","options":["35<sup>o<\/sup>","45<sup>o<\/sup>","55<sup>o<\/sup>","110<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A concave mirror forms a magnified and errect image only when the object is placed","options":["at the centre of curvature","at the focus","between the focus and the pole of the mirror","beyound the radius of curvature",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A thin lens is placed 50cm from an illustrated object. The image produced has linear magnification of \\(\\frac{1}{4}\\). Calculate the power of the lens in dioptres","options":["2.5D","5.0D","10.0D","25.0D",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following characteristics of light determines its colour?","options":["velocity","wavelength","amplitude","intensity",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a part of the electro-magnetic spectrum?","options":["x-rays","microwaves","infrared radiation","alpha rays",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Sound interference is necessary to produce the phenomenon of","options":["beats","doppler effect","acoustic resonance","echo",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A satellite in circular motion around the earth does not have","options":["a gravitational force acting on it","a uniform velocity","an acceleration","a centripetal force acting on it",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"When a conductor mounted on an insulating stand is charged and left for sometime, the conductor eventually loses all its charges. This is because the","options":["electric charges evaporate from the surface of the conductor","charges are connected to earth","charges on the conductor are neutralized by opposite charges from the surrounding air","charges ionize the surrounding air",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An isolated metal sphere of radius R, carrying an electric charge Q, is situated in the medium of relative permitivity, E<sup>r<\/sup>. A test charge is placed at a point p, distance r from the surface of the sphere. Let E<sup>o<\/sup> represent the permitivity of free space. The electric potential at p is given by the expression","options":["\\(\\frac{Q}{4 \\pi E_o E_r}\\)","\\(\\frac{Q}{4 \\pi E_o E_r (R +r)}\\)","\\(\\frac{Q}{4 \\pi E_o E_r(R - r)}\\)","\\(\\frac{Q}{4 \\pi E_o E_rR}\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An isolated metal sphere of radius R, carrying an electric charge Q, is situated in the medium of relative permitivity, E<sub>r<\/sub>. A test charge is placed at a point p, distance r from the surface of the sphere. Let E<sub>o<\/sub> represent the permitivity of free space. The magnitude of the electric field intensity at P is given by the expression","options":["\\(\\frac{Q}{4 \\pi E_o E_r r^2}\\)","\\(\\frac{Q}{4 \\pi E_o E_r(R + r)^2}\\)","\\(\\frac{Q}{4 \\pi E_o E_r(R - r)^2}\\)","\\(\\frac{Q}{4 \\pi E_o E_rR^2}\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A resistor of resistance R is connected to a battery of negligible internal resistance. If a siilar resistor is connected in series with it the","options":["effective resistance of the circuit is halved","total power dissipated is doubled","total current in the circuit is halved","terminal voltage is halved",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A cell of e.m.f. 1.5V is connected in series with a resistor of resistance 3.0\\(\\Omega\\). A voltmeter connected across the cell registers 0.9V. Calculate the internal resistance of the cell","options":["2.0\\(\\Omega\\).","3.0\\(\\Omega\\).","5.0\\(\\Omega\\).","6.0\\(\\Omega\\).",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A wire of resistivity 4.40 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>\\(\\Omega\\) cm has a cross sectional area of 7.50 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup> cm<sup>2<\/sup>. Calculate the length of the wire that will be required to make a 4.0\\(\\Omega\\) resistor","options":["82.50 cm","68.18cm","15.90cm","11.95cm",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A battery of e.m.f. 12.0V and internal resistance0.5\\(\\Omega\\) is connected to 1.5\\(\\Omega\\) and 4.0\\(\\Omega\\) series resistor. Calculate the terminal voltage of the battery.","options":["13.0V","11.0V","3.0V","1.0V",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"If the direction of the curent in a straight wire is reversed, the magnetic field","options":["remains the same","becomes parallel to the wire","ceases to exist","is oppositely directed",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An inductor of inductance 1.0H is connected in series with a capacitor of capacitance 2.0\\(\\mu F\\) in an a.c. circuit. to resonate","options":["112.5Hz","225.0Hz","323.5Hz","707.1Hz",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An ammeter connected to an a.c circuit records 5.5. The peak current in the circuit is","options":["7.8A","7.1A","3.8A","3.5A",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Two isotopes of uranium are designed as \\(^{238}U\\) and \\(^{235}U\\). The numbers 238 and 235 represent their","options":["atomic numbers","nucleon numbers","proton numbers","neutron numbers",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The main difference between between x-rays and \\(\\gamma-rays\\) lies in their","options":["ionizing ability","absorption rate","mode of production","mode of propagation",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An electron of mass 9.1 x 10<sup>-31<\/sup> kg moves with a speed of 10<sup>7<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Calculate the wavelength of the associates wave[h = 6.6 x 10<sup>-34<\/sup>Js]","options":["9.0 x 10<sup>-24<\/sup>m","4.55 x 10<sup>-17<\/sup>m","7.25 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>m","6.20 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>m",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An observer heard the sound of thunder 5.8s after the lightning flash was seen. How far was he from the source? [Speed of sound in air = 330ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["957m","1914m","3828m","8700m","17400m"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The space between the two walls of a vacuum flask is completely evacuated to reduce heat loss by","options":["condensation","conduction","convection","evaporation","radiation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Determine the value of x from the nuclear reaction below,<br>\r\n<br>\r\n\\(^{222}_{86}Rn\\) \u2192 \\(^{x}_{88}Ra\\) + 2\u03b2 + energy","options":["220","222","224","226","228"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the pressure in a liquid is NOT correct? It","options":["acts in all direction","changes with the material of the container","is the same at all points in the same horizontal plane","varies with the density of the liquid","varies with the depth of the liquid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"In which of the following fields is repulsion NOT experienced?","options":["Electrical only","Gravitational only","Magnetic only","Magnetic and electrical","Magnetic and gravitational"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A ball of mass 100g falls from a height of 5m onto a concrete floor and rebounds to a height of 3m. Calculate the energy lost. (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["2J","20J","100J","1000J","2000J"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Two forces of magnitude 8N and 4N act at right angle to each other. The angle between the resultant and the 8N force is","options":["23.9\u00b0","26.6\u00b0","29.5\u00b0","60.0\u00b0","63.4\u00b0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The defect of the eye lens which occurs as a result of weak ciliary muscles is called","options":["astigmatism","hypermetropia","myopia","presbyopia","spherical aberration"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following pairs of phenomena helps in the resolution of the wave-particle paradox of matter?","options":["Compton effect and thermionic emission","Electron diffraction and refraction","emission and absorption of light","Interference and polarization","Reflection and photoelectric effect"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following phenomena is responsible for the spherical shape of soap bubbles?","options":["Adhesion","Capillarity","Cohesion","Osmosis","Surface tension"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A plane progressive wave is represented by the equation y = 0.2sin (200\u03c0t - 0.5.x) where x and y are measured in cm and t in s. What is the frequency of the wave?","options":["0.5Hz","4.0Hz","10.0Hz","100.0Hz","200.0Hz"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A stone is thrown with a speed of 10ms at an angle of 30\u00b0 to the horizontal, Calculate its time of flight, (g = 10ms<sup>2<\/sup>)","options":["0.5s","1.0s","1.7s","2.0s","3.4s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A projectile attains its maximum height when the angle of projection is","options":["30\u00b0","45\u00b0","60\u00b0","75\u00b0","90\u00b0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Inertia is the property of a body which makes the body to","options":["accelerate","be reluctant to move when at rest","experience friction when moving","move randomly","retard"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The term torque means","options":["the equilibrant of two concurrent forces","the moment of a force about an ads","the resultant of several forces acting on a body in equilibrium","two coplanar forces at right angle to each other","two equal and opposite forces whose lines of action do not coincide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A ball of mass 0.1kg moving with velocity of 20ms<sup>-1<\/sup>  is hit by a force which acts on it for 0.02s. If the ball moves off in the opposite direction with a velocity of 25ms<sup>-1<\/sup> , calculate the magnitude of the force.","options":["25N","100N","125N","225N","250N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An object of mass 2kg moves for 5s with a uniform velocity of 10ms. What is the magnitude of its acceleration in ms<sup>-2<br>\r\n<\/sup>?","options":["zero","2.5","10","12.5","100"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"In the electrical method of making a magnet, the polar the magnet formed depends on the","options":["amount of current passed","direction of the current","nature of the material used","orientation of the magnetic material in space","size of the magnetic material"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Two images Y and X are formed by a plane mirror and a convex mirror respectively. Which of the following is correct about their characteristics?","options":["Both are inverted","The magnification of Y is greater than one while that of X is one","The magnification of Y is one while that of X is less than one","Y is inverted while X is erect","Y is real while X is virtual."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The electric potential at a distance d from a point charge q in air of permittivity e<sub>o<\/sub> is expressed as","options":["q<sup>2<\/sup> \u00f7 4\u03c0e<sub>o<\/sub>d","q<sup>2<\/sup> \u00f7 4\u03c0e<sub>o<\/sub>","q \u00f7 4\u03c0e<sub>o<\/sub>d<sup>2<\/sup>","q \u00f7 4\u03c0e<sub>o<\/sub>d","q \u00f7 4\u03c0e<sub>o<\/sub><sup>2<\/sup>d"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The work done in extending a spring by 40mm is 1.52J. Calculate the elastic\u2019constant of the spring.","options":["38.8 Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","60.8 Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","190.0 Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","1900.0 Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>","3800.0 Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct about volatile liquids? They have","options":["low boiling point","Low evaporating rate","high conductivity","high density","high viscosity"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A transformer has an efficiency of 92.5%. the ratio number of turns in the primary coil to that in the secondary coil is 128 : 45. If the current passing through the secondary coil is 9.0A, calculate the current passing through the primary-coil.","options":["2.93A","3.16A","3.42A","25.60A","27.68A"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An immersion heater is rated 1500W. How long does it take the heater to raise the temperature of 1 kg of water by 30\u00b0C? (Assume heat lost to the surrounding is negligible, Specific heat capacity of water 4200Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["84s","112s","130s","168s","280s"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The equation P<sup>x<\/sup>V<sup>y<\/sup>T<sup>z<\/sup> = Constant is Charles\u2019 law if","options":["x = 0, y = 1 and z = -1","x = 0, y = -1 and z = 1","x = 1, y = 1 and z = 0","x = 1, y = 1 and z = -1","x = 1, y = 1 and z = 1"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"When a resistor of resistance R is connected across a.c. the terminal p.d. of the cell is reduced to three-quart its e.m.f. The cell\u2019s internal resistance in terms of R is","options":["\\(\\frac{R}{4}\\)","\\(\\frac{R}{3}\\)","\\(\\frac{R}{2}\\)","2\\(\\frac{R}{3}\\)","R"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following cells does not require a dipolar for effective and efficient delivery of current?","options":["Daniel cell","Dry Leclanche cell","Nickel-iron accumulator","Voltaic cell","Wet Leclanche cell"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about water is NOT correct?","options":["Pure water freezes at 0\u00b0C under normal pressure","The volume of a given mass of water at 0\u00b0 is less than its volume at 4\u00b0C","Water boils at a definite temperature","Water evaporates at all temperatures","Water has its maximum density at 4\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A body accelerating will have a constant speed if it is","options":["falling from a height","in equilibrium","moving in a circular path","moving in a straight line","oscillating"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A sound wave from a ship is received 8.4s later. What is the depth of the sea? [Speed of sound in water 1500ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["0.179km","0.357km","3.150km","6.300km","12.600km"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about a gas is NOT correct?","options":["It has no definite shape","It is compressible","Its molecules are closely packed","Its molecules gain kinetic energy when heated","Its molecules move about randomly"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A body executing simple harmonic motion has an angular speed of 2\u03c0 radians. Its period of oscillation is (\u03c0 3.14).","options":["0.05s","1.00s","2.00s","3.14s","6.28s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Which of the following pairs of musical instruments produce sound due to the vibration of air column?","options":["Bell and piano","Guitar and flute","Trumpet and drum","Trumpet and flute","Violin and organ"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"An effort P applied at one end of a crowbar just overcomes the resistance W at the lid of a tin. The mechanical advantage of the crowbar is expressed as","options":["W + P","P - W","\\(\\frac{w}{p}\\)","\\(\\frac{p}{w}\\)","wp"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"The phenomenon of photoelectric effect is used in the following EXCEPT","options":["automatic doors","bugler alarm","electric fire alarm","sound production from film tracks","television cameras"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"Electric charges on the surface of a conductor would be most evenly distributed if the shape of the conductor is","options":["conical","cubical","cylindrical","parabolic","spherical"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"A series RLC circuit is said to resonate, when","options":["capacitive reactance is zero","conductance is maximum","current is minimum","impedance is minimum","inductive reactance is zero"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"If the air inside a rigid box is heated, the   i, average speed of the molecules increases  ii. pressure of the air increases  iii. average separation of the molecule increases. Which of the statements above are correct?","options":["i and ii only","ii and iii only","i and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following sets of quantities is fundamental?","options":["length, mass and time","speed, length and time","speed, mass and distance","distance, speed and time",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"which of the following statements about Archimedes' principle is correct? The upthrust on a body is a measure of the","options":["mass of fluid displaced","weight of the body","volume of the body","weight of the fluid displaced",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following is\/are in random motion?  i. Pollen grains in water  ii. The molecules of hydrogen gas  ii. Fine chalk particles floating in air","options":["i and ii only","i and iii only","ii and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A car travelling with a uniform velocity of 30ms<sup>-1<\/sup> along a horizontal road overcomes a constant frictional force of 600N. Calculate the power of the engine of the car","options":["18kW","20kW","180kW","200kW",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A rectangular block of dimensions 2.0m x 1.0m x 0.5m weighs 200N. calculate the maximum pressure exerted by the block on a horizontal floor.","options":["100Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","200Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","300Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","400Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A very sensitive spring balance was used to determine the weight of an object at the north pole. When the same spring balance was used to measure the weight of the same object at the equator, it was found to reduce. The explanation for this observation is that","options":["it is very hot at the equator","the spring balance has expanded","the acceleration of free fall due to gravity varies with location","the mass of the body is reduced",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The mass attached to a string is moving in a circular path. If the speed is doubled, the tension in the string will be","options":["doubled","halved","four times as great","one-fourth as much",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"An object of mass 2kg moving with a velocity 3ms<sup>-1<\/sup>1 collides head-on with another object of mass 1kg moving in the opposite direction with a velocity of 4ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. If the objects stick together after collision, calculate their common speed.","options":["0.60ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.67ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.00ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","3.33<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A ball is dropped and it hits the floor at a point A. It rebounds upward to a point B. While moving from A to B its","options":["kinetic energy is increasing","potential energy is increasing","potential energy is decreasing","kinetic energy remains constant",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following devices convert heat energy to electrical energy?","options":["transformer","dynamo","thermocouple","thermostat",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"An object of mass 0.25kg moves at a height h above the ground with a speed of 4ms<sup>-1<\/sup>, if its mechanical energy at this height is 12 J, determine the value of h. [g = 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["0.8m","4.0m","4.8m","5.6m",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following equations for the efficiency of a machine is correct?","options":["Efficiency = \\(\\frac{\\text{Velocity Ratio}}{\\text{Mechanical Advantage}}\\) x 100%","Efficiency = \\(\\frac{input}{output}\\) x 100%","Efficiency = \\(\\frac{\\text{load distance}}{\\text{effort distance}}\\) x 100%","Efficiency = \\(\\frac{\\text{Mechanical Advantage}}{\\text{Velocity Ratio}}\\) x 100%",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The design of the thermostat of an electric iron is based on the","options":["emmision of electrons from metals when heated","increase in size of metals when heated","increase in the density of metals when heated","change in the mass of metals when heated",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A metal rod of length 50cm is heated from 40<sup>o<\/sup>C to 80<sup>o<\/sup>C. If the linear expansivity of the material is \\(\\alpha\\), calculate the increase in length of the rod (in metres) in terms of \\(\\alpha\\)","options":["20\\(\\alpha\\)","200\\(\\alpha\\)","2000\\(\\alpha\\)","20000\\(\\alpha\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The cubic expansivity of a certain gas at constant pressure is \\(\\frac{1}{273} k^{-1}\\). If a given mass of the gas is held at constant pressure and its volume at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C is 273m<sup>3<\/sup>, determine the volume of the gas at 273<sup>o<\/sup>C.","options":["273m<sup>3<\/sup>","546m<sup>3<\/sup>","819<sup>3<\/sup>","1092<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Water of mass 1.5kg is heated from from 30<sup>o<\/sup>C to 80<sup>o<\/sup>C using an electric kettle which is rated 5A, 230V. Calculate the time taken to reach the final destination [specific heat capacity of water 4200Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["4.57 minutes","5.02 minutes","7.30 minutes","10.04 minutes",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The working principle of a pressure cooker is based on the","options":["increase in the volume of steam inside it","complete trapping of heat inside it","increase in the pressure of the pot","decrease in the pressure of the pot",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"It takes a shorter time for a liquid to boil at the top of a mountain than at the base because at the top, the","options":["temperature is higher","pressure is lower","humidity is higher","temperature is constant",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Light is considered as a transverse wave because it travels","options":["through material without causing disturbance of the medium","through space with constant speed","in a direction parallel to the plane containing the electric and magnetic fields","in a direction perpendicular to the plane containing the electric and magnetic fields",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"In the day time, it is possible to see under shady areas such as under a tree because light has undergone","options":["internal reflection","refraction","diffraction","diffuse reflection",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The distance between a concave mirror and an object placed in front of it is 1.0m. If the raduis of curvature of the mirror is 4.0m, the image formed will be","options":["2.00m behind the mirror","2.00m in front of the mirror","1.25m in front of the mirror","1.25m behind the mirror",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"The image of an object formed by a convex mirror is","options":["real, errect and enlarged","real, inverted and enlarged","virtual, erect and diminished","virtual, erect and enlarge",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"When viewed straight down, a fish in a pond is","options":["father below than it apperas to be","mearer than it appears to be","found at exactly the same point it is seen","seen beside its image",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A converging lens and a screen are placed 20 cm and 80 cm respectively from an object in a straight line so that a sharp image of the object is formed on the screen. If the object is 3cm high. Calculate the height of the image formed","options":["1 cm","9cm","12cm","15cm",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following defects of vision is as a result of the eye ball being too long?","options":["long sight","astigmatism","short sight","loss of accommodation",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"a sound wave is produced fron a source ans an echo is heard t seconds afterwards. If d is the distance of the reflecting surface from the source, v the speed, p the wavelength and T the period of the wave, then","options":["d = \\(\\frac{2t}{\\lambda}\\)","d = \\(\\frac{\\lambda t}{2T}\\)","d = \\(\\frac{2T}{\\lambda t}\\)","d = \\(\\frac{\\lambda T}{2t}\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A negatively charged rod is held close to an uncharged metal ball on an insulating stand. The ball will","options":["be negatively chargeed","be positively charged","have an excess negatively charges on the side nearest the rod","have an excess positively charges on the side nearest the rod",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Two bodies each carrying a charge of 2.00 x 10<sup>-10<\/sup>C are 5cm apart. Calculate the magnitude of the force between the charges.[\\(\\frac{1}{4\\pi \\mathit{E}_o} = 9.00 \\times 10^9 Nm^2C{-2}\\)]","options":["1.44 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup>N","7.20 x 10<sup>-9<\/sup>N","7.20 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>N","1.44 x 10<sup>11<\/sup>N",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"If the charge on an object is measured as 4.0 x 10<sup>-18<\/sup>C, how many excess electrons does the object possess, given that the charge of an electron is 1.6 x 10<sup>-18<\/sup>C","options":["18","19","25","37",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following is a unit of the time rate of flow of electric charges?","options":["coulomb","ampere","volt","watt",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A wire 1.0m long and with cross-sectional area 2.0 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup> m<sup>2<\/sup> has a resistance of 0.1\\(\\Omega\\). Calculate the electrical conductivity of the wire","options":["2.0 x 10<sup>7<\/sup>\\(\\Omega^{-1} m^{-1}\\)","5.0 x 10<sup>7<\/sup>\\(\\Omega^{-1} m^{-1}\\)","2.0 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>\\(\\Omega^{-1} m^{-1}\\)","5.0 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>\\(\\Omega^{-1} m^{-1}\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Three capacitors each of capacitance 1.5\\(\\mu F\\) are connected in series. The total capacitance in the circuit is","options":["2.0 \\(\\mu F\\)","1.5 \\(\\mu F\\)","0.6 \\(\\mu F\\)","0.5 \\(\\mu F\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A voltmeter is a device that","options":["draws high current","has a very low resistance","has a very high resistance","is able to measure both voltage and current",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following actions will not increase the sensitivity of a moving coil galvanometer?","options":["using a strong temporary magnet","increasing the area and number of turns of the coil","using a week hair spring","using a light pointer",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Fleming's right hand rule is also called the","options":["motor rule","dynamo rule","screw rule","thumb rule",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A transformer is required to supply 12 V<sub>rms<\/sub> to operate a toy train set from a 240 V<sub>rms<\/sub>. If the number of turns in the in the secondary coil is 100, calculate the number of turns required in the primary coil","options":["5","12","2000","2400",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A direct current of 5A flow through a 0.2H inductor. Calculate the energy stored in the inductor","options":["0.5J","1.0J","2.5J","5.0J",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Both \\(\\gamma\\)-rays and X-rays  i. can be produced by thermionic emission  ii. have low frequencies  iii. have short wavelengths. Which of the statements above is\/are correct?","options":["i only","ii only","iii only","i and iii only",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"When a radioactive substance undergoes a beta decay, its","options":["mass number decreases by 1","atomic number decreases by 1","mass number increases by 1","atomic number increases by 1",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Nuclear fission is preffered to nuclear fusion in the generation of energy because","options":["very high temperature are required for fusion","the raw materials for fusion are easily obtained","energy obtained from fusion is relatively small","the by-products of fusion is very dangerous",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Control in nuclear reactors is effected with boron rods because rhe rods have the ability to","options":["absorb electrons","absorb neutron","accelerate electrons","slow down neutrons",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"A radioactive element has a decay constant of 0.077s<sup>-1<\/sup>. Calculate its half-life","options":["13.0s","9.0s","5.1s","0.5s",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"Which of the following observations is not an effect of surface tension?","options":["droplets of water dripping slowly from a tap","mercury spilled on a clean glass plate forms spherical droplets","an indect walking across the surface of a pond","water flowing out more easily then engine oil from a container",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following physical quantities is correctly paired with it's corresponding S.I unit?","options":["density[kg m<sup>3<\/sup>]","power[Js<sup>-1<\/sup>]","specific latent heat [J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","Pressure [Nm<sup>-1<\/sup>]",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A liquid of volume 2.00 m<sup>3<\/sup> and density 1.00 x 10<sup>3<\/sup> is mixed with 3.00 m<sup>3<\/sup> of another liquid of density 8.00 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>kg m<sup>-3<\/sup>. Calculate the density of the mixture [Assuming there is no chemical reaction]","options":["5.20 x 10<sup>2<\/sup> kg m<sup>-3<\/sup>","1.13 x 10<sup>3<\/sup> kg m<sup>-3<\/sup>","8.80 x 10<sup>2<\/sup> kg m<sup>-3<\/sup>","5.20 x 10<sup>2<\/sup> kg m<sup>-3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about solid friction are correct? It  i. is a force  ii. occurs between the surfaces of two bodies in contact  iii. depends on the area in contact","options":["i and ii only","i adnd iii only","ii and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A mass of mass m, experiences a viscous drag, F and an upthrust, U as he descends towards the ground at a steady velocity, Using a parachute. If the acceleration of free fall is g, which of the following expressions is correct?","options":["FU = mg","U + F - mg = 0","U - F = mg","F - U - mg = 0",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"a body moving at a constant speed accelerates when it is in","options":["rectilinear motion","translational motion","circular motion","vibrational motion",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"An object of mass 2 kg moves with a uniform speed of 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup> for 5s along an straight path. Determine the magnitude of its acceleration","options":["0 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","1 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","3 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","4 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The team rectilinear acceleration means the rate of increase of","options":["velocity along a circular path in a unit time","distance along a rectangular path in a unit time","displacement along a straight-line path in a unit time","velocity along a straight-line path in a unit time",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A body moving with an initial velocity U accelerates until it attains a velocity of V within a time t. The distance, s covered by the body is given by the expressions","options":["s = (\\(\\frac{v - u}{2}\\))t","s = (\\(\\frac{v + 2u}{2}\\))t","s = (\\(\\frac{v + u}{2}\\))t","s = (\\(\\frac{2v + u}{2}\\))t",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A body accelerates uniformly from rest at 2ms<sup>-2<\/sup>. Calculate the magnitude of its velocity after travelling 9m","options":["4.5 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","18.0<sup>-1<\/sup>","36.0<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A swinging pendulum between the rest position and its maximum displacement possesses","options":["Kinetic energy only","potential energy only","gravitational energy only","both kinetic and potential energy",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A block of mass 4.0kg causes a spiral spring to extend by 0.16m from its unstretched position. The block is removed and another body of mass 0.50kg is hung from the same spiral spring. If the spring is then stretched and released, what is the angular frequency of the subsequent motion? [g = 10 ms <sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["10\\(\\sqrt 5\\) rads<sup>-1<\/sup>","5\\(\\sqrt 2\\) rads<sup>-1<\/sup>","5 rads<sup>-1<\/sup>","\\(\\sqrt 5\\) rads<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"An external force of magnitude 100N acts on a particle of mass 0.15kg for 0.03s. Calculate the change in the speed of the particle","options":["50ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","25ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","20ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A car of mass 800kg moves from rest on a horizontal track and travels 60m in 20s with uniform acceleration. Assuming there were no frictional forces, calculate the accelerating force","options":["240.0N","800.0N","1600.00N","2400.0N",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A plane inclined at 30<sup>o<\/sup> to the horizontal has an efficiency of 50%. Calculate the force parallel to the plane required to push a load of 120N uniformly upn the plane","options":["50.0N","120.0N","200.0N","240N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Mechanical energy can be either","options":["kinetic or electric","chemical or potential","potential or kinetic","electric or heat",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following surfaces will radiate heat energy best?","options":["Red surface","white surface","black surface","yellow surface",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The ice and steam point on a mercury-in-glass thermometer are 10cm and 30cm respectively. Calculate the temperature in decree Celsius when the mercury meniscus is the 14cm mark","options":["20<sup>o<\/sup>C","30<sup>o<\/sup>C","34<sup>o<\/sup>C","70<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following statements distinguishes thermal conduction for convection?  i. Conduction requires a material medium while convection does not  ii. In convection, there is actual motion of hot material, while in conduction, molecules molecules vibrates faster about their mean positions  iii. Conduction takes place in solids while convection takes place in fluids.","options":["i and ii only","ii and iii only","i and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A cube made of metal of linear expansivity \\(\\alpha\\) is heated through a temperature \\(\\theta\\). If the initial volume of the cube is V<sub>o<\/sub>, the correct expression for the increase in volume of the cube is","options":["\\(\\frac{1}{3} \\alpha V_o \\theta\\)","\\(\\frac{1}{2} \\alpha V_o \\theta\\)","\\(2 \\alpha V_o \\theta\\)","\\(3 \\alpha V_o \\theta\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A relative density bottle of volume 50cm<sup>3<\/sup> is completely filled with a liquid at 30<sup>o<\/sup>C. It is then heated to 80<sup>o<\/sup>C such that 0.75cm<sup>3<\/sup> of the liquid is expelled. Calculate the apparent cubic expansivity of the liquid.","options":["0.00030k<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.00032k<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.01970k<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.02030k<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A body of mass 200g and specific heat capacity 0.4Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>k<sup>-1<\/sup> cools from 37<sup>o<\/sup>C to 31<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate the quantity of the heat released by the body.","options":["4800J","1200J","480J","202J",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"According to the kinetic theory of gasses, which of the following property of a gas can be affected by the collision of the gas molecule with the walls of the container?","options":["temperature","energy","viscosity","pressure",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The pressure of a fixed mass of an ideal gas at 27<sup>o<\/sup>C is 3 pa. The gas is heated at a constant volume until its pressure is 5 pa. Determine the new temperature of the gas.","options":["100<sup>o<\/sup>C","227<sup>o<\/sup>C","273<sup>o<\/sup>C","500<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following wave is electromagnetic?","options":["x-rays","sound waves","water waves","tidal waves",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The distance between two points P and Q, along a wave is 0.05m. If the wave length of the wave is 0.10m, determine the phase angle between P and Q in radians","options":["0.1\\(\\pi\\)","\\(\\pi\\)","2\\(\\pi\\)","10\\(\\pi\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following phenomena is not a direct consequence of rectilinear propagation of light?","options":["lunar and solar eclipses","images of objects in a pin hole camera","diffraction of light","shadows of opaque object",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"An object is placed 10cm in front of a plane mirror. If it is moved 8cm away father away from the mirror, determine the distance of the final image from the mirror","options":["2cm","9cm","16cm","18cm",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"In which of the following piece of apparatus is the radius of curvature equal to twice the focal length?","options":["converging lens","diverging lens","converging mirror","parabolic mirror",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"When an object is placed at the centre of curvature of a concave mirror, its image is formed at","options":["the focus","infinity","the centre of curvature","a distance twice the radius of curvature",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A rectangular glass prism of thickness d and absolute refractive index n is placed on a point object which is viewed vertically downward from above the prism. Which of the following expressions correctly defines the apparent upward displacement of the object?","options":["\\(\\frac{d}{n}\\)","dn","\\(\\frac{d}{n - 2}\\)","\\(\\frac{d(n - 1)}{n}\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following factors can affect the speed of sound in air?  i. The temperature of the surrounding  ii. The direction of the wind  iii. The pitch of the sound.","options":["i and ii only","ii and iii only","i and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A sounding tuning fork is brought near the open end of a pipe containing air and the loudness of the sound is observed to increase. This observation is due to","options":["an echo","resonance","interference","reverbration",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about sound wave is not correct? Sound waves can be","options":["reflected","refracted","diffracted","polarized",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A dry plastic comb used in combing hair was found to attract pieces of paper and dust. The most probable explanation for this phenomenon is that the comb has been given","options":["magnetization by induction","electric charges by induction","electric charges by conduction","electric charges by friction",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct about resonance? Resonance occurs when a body","options":["vibrates with its natural frequency","is forced to vibrate on its own natural frequency by another body at the same vibration","vibrates at the frquency of the body causing the vibration","vibrates with an irregular frequency",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following components is used for storing electric charges?","options":["inductor","resistor","capacitor","electrometer",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following operations does not represent an action of a force field?","options":["falling of a mango fruit from the tree","picking of nails using a bar magnet","repulsion of two like charges","pushing of a wheel-barrow on a level gound",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"A bulb marked 240V, 40W is used for 30 minutes. Calculate the heat generated","options":["320J","400J","10800J","72000J",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Five 80-W and three 100W are run for 8 hours. If the cost of energy is N5.00 per unit, calculate the cost of running the lamp. [1 unit = 1 kWh]","options":["N280.00","N28.00","N7.20","N1.44",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following electromagnetic wave can be detected by its heating effect?","options":["ultraviolet radiation","x-rays","gamma rays","infrared radiation",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"If a gas is excited by high voltage to produce a discharge and the light is examined in a spectrometer","options":["an explosion is observed","the rainbow colours are seen","an emission spectrum is observed","dark lines are observed",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The number of protons in an element increased by one after a radioactive decay. The element must have decay by emitting","options":["a beta particle","an alpha particle","a gamma ray","a neutron",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"In a nuclear reactor, chain reactions result from the release of","options":["electrons","photons","neutrons","protons",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"The correct sequence of energy transformation in the operation of an x-ray tube is  i. X-rays  ii. Kinetic energy of thermo electrons  iii. Potential energy of the target atoms  iv. Heat energy of the emitted electrons","options":["iv, iii, ii, i","ii, iv, iii, i","iv, ii, iii, i","iii, iv, ii, i",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"There is always an uncertainty involved in any attempt to measure the position and momentum of an electron simultaneously. This statement is known as the","options":["de Broglie's law","Heisenberg uncertainty principle","Franck-Hertz experimental law","wave-particle paradox",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"Which of the following phenomena causes capillary of liquids in tubes of narrow bore?","options":["viscosity","surface tension","osmosis","brownian motion",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following physical quantities are derived?  i. Area  ii. Thrust  iii. Pressure  iv. Mass","options":["i, ii, iii and iv","i, ii and iii only","i, ii and iv only","i and iii only",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A block of volume 3 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup> and density 2.5 x 10<sup>3<\/sup> kg m<sup>-3<\/sup> is suspended from a spring balance with \\(\\frac{2}{3}\\) of its volume immersed in a liquid of density 900 kg m<sup>-3<\/sup>. Determine the reading of the spring balance [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["0.18N","0.57N","0.75n","0.93N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A solid body will float in a liquid if its","options":["density is less than that of a liquid","mass is equal to that of the liquid","density is greater than that of the liquid","mass is less than that of the liquid",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"An object is said to undergo oscillatory motion when it moves","options":["in an erratic manner","to and fro about a fixed point","in a circular path","along a continuous path from the starting point",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A body is rotating in a horizontal circle of radius 2.5m with an angular speed of 5 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>. Calculate the magnitude of the radial acceleration of the body","options":["62.50ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","31.25ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","12.50ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","10.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A moving car of mass 800 kg experiences a frictional force of 200N. If it accelerates 2 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>, calculate the magnitude of the force applied to the car","options":["600N","1000N","1600N","1800N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Uniform speed occurs when there is equal change of","options":["distance in equal times","displacement in equal times","velocity in equal times","acceleration in equal times",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A car accelerates uniformly from rest at 5 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>. Determine its speed after 10s","options":["50.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","25.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following quantities is a vector?","options":["speed","distance","energy","momentum",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"which of the following statements about simple harmonic motion is correct? The","options":["total mechanical energy is always conserved","linear acceleration is directed to any variable point","linear acceleration varies inversely with displacement","period of oscillation varies linearly as acceleration due to gravity",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A force acting on a body causes a change in the momentum of a body from 12 kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup> to 16kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup> in 0.25. Calculate the magnitude of the impulse","options":["28.0Ns","20.0Ns","4.0Ns","0.8Ns",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following source of energy is renewable?","options":["petroleum","charcoal","hydro","nuclear",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A stone of mass 2.0kg is thrown vertically upward with a velocity of 20.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the initial kinetic energy of the stone","options":["200J","400J","800J","1600J",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the mouth piece of a telephone is correct? It converts sound energy into","options":["acoustic energy","mechanival energy","electrical energy","heat energy",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The potential energy in an elastic string of force constant K which has been extended by X metres is expresses as","options":["\\(\\frac{1}{2}k \\Box ^2\\)","\\(k \\Box ^2\\)","\\(\\frac{1}{2}k \\Box \\)","\\(k \\Box \\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The engine of a train produces a force of 3000N when moving at 30.ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. calculate the power of the engine","options":["1.00 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>W","3.00 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>W","9.00 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>W","3.00 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>W",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The velocity ratio of an inclined plane, inclines at an angle \\(\\theta\\) to the horizontal can be expressed as","options":["(sin \\(\\theta)^{-1}\\)","\\(\\sin \\theta\\)","(cos \\(\\theta)^{-1}\\)","\\(\\cos \\theta\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A block and tackle system has six pulleys. a force of 50N applied to it lifts a load of weight W. If the efficiency of the system is 40%, calculate W","options":["300N","200N","140N","120N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The sagging of overhead electrical cables is the consequence of","options":["linear expansivity","superficial expansivity","cubic expansivity","conductivity",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The silvered  surface in a vacuum flask reduces heat loos due to","options":["conduction","convection","radiation","evaporation",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"How long will it take to heat 3kg of water from 28<sup>o<\/sup>C to 88<sup>o<\/sup>C in an electric kettle taking 6a from a 220V supply? [specific heat capacity of water = 4180 J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["120s","570s","600s","836s",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The amount of energy required to change a kilogram of ice in water without a change in temperature is","options":["heat capacity of ice","specific heat capacity","specific latent heat of vaporisation of ice","specific latent heat of fusion of ice",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A quantity of steam at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C condenses to water at the same temperature by releasing 6.9 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>J of energy. Calculate the mass of the condensed steam. [specific latent heat of vaporization of eater = 2.3 x 10<sup>6<\/sup> J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["3.0 x 10<sup>-1<\/sup> kg","3.0 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup> kg","3.0 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup> kg","3.0 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup> kg",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The temperature of a liquid falls after some of it has evaporated because","options":["the liquid left is smaller in volume and the breeae easily cools it","the more energetic molecules have escaped into the atmosphere","the liquid left has less latent heat","after evaporation impurites are left behind",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The S.I units of frequency, period and amplitude of a wave are respectively","options":["hertz, second and centimeter","second, metre and hertz","metre, hertz and seconds","hertz, second and metre",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"a note of frequency 2000Hz has a velocity of 400 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. calculate the wavelength of the note","options":["5.0m","2.0m","0.5m","0.2m",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The eclipse of the moon occurs when the","options":["moon comes exactly between the earth and the sun","earth comes exactly between the moon and the sun","sun comes exactly between the earth and the moon","moon reflects all the rays from the sun onto the earth",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following observations cannot be explained using the rectilinear propagation of light?","options":["production of images by a pinhole camera","production of real images of objects by lenses","formation of an annular eclipse","diffraction patterns of light",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The distance between the successive crests of a wave travelling at 20ms<sup>-1<\/sup> is 25cm. Calculate the frequency of the wave","options":["0.8Hz","5.0Hz","50.0Hz","80.0hz",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A ray from a fixed object is incident on a plane mirror at an angle of 20<sup>o<\/sup>. If the mirror is rotated through 30<sup>o<\/sup> by how many degree would the reflected ray rotate?","options":["60<sup>o<\/sup>","50<sup>o<\/sup>","40<sup>o<\/sup>","30<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following distances is usually adjustable in the camera? The distance between the","options":["lens and the film","diaphragm and the shutter","shutter and the film","diaphragm and the film",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A travelling microscope is focused on a mark on a table. If a glass block of thickness 18.0cm is placed on the mark by how many centimeters will the microscope be moved upwards so as to focus the mark once again? [refractive index of glass = 1.5]","options":["27cm","24cm","9cm","6cm",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"In which of the following media would sound wave travel fastest?","options":["wood","water","iron","mercury",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following actions is necessary in order to tune a string to produce a note of an octave higher than its fundamental?","options":["doucling the length of the string","reducing the tension by half","reducing the mass per unit length","increasing the tension four times",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The acceleration due o gravity may be defined as the force","options":["of attraction of the sun and on the earth","with which the earth revolves around the sun","with which the earth attracts one kilo-gram mass","of the moon on the earth",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"An electron of mass m and charge \\(\\Box\\) enters a uniform electric field between two metal plates P and q separated by a distance d. P is maintained at a potential V while Q is earthed. Determine an expression for the magnitude of the acceleration of electron through the field","options":["\\(\\frac{eV}{md}\\)","\\(\\frac{d}{meV}\\)","\\(\\frac{md}{eV}\\)","\\(\\frac{e}{Vmd}\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following factors does not affect the capacitance of a parallel plate capacitor?","options":["area of the plates","nature of the surface of the plates","distance of separation between the plates","nature of the insulating material between the plates",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The equivalent capacitance of a 3\\(\\mu F\\) capacitor and a 6\\(\\mu F\\) capacitor connected in parallel is","options":["2.0\\(\\mu F\\)","3.0\\(\\mu F\\)","4.5\\(\\mu F\\)","9.0\\(\\mu F\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"a cell of e.m.f. 1.5V and internal resistance 1.0\\(\\Omega\\) is connected to two resistor of resistance 2.0\\(\\Omega\\) and 3.0\\(\\Omega\\) in series. Calculate the current through the resistors","options":["0.25A","0.30A","0.35A","0.50A",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"An electric lamp rated 120W is used on a 240Vrms, calculate the resistance of its filament","options":["480\\(\\Omega\\)","360\\(\\Omega\\)","60\\(\\Omega\\)","2\\(\\Omega\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about a bar magnet is correct?","options":["iron fillings cling uniformly along the length of a bar magnet","the magnetic properties are more pronounced at the middle of a magnet","it is impossible to have the same poles at the end of a magnet","the magnetic properties are more pronounced at points near the end of the bar",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The force experienced by a current-carrying conductor move in a magnetic field is employed in the working of the  i. moving coil ammeter  ii. electric bell  iii. electric motor. Which of the statements above are correct?","options":["i and ii only","ii and iii only","i and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"The breaking up of an atomic nucleus into the fragment of nearly equal size is known as","options":["nuclear fusion","nuclear fission","thermonuclear reaction","natural radioactivity",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A 500kV is applied across an X-ray tube. Calculate the maximum velocity of the electrons produced [Me = 9.1 x 10<sup>-31<\/sup>kg, e = 1.6 x 10<sup>-19<\/sup>C]","options":["4.2 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.9 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.2 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.8 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"A radioactive substance of mass 768g has a half life of 3 years. After how many years does this substance leave only 6g undecayed?","options":["21","18","15","12",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Fusion is not usually used for generating electric power because","options":["no energy is released when fusion takes place","very high temperatures are required to initiate fusion reaction","the raw materials needed is not easily available","heavy nuclei are involved",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"An atom \\(^{234}_{91} P\\) emits a gamma radiation. The resultant nuclide is","options":["\\(^{230}_{90} Th\\)","\\(^{234}_{91} Pa\\)","\\(^{234}_{90} Th\\)","\\(^{234}_{89} Ac\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"Which of the following phenomena is the practical evidence for the existence of the continual motion of molecules?","options":["Translational motion","rotational motion","brownian motion","oscillatory motion",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Each of the following physical quantities is classified as a vector or a scalar quantity. Which of the classifications is correct?","options":["electric potential (Vector)","momentum (scalar)","gravitational field intensity (scalar)","magnetic flux density (vector)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about a spring balance and\/or a chemical balance is not correct?","options":["the chemical balance operates on the principle of moments","the sprin balance operates on Hooke's law","either may be used to measure the weight of a substance","the reading of a spring balance changes over the surface of the earth, while that of the chemical balance remaind constant",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The friction which exists between two layers of liquid in relative motion is called","options":["capillarity","surface tension","viscosity","cohension",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A body of mass 25kg, moving at 3ms<sup>-1<\/sup> on a rough horizontal floor is at rest after sliding through a distance of 2.50m on the floor. Calculate the co-efficient of sliding friction. [g = 10.0ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["0.09","0.18","0.36","0.54",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following simple machines is a second class lever?","options":["wheel barrow","crowbar","claw hammer","seesae",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A wheel and axle of radii 800mm and 200mm respectively is used to raise a body of weight 800N by the application of 250N. Calculate the efficiency of the machine","options":["85%","80%","60%","20%",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Masses,m<sup>1<\/sup> and m<sup>2<\/sup> at the 20-cm and 65-cm marks respectively of a uniform metre rule freely suspended at its centre of gravity. If the metre rule balances horizontally, determine the ratio m<sup>2<\/sup> : m<sup>1<\/sup>","options":["2 : 1","3 : 3","2 : 3","1 : 2",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following type of motion does a body undergo when acted upon by a couple?V","options":["vibrational","translational","rotational","random",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A body starts from rest and accelerates uniformly at 5ms<sup>-1<\/sup> until it attains a velocity of 25ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Calculate the time taken to attain this velocity","options":["2.5s","5.0s","10.0s","125.0s",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The frequency of a swinging pendulum is the","options":["number of complete oscillations the pendulum makes in a second","number of amplitudes the bob makes in a second","angle the bob swings through in a second","distance the bob covers in a second",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following about an object performing simple harmonic motion is correct? Its acceleration","options":["is maximum at the extreme ends","is constant and directed towards a fixed point","is zero when it is displayed from the equilibrum position","varies linearly with the displacement from a fixed point and is directed towards the fixed point",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A body of mass 5kg moving with a velocity of 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup> collides with a stationary body of mass 6kg. If the two bodies stick together and move in the same direction after their collision, calculate their common velocity","options":["4.55ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","12.00ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","30.00ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","50.00ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Fuel was consumed at a steady rate of 5.0 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>kg per second in a rocket engine and ejected as a gas with a speed of 4 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Determine the thrust on the rocket","options":["20N","80N","200N","800N",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following quantities has the same unit as energy?","options":["power","work","force","momentum",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following source of energy is renewable?","options":["sun","petroleum","coal","uranium",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The lower and upper fixed point of a thermometer are 30mm and 180mm respectively. Calculate the temperature in degrees Celsius when the thermometer reads 45mm","options":["10.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","15.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","20.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","30.0<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A body of mass m, has a specific heat capacity s, and a heat capacity  c. If the temperature of the body changes by \\(\\theta^oC\\), Which of the following equation is correct?","options":["ms\\(\\theta\\) = mv<sup>-1<\/sup>","ms = C","ms = s\\(\\theta\\)","ms = c\\(\\theta\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"An immersion heater rated 400W, 220V is used to heat a liquid of mass 0.5kg. If the temperature of the liquid increases uniformly at the rate of 2.5<sup>o<\/sup>C per second, calculate the specific heat capacity of the liquid. [Assume no heat is lost]","options":["1100Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","320Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","200Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","176Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Water falls through a height of 50m. Determine the temperature rise at the bottom of the fall. [Neglect energy losses. Specific heat capacity of water = 4200Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup>, g = 10ms<sup>2<\/sup>]","options":["0.119<sup>o<\/sup>C","0.840<sup>o<\/sup>C","1.190<sup>o<\/sup>C","8.400<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The energy required to change a solid to liquid at constant temperature is called","options":["thermal capacity","has lower specific heat capacity","latent heat of fusion","latent heat of vaporisation",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about boiling and evaporation at atmospheric pressure is correct?","options":["evaporation and boiling of water take place at 100<sup>o<\/sup>","evaporation of water takes place at a temperature greater than 100<sup>o<\/sup>C, while boiling takes place at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C","evaporation of water takes place at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C while boiling takes place at a higher temperature","boiling takes place at 100<sup>o<\/sup> while evaporation my take place at temperatures lower than 100<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","options":["the density of a liquid decreases when it expands","the density of a liquid increases when the liquids are heated","the real expansivity of a liquid is less than its apparent expansivity","a liquid changes to solid when heated to a sufficiently high temperature",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The pressure exerted by a given mass of gas in a container","options":["decreases if the container is heated","increases if the molecules of the gas move faster","increases if the container is doubled","decreases as the kinetic energy of the gas molecules inceases",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about a progressive mechanical wave is correct?","options":["it can be a plane polarised","its energy is localised at specific points of its profile","it does not require a material medium for its propagation","its frequency remains constant as it travels between different media",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The distance between two points in phase on a progressive wave is 5cm. If the sped of the wave is 0.2ms<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate its period","options":["4.00s","2.50s","0.25s","0.04s",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Radio waves travel in air at 3.0 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. If the waves enter water of refractive index \\(\\frac{4}{3}\\), calculate the speed of radio waves in water","options":["4.33 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.00 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.25 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.33 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The amplitude of a wave is the","options":["distance travelled by the wave in a complete cycle of its motion","maximum diplacement of the wave particle from the equilibrum position","separation of two adjacent particles vibrating in a phase","distance between two successive troughs of the wave",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following optical instruments does not depend on the use of plane mirrors?","options":["kaleidoscope","simple microscope","sextant","simple periscope",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A ray of light is incident normally on a plan mirror. If the incident ray is kept fixed while the mirror is rotated through an angle of 30<sup>o<\/sup>, determine the initial and final angles of reflection respectively","options":["0<sup>o<\/sup> and 60<sup>o<\/sup>","90<sup>o<\/sup> and 30<sup>o<\/sup>","0<sup>o<\/sup> and 30<sup>o<\/sup>","90<sup>o<\/sup> and 60<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"In which of the following media is the transmission of sound wave fastest?","options":["Vacuum","Air","Wood","Iron",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The ability of a material to store an electric charge when its plates are at different potentials is referred to as its","options":["conductance","inductance","capacitance","resistance",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Two capacitors if capacitance 0.4\\(\\mu F\\) and 0.5\\(\\mu F\\) are connected in parallel and charged to a p.d. of 50V, Determine the total charge acquired","options":["45\\(\\mu C\\)","25\\(\\mu C\\)","20\\(\\mu C\\)","10\\(\\mu C\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A parallel plate capacitor of capacitance 600\\(\\mu F\\) has a potential difference of 200V between its plates. Calculate the charge on either plate of the capacitor","options":["1.2C","3.3C","3330.0C","12.0000.0C",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A parallel plate capacitor of capacitance 600\\(\\mu F\\) has a potential difference of 200V between its plates. Calculate the charge on either plate of the capacitor","options":["1.2C","3.3C","3330.0C","12.0000.0C",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"a chemical cell of internal resistance 1\\(\\Omega\\) supplies electric current to an external resistor of resistance 3\\(\\Omega\\). Calculate the efficiency of the cell","options":["75%","50%","33%","25%",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"An electric lamp is rated 240V, 40W. What is the cost of running the lamp for 72 hours if the electricity authority charges N2.50 per kWh?","options":["N7.20","N18.00","180.00","N720.00",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following statements explains lost volt in an electric circuit? The","options":["total p.d from a source to maintain a flow of current through the circuit as well as the source","p.d to drive current through the circuit component except the source","p.d across all external components connected to the source of electricity","p.d across the internal resistance of the cell",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A constantan wire has a cross sectional area of 4 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>m<sup>2<\/sup> and a resistivity of 1.1 x 10<sup>-6<\/sup>\\(\\Omega\\)m. If a resistor of resistance 11\\(\\Omega\\) is to be made from this wire, calculate the length of the wire required","options":["0.4m","0.8m","2.5m","5.0m",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The mass and weight of a body on earth are 8kg and 80N respectively. Determine the mass and weight of the body respectively on a planet where the pull of gravity is \\(\\frac{1}{8}\\) that on earth","options":["8kg, 8N","1kg, 10N","64kg, 10N","8kg, 10N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Lenz's law of electromagnetic induction states that","options":["a force is exerted on a current-carrying conductor in a magnetic field","electromotive force id induced in a circuit whenever there is a change in the magnetic flux linked with the circuit","the magnitude of the induced electromotive force in a circuit is proportional to the rate of change of flux linking the circuit","the induced current in a coil is in such a direction that it sets up a magnetic field which opposes the change producing it",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A bar magnet is placed near and lying along the axis of a solenoid connected to a galvanometer. The pointer of the galvanometer shows no deflection when","options":["the magnet is moved away from the stationary solenoid","the solenoid is moved away from the stationary magnet","the magnet is moved towards the stationary solenoid","there is no relative motion between the magnet and the solenoid",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"an electric motor is a machine that converts","options":["mechanical energy into electrical energy","electrical energy into mechanical energy","high voltage to low voltage","low voltage to high voltage",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is an advantage of nuclear fusion over nuclear fission?","options":["The resulting chain reaction which produces large amount of energy","no radioactve wave is produced as bye product","very high temperature is required in the process","the end product is lead",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not a reason for using soft iron in making the core of a transformer? It","options":["retains its magnetism for a long time","is easily magnitised","reduces energy loss due to hysteresis","is easily demagnetised",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Beta particles are faster-moving","options":["protons","electrons","neutrons","photons",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A process by which two light atoms join to form a new atom of higher atomic mass is","options":["natural radioactivity","nuclear fission","nuclear fusion","chain reaction",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Light of energy 5.0 eV falls on a metal of work function 3.0 eV and electrons are emitted, determine the stopping potential. [electronic charge, e = 1.60 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-19<\/sup>]","options":["1.7V","2.0V","8.0V","15.0V",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The mass of a proton is 1.0089\\(\\mu\\) and that of a neutron is 1.0089\\(\\mu\\). Determine the energy evolved in stabilizing the nucleus of nitrogen of mass number 14 with 7 protons and 7 neutrons. [speed of light = 3.0 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>; 1\\(\\mu\\) = 1.67 x 10<sup>-27<\/sup>kg]","options":["1.710 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>J","3.131 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>J","1.476 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>J","2.332 x 10<sup>-9<\/sup>J",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Uranium of atom number 92 and mass number 238 emits an alpha particle from its nucleus. The new nucleus formed has respectively, atomic number and mass number","options":["94 and 238","90 and 236","88 and 234","90 and 234",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The angle between the geographic and the magnetic meridians at a place on the earth\u2019s surface is the","options":["angle of declination","angle of depression","angle of dip.","latitude of the place","longitude of the place"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"An object is placed in front of a concave mirror whose radius of curvature is 12cm. If the magnification of the Image produced is 1.5, how far is the object from the mirror?","options":["8cm","10cm","15cm","18cm","20cm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A body moves along a circular path with uniform angular speed of 0.6 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup> and at a constant speed of 3.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. <br>\r\n<br>\r\nCalculate the acceleration of the body towards the centre of the circle.","options":["0.2.ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","1.8 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","5.0 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","5.4 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","25.0 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the statements is\/are true of two bodies involved in an inelastic collision? After collision. <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. the kinetic energy increases <br>\r\nII. The momentum decreases<br>\r\nIII. Their velocities are the same.","options":["I only","II Only","III only","I and II only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"491 K is equivalent to","options":["273 \u00b0C","218 \u00b0C","373 \u00b0C","491 \u00b0C","764 \u00b0C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"An atom radiates 1.5 \u00d7 10<sup>-19<\/sup>J when an electron jumps from one level to another. What is the wavelength of the emitted radiation? (Planck\u2019s constant 6.6 \u00d7 l0<sup>-34<\/sup>Js ; Speed of light in vacuum = 3.0 \u00d7 108ms<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["1.32 \u00d7 10<sup>-6<\/sup>m","2.97 \u00d7 10<sup>-6<\/sup>m","3.30 \u00d7 10<sup>-6<\/sup>m","6.82 \u00d7 10<sup>-6<\/sup>m","8.01 \u00d7 10m<sup>-6<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A 12V battery supplies a current of 0.4A to a lamp. Calculate the resistance of the lamp.","options":["30.00","4.80","3.00","0.30","0.03"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"In which of the following is the expansion of solids a disadvantage?","options":["Electric iron","Fire alarm","The balance wheel of a watch","The bimetallic thermometer","The fitting of wheels in rims"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following is a desirable property of a fuse Wire?","options":["High expansively","High thermal conductivity","Low density","Low electrical resistivity","Low melting point"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A projectile is projected with an initial velocity u, at an angle \u03b8 to the horizontal. The maximum height attained is.","options":["U<sup>2<\/sup> sin  \\(\\frac{\\theta}{g}\\)","2U<sup>2<\/sup> sin<sup>2<\/sup> \\(\\frac{\\theta}{g}\\)","U sin<sup>2<\/sup> \\(\\frac{\\theta}{g}\\)","U<sup>2<\/sup> sin<sup>2<\/sup>\\(\\frac{\\theta}{g}\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A stone of mass 0.7 kg is projected vertically upward with a speed of 5 ms-1. Calculate the maximum height reached. [g =10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["1.25m","1.50m","2.50m","3.75m","5.00Nm"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Calculate the magnitude of the force due to a magnetic field of 0.40T on an electron moving perpendicular to the field with a speed of 4.00 \u00d7 106ms<sup>-1<\/sup> (e 1.60 \u00d7 10<sup>-19<\/sup>C]","options":["6.40 \u00d7 <sup>-10<\/sup>","6.40\u00d7 10<sup>-13<\/sup>N","2.56 \u00d7 10<sup>-13<\/sup>N","1.60 \u00d7 10<sup>-12<\/sup>N","2.30 \u00d7 10<sup>-11<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A voltage of 240V is connected to the primary coil of a the rating of the primary turns to the secondary turns if the voltage available at the secondary coil is 15V","options":["0.06","0.9","1.6","16","36"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Two metals A and B lose the same quantity of heat when their temperatures drop from 20\u00b0C to 15\u00b0C. If the specific heat Capacity of A Ii thrice that of B, calculate the ratio of the mass of A to that of B.","options":["3:01","4:03","3:04","1:02","1:03"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"When a yellow card is viewed in blue light, It will appear","options":["black","orange","purple","red","white"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Mercury does NOT wet glass because","options":["glass is an amorphous substance","the adhesive force is greater than the cohesive force","the cohesive force is greater than the adhesive force.","mercury has very high thermal conductivity","mercury is opaque."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"When some ice cubes are added to a glass of warm water, the glass is cooled by a process of","options":["conduction only","convection only","conduction and convection","conduction and radiation","radiation only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The length of a simple pendulum is increased by a factor of four. By what factor is its period Increased?","options":["0.25","0.5","1.66","2","4"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following pairs is an example of translucent bodies?","options":["Cardboard and moon","Clear water and glass","Frosted glass and waxed paper","Oiled paper and brick","Wood and metal sheet"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Calculate the peak voltage that could be obtained from a 220 V\\(_{r.m.s}\\)main supply.","options":["70.7V","110.0V","155.6V","311.1V","440.0V"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The mercury column in a simple mercury barometer is of height 5m above the mercury in a reservoir. If the tube is replaced with one whose radius is twice that of the first tube, what will be the height of the mercury column in the new tube?","options":["2.5m","5.0m","7.5m","10.0m","20.0m"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The escape velocity of an object from the gravitational field of a planet <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. Increases with the mass of the object <br>\r\nII. Increases with the mass of the planet<br>\r\nIII. Is smaller on the moon than on the earth. Which of the above statements is\/are correct?","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","II and III only","I, II and III"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following is a non-renewable energy source?","options":["Coal","Hydro","Ocean waves","Solar","Tides"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"An object of mass 5.0 cg moving with a velocity of 12ms<sup>-1<\/sup> due north hits a stationary body of mass 7.0kg. If they stick together after collision and move with velocity V due north, calculate the magnitude of V.","options":["12ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","7ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","6ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","4ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is\/are correct in any machine? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. The velocity ratio is usually greater than the mechanical advantage. <br>\r\nII. Efficiency work inputwork outputIII. The velocity ratio is independent of friction.","options":["I only","III only","I and II only","I and III only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following is used for shielding radioactive fallout?","options":["Aluminum","Lead","Iron","Plastic","Wood"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The charge of an alpha particle can be neutralized by","options":["1 beta particle","2 photons of gamma rays","2 beta particles","4 beta particles","4 photons of gamma rays"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following will reduce the frequency of oscillation of a simple pendulum?","options":["Decreasing the length of the string","Increasing the amplitude of oscillation","Increasing the length of the string","Increasing the mass of the bob","Reducing the mass of the bob."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A box is pulled a distance s along a smooth horizontal floor by a force of magnitude F, inclined at an angle \u03b8 to the horizontal. The work done is","options":["Fs cos \u03b8","Fs cosec \u03b8","Fs sec \u03b8","Fs sin \u03b8","Fs tan \u03b8"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following is\/are longitudinal wave(s)? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. Light waves from the sun<br>\r\nII. Sound waves in the air<br>\r\nIII. Waves on a vibrating string","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","I and III only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is\/are correct? Sound waves travel through<br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. air<br>\r\nII. vacuum <br>\r\nIII.Water","options":["II only","I and II only","II and III only","I and III only","I, II, and III"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"An electric motor primary converts","options":["electrical energy to chemical energy","electrical energy to heat energy","electrical energy to mechanical energy","mechanical energy to electrical energy","mechanical energy to light energy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Radio receivers are tuned using","options":["electromagnets","electric motors","Inductors","variable capacitors","variable resistors"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Three non-parallel coplanar forces which can be represented both in magnitude and direction by the three sides of a triangle taken in order will","options":["have any one force being the equilibrant of the other two","make a body move randomly","make a body oscillate","move a body along a straight line","rotate a body about its axis"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"A constant force acts on a body of mass 50kg and changes its speed from 20ms<sup>-1<\/sup> to 90ms<sup>-1<\/sup> in 10 seconds. Calculate the magnitude of the force applied.","options":["590N","500N","450N","350N","180N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a component of a slide projector?","options":["Concave mirror","Condenser","Convex mirror","light source","Screen."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"Notes of the same frequency sounded on a guitar and trumpet may differ in <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. loudness <br>\r\nII. Pitch<br>\r\nIII. quality Which of the statements above is correct?","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and II only","I, II and III"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The amplitude of oscillation of a simple pendulum bob diminishes slowly because","options":["energy is applied by some external agencies","frictional forces dissipate the energy of motion","the frequency of oscillation increases with the mass of the bob","the frequency of oscillation varies with time","the period of oscillation varies with time."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The wave theory of light does not explain photoelectricity because","options":["light waves carry little energy","particles cannot be emitted by waves","the frequency of light waves too high","there is a threshold wavelength for electron emission","the wavelength of Light waves is too short."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The most suitable instrument for measuring the diameter of a thin wire is a","options":["meter rule","micrometer screw gauge","pair of dividers","pair of engineer\u2019s calipers","venire calipers"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"The molecular structure of a liquid is such that","options":["the molecules have unlimited freedom of movement","molecular movement is restricted to vibration only","intermolecular collisions take place","all molecules moves move with the same speed",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the mass and the weight of a body is not correct? its","options":["mass is a scalar quantity","weight is a function of the gravitational pull on it","mass on earth and on the moon is the same","weigh at the equatior and at the poles is the same",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"An object weighs 60.0N in air, 48.2N in a certain liquid X, and 44.9N in water, Calculate the relative density of X","options":["3.300","1.279","0.932","0.782",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Calculate the change in volume when 90g of ice is completely melted. [density of water = 1g cm<sup>-3<\/sup>, density of ice = 0.9cm<sup>-3<\/sup>]","options":["0.00cm<sup>3<\/sup>","9.00cm<sup>3<\/sup>","10.00cm<sup>3<\/sup>","90.00cm<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following concept is not an evidence of the particle nature of matter?","options":["diffusion","brownian motion","diffraction","crystallization",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A diver is 5.2m below the surface of water of density 1000Kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>. If the atmospheric pressure is 1.02 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>pa. Calculate the pressure on the diver [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["6.20 x 10<sup>4<\/sup> pa","1.02 x 10<sup>5<\/sup> pa","1.54 x 10<sup>5<\/sup> pa","5.20 x 10<sup>5<\/sup> pa",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A steel needle floating on water, sinks when kerosine is added to the water. This is because the kerosine","options":["increased the surface tension of the water","reduces the density of the water","reduces the surface tension of the water","reduces the upthrust on the needle",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"On which of the following factor does the viscosity of a liquid depend?  i. Nature of the liquid.  ii. Temperature of the liquid.  iii. Area of the liquid surface","options":["i and ii only","ii and iii only","i and iii only","i, ii and iii",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"An elastic string of force constant 200N m<sup>-1<\/sup> is stretched through 0.8m within its elastic limit. Calculate the energy stored in the string","options":["64.0J","80.0J","128.0J","160.0J",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A machine of velocity ratio 5 is used in lifting a load with an effort of 500N. If the machine is 80% efficient. Determine the magnitude of load","options":["2500N","2000N","900N","625N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The speed of an object in rectilinear motion can be determine from the","options":["area under a velocity-time graph","area under a distance-time graph","slope of a distance-time graph","slope of a velocity-time graph",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A body is said to be moving with uniform acceleration if it experiences equal","options":["increase in velocity at equal time intervals","decreases in velocity at equal time intervals","increases in speed at equal time intervals","decreases in speed at equal time intervals",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A body of mass 8kg moving with a speed of 30ms<sup>-1<\/sup> is brought to rest in 2.5s by a constant retarding force. Calculate the magnitude of the force","options":["240N","96N","20N","9N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A force acting on a body causes a change in the momentum of the body from 12kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup> to 16kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup> in 0.2s. calculate the magnitude of the force","options":["140.0N","20.0N","4.0N","0.8N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The bob of a single pendulum has a mass of 0.02kg. Determine the weight of the bob [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["0.02N","0.20N","20.00N","200.00N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A ball bearing is projected vertically upwards from the ground with a velocity of 15ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Calculate the time taken by the ball to return to the ground [g = 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["1.5s","3.0s","5.0s","7.5s",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A loaded spring performs simple harmonic motion with an amplitude of 5cm. If the maximum acceleration of the load is 20cm s<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the angular frequency of the motion","options":["2 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>","4 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>","5 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>","10 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"When compared with water, mercury is preferred as a thermometric liquid because","options":["has a higher density","has lower specific heat capacity","exhibits anomalous thermal expansion","contains molecules which have very strong adhensive forces",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following values on the absolute scale of temperature is the ice point?","options":["0K","32K","100K","273k",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"On a cold day, a concrete floor feels colder to the bear foot then a mat on the same floor because the","options":["is better conductor of heat than the foot","mat loses heat to the bare foot at a faster rate","mat is better conductor of heat than the floor","concrete floor is a better conductor of heat than the mat",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"When a metal ball is heated through 30<sup>o<\/sup>C,its volume becomes 1.0018cm<sup>3<\/sup>. If the linear expansivity of the material of the ball is 2.0 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate its original volume","options":["1.0000cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.0020cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.0036cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.0180cm<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A faulty barometer reads 72.6cm Hg when the atmospheric pressure is 75.0cm Hg. Calculate the atmospheric pressure when the barometer reads 72.0cn Hg","options":["79.4cm Hg","74.38cm Hg","74.2cm Hg","69.4cm Hg",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"On a basis of the kinetic theory, an increase in the temperature of a fixed volume of an ideal gas causes","options":["a incease in the number of gas molecules","a decrease in the density of the gass","an increase in the average speed of the gas molecules","a decrease in pressure exerted by the gas",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The temperature of 900cm<sup>3<\/sup> of an ideal gas at a pressure of 114cm Hg is 27<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate its volume at 76cm Hg and 0<sup>o<\/sup>C","options":["50.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","546.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","659.3cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1228.5cm<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The basic difference between a transverse wave and a longitudinal wave travelling in the same direction in a medium is in the","options":["amplitude of the wave","wavelength of the wave","direction of vibration of the particles of the medium","period of vibration of the particle of the medium",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A wave travelling from water to glass suffers a change in its speed at the common boundary. Which of the following properties explains this observation?","options":["dispersion","refraction","interference","diffraction",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The image of an optical pin placed at the principal focus of a concave mirror will be formed","options":["between the principal focus and the pole","at the centre of the curvature","between the principal focus and the centre of curvature","at infinity",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A man 1.8m tall stands 3m away from a pin hole camera. If the distance between the pin hole and the screen of the camera is 0.3m. Calculate the height of the image of the man produced by the camera","options":["0.18m","0.50m","1.62m","18.00m",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"During a thunderstorm, lightning and thunder occurred simultaneously in the atmosphere. An observer on the earth surface's sees the lightning flash shortly before hearing the thunder. This is because the","options":["atmospheric pressure is higher at the surface than at the higher altitudes","speed of sound is less than that of light","temperature of the atmosphere decreases with altitude","atmospheric density decreases with altitude",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A magnified and virtual image of a near object is produced by","options":["prism binoculas","astronomical telescope","periscope","simple microscope",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A girl stand 80m away from a tall cliff and blows a whistle. If the speed of sound in air is 330ms<sup>-1<\/sup>, how long would it take for her to hear the echo of the sound?","options":["2.062s","0.970s","0.485s","0.242s",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following reasons explains why the walls and ceilings of a standard concert hall are usually covered with perforated pads? To","options":["increase the intensity of sound waves","increases the loudness of the sound waves","reduce the effect of revibration of sound waves","decreases thr frequency of sound waves",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The sound from a vibrating tuning sound is when the tip of its stem is placed on a wooden table than when in air because","options":["the friction between the table and the tuning fork generates additional energy","air molecules obsorb sound wave but wood transmit sound waves","the table increases the frequency of the turning fork","a large mass of air is set into vibration by the table",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Charges on a conductor are","options":["evenly distributed over a surface of any shape","concentrate on the inner surface of the conductor","concentrate at the outer flat surface of the conductor","generally concentrated at sharply curved surface",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of following functions is performed by manganese IV oxide in the Lenclanche cell?","options":["control of local action","depolarisation of the cell","regulating current flow in the cell","reduction of the internal resistance of the cell",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A car fuse marked 3A operates optimally on a 12V battery, calculate the resistance of the fuse","options":["36.0\\(\\Omega\\)","15.0\\(\\Omega\\)","9.0\\(\\Omega\\)","4.0\\(\\Omega\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Find the cost of running a 60W lamp for 24 hours. If 1kW hr cost 5 naira","options":["14.4 naira","12.5 naira","7.2 naira","2.0 naira",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The quantity of electric charge stored in a capacitor is measured in","options":["farad","ampere","coulomb","volt",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Calculate  the energy stored in a 20\\(\\mu F\\) capacitor. If the p.d between the plates is 40V","options":["3.2 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>J","1.6  x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>J","8.0  x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","4.0  x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>J",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Given that the gravitational constant is G. Newton's universal law of gravitation states that the force of attraction between two masses M<sub>1<\/sub> and M<sub>2<\/sub> separation by a distance r is","options":["\\(Gr^2 M_1M_2\\)","\\(Gr M_1M_2\\)","\\(\\frac{GM_1 M_2}{r^2}\\)","\\(\\frac{GM_1 M_2}{r}\\)",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A charge of 1.6 x 10<sup>-10<\/sup>C is placed in a uniform electric field of intensity 2.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup> NC<sup>-1<\/sup>. calculate the magnitude of the electric force exerted on the change","options":["3.2 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>N","1.8 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>N","3.2 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>N","1.8 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>N",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct?","options":["a magnetic  field is a region in which a magnetic force will be detected","a magnetic line of force is a path along which a magnetic fields are scalar quantities it were free","magnetic fields are scalar quantities","neutral point are obtained where the earth's magnetic force is exactly equal and opposite to that due to a magnet",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The main function of the mouth piece of a telephone is that it converts sound energy to","options":["mechanical energy","electrical energy","chemical energy","thermal energy",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"An atom is normally electrically neutral because the","options":["number of electrons is equal to the number of protons","number of electrons is equal to the number of neutrons","number of protons is equal to the number of neutrons","electrons of the atom are buried deeply in the nucleus",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"In which of the following devices is the principle of photoelectric effect not applicable?","options":["close-circuit television camera","burglar alarm","solar cells","periscope",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about X-rays is not correct? They","options":["are electromagnetic waves","can be used to study crystal lattice","can destroy living cells","are produced from the nucleus of an atom",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A radioactive substance has a half-life of 3 days. If a mass of 1.55g of this substance is left after decaying for 15 days, determine the original value of the mass","options":["49.6g","37.2g","24.8g","12.4g",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following representations is correct for an atom X with 28 electrons and 30 neutrons?","options":["\\(^{30}_{28} X\\)","\\(^{28}_{30} X\\)","\\(^{58}_{30} X\\)","\\(^{58}_{28} X\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of these expresses the relationship between the earth\u2019s magnetic field FE, and the field\u2019 FB due to a magnet at neutral points? FE is","options":["equal and opposite to F<sup>B<\/sup>","equal to and in the same direction with F<sup>B<\/sup>","greater than and in the same direction with F<sub>B<\/sub>","greater than and opposite to F<sub>B<\/sub>","less than and opposite to F<sub>B<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A voltage supply of 12V r.m.s. and frequency 90Hz is connected to a 4 \u03c9 resistor. Calculate the peak value of the current","options":["48.8 A","30.0 A","27.5 A","4.2 A","3.0A"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"How far from a hill should a boy stand to hear the echo of his clap 1 .6s later? [Speed of sound in air is 340ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["186m","272m","544m","1088m","2000m"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the statements about prism binoculars is\/are correct? They <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. are a pair of two telescopes mounted side by side <br>\r\nII. reduce the optical path of the light ray from the objective to the eye piece <br>\r\nIII, present inverted and diminished image to the viewer <br>\r\nIV. present erect and magnified image to the viewer.","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","I, II and IV only","II, III and IV only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A body of mass 40g loses 80J of heat energy. If the specific heat capacity of the body is 400 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the change in temperature of the body.","options":["0.2K","0.4K","2.0K","5.0K","10.0K"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A force F is applied to a body P as shown in the diagram above. If the body moves through a distance, a, which of the following represents the work done?","options":["Fa","Fa Cos \u03b8","\\(\\frac{Fa}{\\cos \\theta}\\)","FaSin \u03b8","\\(\\frac{Fa}{\\sin \\theta}\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"In which of these fields are repulsive forces NOT experienced? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. Magnetic field <br>\r\nII. Gravitational field <br>\r\nIII. Electric field","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and III only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The component of a vector in a given direction is","options":["equal to the magnitude of the resultant vector in that direction","equal to the magnitude of the resultant vector in the opposite direction","its effective magnitude","its effective value in that direction","its effective value in the opposite direction"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A plane which is Inclined at an angle of 30 \u00b0 to the horizontal has a velocity ratio of","options":["2","1","0.87","0.67","0.5"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A mass of 5kg is suspended from the ceiling of a lift with a light inextensible string. As the lift moves upwards with an acceleration of 2ms<sup>-2<\/sup>, the tension in the string is [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["25N","40N","50N","60N","70N"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT an example of a percussion instrument?","options":["Bell","Drum","Flute","Gong","Xylophone"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The time t<sub>1<\/sub>, t<sub>2<\/sub> and t<sub>3<\/sub> for 20 complete oscillations of a simple pendulum experiment are 32.0s, 34.6s and 35.5s respectively. Calculate the mean period of the pendulum.","options":["1.60s","1.70s","1.73s","1.78s","5.11s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Calculate the magnitude of the electric field intensity in vacuum at a distance of 25cm from a charge of 5 \u00d7 10<sup>-3<\/sup>C. [Take 1\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>0<\/sub>]","options":["7.2 \u00d7 108NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.8 \u00d7 108NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.6 \u00d7 108NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","3.6 \u00d7 108NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.5 \u00d7 106NC<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The temperature at which the water vapour present in the air is just enough to saturate the air is the _______ point.","options":["boiling","critical","dew","ice","steam"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The frequency of a body executing simple harmonic motion when left undisturbed is known as__________ frequency.","options":["damped","forced","free","natural","sinusoidal"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"When very hot water is poured into a thin-walled glass container, it is less likely to break because","options":["all parts of the container got heated-uniformly","glass can withstand a very high temperature","the molecules of glass are too far apart to cause breakages of the container","the outer part of the container is cooler than the inner part","thin glass does not expand fast"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"An electron makes a transition from - 1.60 eV energy level to - 10.4eV energy level Calculate the energy loss due to the transition.","options":["16.64eV","12.00eV","10.40eV","8.80eV","6.50eV"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which to the following is NOT a fundamental unit?","options":["Ampere","Kelvin","Kilogramme","Newton","Second"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"For total internal reflection to occur,<br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. light must be travelling from an optically more dense to an optically less dense medium. <br>\r\nII. the angle of incidence in the denser medium must be greater than its critical angle.<br>\r\nIII. the angle of refraction in the less dense medium must be equal to 90 \u00b0. Which of the statements above is\/are correct?","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and II only","II and III only."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A note, A from a guitar produces a wave of amplitude 4 mm and frequency 1000 Hz. Another note, B from a whistle produces a similar waveform of amplitude 2 mm and frequency 2200 Hz. If the two notes are compared,","options":["A has a higher pitch than B","A is louder than B.","B has a greater speed than A","B is louder than A","A and B have the same quality"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Calculate the wavelength of light travelling with a speed of 3 \u00d7 108ms<sup>-1<\/sup> and a frequency of 6.2 \u00d7 10<sup>14<\/sup>Hz.","options":["4.8 \u00d7 10<sup>-8<\/sup>m","4.8 \u00d7 10<sup>-7<\/sup>m","4.8 \u00d7 10<sup>-6<\/sup>m","4.8 \u00d7 10<sup>-5<\/sup>m","4.8 \u00d7 10<sup>-4<\/sup>m"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"What is the uncertainty in the measurement of time, if the uncertainty in measuring the energy of an electron of mass 10<sup>-30<\/sup> kg is 2.45 \u00d7 10<sup>-19<\/sup>J? h = 6.6 \u00d7 10<sup>-34<\/sup>","options":["1.35 \u00d710<sup>-15<\/sup>s","2.69 \u00d7 10<sup>-15<\/sup>s","4.15 \u00d7 10<sup>-15<\/sup>s","9.05 \u00d7 10<sup>-15<\/sup>s","1.62 \u00d7 10<sup>-14<\/sup>s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A body has masses of 0.013kg and 0.012 kg in oil and water respectively. If the relative density of oil is 0.875 calculate the mass of the body.","options":["0.02 kg","0.03kg","0.04kg","0.05kg","0.06kg"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A stone is dropped from the top of a tower of height 11 .25m. Calculate the time it will take to reach the ground. [g = 10ms-2]","options":["1.00s","1.50s","2.25s","2.50s","3.00s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The rate of diffusion of gases increases with increase(s) in <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. density<br>\r\nII. temperature <br>\r\nIII, mass. Which is\/are correct?","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","II and III only","I, II and III"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"In which of the following are crystalline structures observable? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. Gas <br>\r\nII. Liquid <br>\r\nIII. Solid","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and III only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Heat <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. is a form of energy <br>\r\nII. is measured with a thermometer<br>\r\nIII. cannot be created or destroyed<br>\r\nIV. from a hot object is transferred through conduction only. Which of the statements above are correct?","options":["I and II only","I and III only","I, II and III only","II, III and IV only","I, II, III and IV"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"When the same amount of current, I is passed through different wires under the same conditions, the rates of production of heat are","options":["directly proportional to I","directly proportional to the resistances of the wires","directly proportional to the square of the resistances of the wires","inversely proportional to I","inversely proportional to the resistance of the wires"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Emission spectra are caused by","options":["kinetic energy of moving atoms","potential energy of an electron in an atom","transition of an electron from a higher energy level to a lower energy level","transition of an electron from a lower energy level to higher energy level","transition of excited protons in the nucleus."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"Which of the following is used as a depolarizer in a Denial cell?","options":["Ammonium chloride","Copper (II) tetra Oxo sulphate (VI) solution","Manganese (IV) oxide","Tetraoxo sulphate (VI) acid","Water"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A radioactive isotope has a half-life of 8 days. What fraction of the atoms will remain after 72 days?","options":["9.766 \u00d7 10<sup>-4<\/sup>","1.736 \u00d710<sup>-3<\/sup>","1.953 \u00d710<sup>-3<\/sup>","3.472 \u00d7 10<sup>-3<\/sup>","3.906 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"If the distance between the plates of a parallel plate capacitor is decreased, its capacitance","options":["becomes zero","decreases","increases","is halved","remains the same"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A ray of light experiences a minimum deviation when passing through an equilateral triangular glass prism. Calculate the angle of incidence of the ray. [Refractive index of glass = 1.5]","options":["300.0\u00b0","48.6\u00b0","60.0\u00b0","75.5\u00b0","105.0 \u00b0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"The relative density of dilute tetraoxosulphate (vi) acid in a battery is measured with a","options":["barometer","hydrometer","manometer","hypsometer",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2004"},{"question":"A tuber of cassava can be processed into powder. This explains the face that","options":["matter can change sponteneously from one state to another","matter cannot be destroyed","force is required to change natter from one state to another","matter is made up of tiny particle",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A piece of metal of relative density 5.0 weighs 60N in air. Calculate its weight when fully immersed in water","options":["4N","5N","48N","60N",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The tendency of a body to remain at least when a force is supplied to it is called","options":["impulse","momentum","inertia","friction",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A force acts on a body for 0.5s changing its momentum from 16.0kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup> to 21.0kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the magnitude of the force","options":["42.0N","37.0N","32.0N","10.0N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A moving object is said to have a uniform acceleration if its","options":["displacement decreases at a constant rate","speed is directly proportional with time","velocity increases by equal amount in equal time intervals","velocity varies inversely with time",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The period of an oscillatory motion is defined as the","options":["average of the time used in completing different numbers of oscillations","time to complete a number of oscillations","time to complete one oscillation","time taken to move from one extreme position to another",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The mass on a loaded spiral spring oscillates vertically between two extreme positions P and R equidistant from the equilibrium position Q. Which of the following statements about the system is not correct","options":["the momentum of the mass is maximum at Q","the elastic potential energy of the spring is maximum at Q","the kinetic energy of the mass is maximum at P","the total energy of the system is always constant",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A ball f mass 5.0kg hits a smooth vertical wall normally with a speed of 2ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Determine the magnitude of the resulting impulse","options":["2.0kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","10.0kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.0kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.5kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statements correctly defines a simple machine? a device","options":["that can provide electric current","which can only carry people from one place to another","with which work can be done easily","which changes the state of rest or of uniform motion of an object along a straight ine",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A platinum resistance thermometer has a resistance 4\\(\\Omega\\) at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 100\\(\\Omega\\) at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C. Assuming the resistance changes uniformly with temperature. Calculate the resistance of the thermometer when the temperature is 45<sup>o<\/sup>C","options":["14.0\\(\\Omega\\)","6.7\\(\\Omega\\)","3.2\\(\\Omega\\)","2.7\\(\\Omega\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"a metal rod of length 100cm is heated through 100<sup>o<\/sup>C, calculate the change in length of the rod [linear expansivity of the material of the rod is 3 x 10<sup>-6<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["4mm","3mm","2mm","1mm",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The heat capacity of a calorimeter is the amount of energy required to","options":["change the temperature of 1kg of the calorimeter by 1k","change 1kg mass of the calorimeter to liquid at the same temperature","change the temperature of the calorimeter","melt the calorimeter into liquid at a constant temperature",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statement about latent heat of vaporization is correct? It","options":["weakens the adhesive force between molecules of a liquid and those of its container","breaks completely the force of attraction completely between the molecules of a liquid","add to the heat content of a liquid","increases the cohesive forces between liquid molecules",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"When the pressure of a fixed mass of gas is doubled at constant temperature, the volume of the gas is","options":["increased four times","doubled","unchangeable","halved",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The volume of a given mass of an ideal gas at 327k and 9.52 x 10<sup>4<\/sup> Pa is 40cm<sup>3<\/sup>. calculate the volume of the gas at 273k and 1.034 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>Pa.","options":["68.23cm<sup>3<\/sup>","47.91cm<sup>3<\/sup>","44.60cm<sup>3<\/sup>","30.75cm<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A wave of weight length 0.30m travels 900m in 3.0s, calculate its frequency","options":["68.0Hz","225.0Hz","1000Hz","750.0Hz",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following condition is necessary for the occurrence of total internal reflection of light?","options":["light must travel from an optical less dense to a denser medium","the angle of incidence must be equal to the critical angle","the angle of incidence must be greater than the critical angle","the angle of refraction must be 90<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The image which cannot be formed on a screen is said to be","options":["inverted","erect","real","virtual",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"An object is placed on the principal axis and at the centre of curvature of a concave mirror, the image of the image formed by the mirror is","options":["real and magnified","real and inverted","erect and magnified","erect and virtual",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A converging lens produces an image four times as large as an object placed 25cm from the lens. Calculate its focal length","options":["100cm","33cm","29cm","20cm",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The horizontal floor of a water reservoir appears to be 1.0m deep when viewed vertically from above. If the refractive index of water is 1.35, calculate the real depth of the reservoir","options":["2.35m","1.35m","1.00m","0.35m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A converging lens has a focal length of 5cm. Determine its power","options":["+20.0","+0.2","-20.00","-0.2",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following pairs of rays shows the widest separation in the spectrum of white light?","options":["green and blue","orange and indigo","blue and violet","red and yellow",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the human eye and the camera is correct?","options":["both form virtual image of objects","the image formed by the eye is upright in the retina while that formed by the camera is inverted on the film","the inside of both of them is blackened to absorb unwanted light","the focal length of both eye lens and the camera lens can be varied",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The speed of sound in air is is directly proportional to","options":["its temperature on the celsius scale","ite temperature in the thermodynamic scale","the cube root of its temperature on its celcius csale","the square roor of its temperature on the absolute scale",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A sonometer wire of linear density 0.08kg m<sup>-1<\/sup> subjected to a tension of 800N is plucked. Calculate the speed of a pulse which moves from one end of the wire to the other","options":["179.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","100.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","15.8ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","8.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following instruments gives a pure note when sounded?","options":["talking drum","siren","tunning fork","guitar",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following features of an electrostatic line of force is not correct?","options":["it is an imaginary line which a positive charge will describe if it is free to move","the tangent drawn at any point on a curved line of force shows the direction of the electric field intensity at that point","it is sometimes curved","it can cross another line of force in a region of intense electric field",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statement about force is correct ?","options":["electrostatic, gravitational and magnetic forces are always attractive","electric, gravitational and magnetic field obeys inverse square law","field lines are real but their corresponding field are imaginary","field lines and their corresponding fields are both real",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A positively charged glass rod is placed by near the cap of a positively charge electroscope. The divergence of the leaf is observed to","options":["decrease","increase","remain the same","increase and collapse immediately",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Two identical cells each of e.m.f 2v and internal resistance 1.0\\(\\Omega\\) are connected in parallel. The combination is connected to an external load of 1.5\\(\\Omega\\). Calculate the current in the circuit","options":["0.57A","1.00A","1.14A","2.00A",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following factors does not affect the the electric resistance of a wire?","options":["length","mass","temperature","cross sectional area",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A current of 10A passes through a conductor for 10s, calculate the charge flowing through the conductor","options":["100.0C","10.0C","1.0C","0.1C",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A lamp is rated 240V 60W, calculate the resistance of its filament","options":["240\\(\\Omega\\)","360\\(\\Omega\\)","960\\(\\Omega\\)","1440\\(\\Omega\\)",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The maximum power dissipated by a 100\\(\\Omega\\) resistor in a circuit is 4W. Calculate the voltage across the resistor","options":["10V","20V","25V","400V",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"One difference between a reactance and a resistance in an alternating current circuit is","options":["resistance is larger than reactance","energy is not diaaipated in a reactance","energy is stored in a resistance but not in a reactance","the current in a reactance is lower than in the resistance",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The direction of induced current in a straight wire placed in magnetic field is determined by using","options":["Fleming's right hand rule","Maxwell's screw rule","Faraday's law","Lenz's law",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about an electromagnet is correct?","options":["it is a temporary magnet","its strength depends on the current","its stength depends on the number of turns in its coil","it has permanent poles",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not true of the isotopes of an element? They","options":["are atoms of the same element","have the same chemical properties","have the same atomic number","have the same mass number",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is true of ultra violet radiations? It","options":["supports the sensation of hearing","does not cause the emission of electrons from metals","is an electromagnetic wave","is not capable of causing sun burns",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A radioactive element has a decay constant of 0.077s<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate its half life","options":["12.5s","9.0s","5.1s","0.5s",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The minimum energy required to remove an electron from an atom is known as","options":["excitation energy","ionization energy","binding energy","photon energy",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Nuclear fission is preferred to nuclear fusion in the generation of energy because","options":["very high temperature are required for fusion","the raw material of fusion are not easily obtained","energy obtained from fusion is relatively smaller","the by product of fusion are very dangerous",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following reactions represents nuclear fusion?","options":["\\(^2_1H + ^2_1H \\to ^3_2He + ^1_0n\\)","\\(^235_92U + ^1_0n \\to ^145_56Ba + ^90_36Kr \\)","\\(^234_90TH \\to ^0_-1n + ^3_2He + ^1_0Pa\\)","\\(^238_92U \\to ^4_2H \\to ^3_2He + ^234_90Th\\)",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Young\u2019s modulus of elasticity is the ratio of stress to strain, provided the load does not exceed the","options":["breaking point","elastic limit","plastic limit","stress limit","yield point"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following instruments can be used to measure e.m.f. most accurately.","options":["Ammeter","Galvanometer","Metre bridge","Potentiometer","Voltmeter"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Evaporation of a liquid produces cooling of the liquid because the","options":["attraction between the vapour molecules and the liquid molecules is great","average kinetic energy of the liquid is reduced","density of the liquid decreases","vapour pressure above the liquid rises","volume of the liquid decreases"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Calculate the amount of heat generated in an external load of resistance 8\u03a9 if an alternating current of peak value 5 A is passed through it for 100s.","options":["2.0 \u00d7 10<sup>4<\/sup>J","1.0 \u00d7 10<sup>4<\/sup>J","5.0 \u00d7 10<sup>3<\/sup>J","4.0 \u00d7 10<sup>3<\/sup>J","2.0 \u00d7 10<sup>2<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"For which of the following sets are the units fundamental?","options":["Area, length and volume","Impulse, mass and time","Length, time and mass","Velocity, distance and time","Volume, mass and density"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"How much heat is required to convert 50g of water at 100\u00b0C to steam at the same temperature? (Specific latent heat of vaporization of water = 2260 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>1)","options":["1.13 \u00d7 10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","1.31 \u00d7 10<sup>2<\/sup>J","1.30 \u00d7 10<sup>4<\/sup>J","1.13 \u00d7 10<sup>5<\/sup>J","1.31 \u00d7 10<sup>6<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following radiations have the longest wavelength?","options":["Gamma rays","Infra-red","Light waves","Radio waves","Ultra-violet rays"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Lines of force <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. Begin and end on equal and opposite electric charges.<br>\r\nII. are in state of tension which causes them to shorten <br>\r\nIII. attract one another.<br>\r\n<br>\r\nWhich of the statement(s) is\/are correct?","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and II only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A wire of length 100cm and cross-sectional area 2.0 \u00d7 10<sup>-3<\/sup>cm<sup>2<\/sup> has a resistance of 0.10 \u03c9. Calculate its electrical conductively.","options":["2.0 \u00d7 10-6 \u03c9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.0 \u00d7 10-5 \u03c9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0 \u00d7 106 \u03c9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.0 \u00d7 106 \u03c9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.0 \u00d7 107 \u03c9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"\\(^{226}_{88}Ra\\) \\(\\to\\) \\(^{222}_{866}Rn\\) + X + Energy. The equation above represents a nuclear decay of radium isotope. What is X?","options":["Alpha particle","Beta particle","Gamma ray","Neutron","X \u2013 ray"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A body that produces its own light is said to be","options":["luminous","non-incandescent","opaque","translucent","transparent"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Two equal capacitances are connected first in series and then in parallel. The ratio of the effective series capacitance to the effective parallel capacitance is","options":["0.25","0.50","1.00","2.20","4.00"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The resistance of a series R-C circuit is 5 \u03c9 If the impedance of the circuit is 13 \u03c9 calculate the reactance of the capacitor","options":["12 \u03a9","14 \u03a9","16 \u03a9","18 \u03a9","65 \u03a9"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The motion of the prongs of a sounding turning fork is","options":["circular","oscillatory","random","rotational","translational"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A constant force of 5N acts for 5s on a mass of 5kg initially at rest. Calculate the final momentum of the mass.","options":["125 kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","75 kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","25 kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","20 kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>","5 kgms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A stone is released from a height of 80m above the ground. Calculate its velocity just before it strikes the ground. (g=10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["25ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","40 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","55 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","65ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","80 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The S.l unit of magnetic flux density is","options":["farad","henry","kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>","tesla","weber"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A narrow, uniform glass tube, closed at one end, constains air which is sealed by a thread of mercury. The tube is placed first horizontally and then vertically with the open end at the top. Which of the following statements is correct?","options":["The length of the entrapped air in the horizontal position is less than that in the vertical position","The length of the entrapped air in the vertical position is less than that in the horizontal position","The length of the mercury column becomes shorter in the horizontal position than in the vertical position","The length of the mercury column becomes shorter in the vertical position than in the horizontal position","The pressure of the entrapped air is atmospheric in both cases."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following motions will be produced by a pair of equal, opposite and non-collinear parallel forces acting on a body?","options":["Oscillatory","Random","Rotational","Translational","Vibratory"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The inability of the eye to focus near objects is known as","options":["astigmatism","eye ring","hypermetropia","myopia","presbyopia"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A platinum-resistance thermometer has a resistance of 4\u03a9  at 0\u00b0C and 12\u03a9 at 100\u00b0C. Assuming that the resistance changes uniformly with temperature. Calculate the resistance of the thermometer when the temperature is 45\u00b0C.","options":["6.0\u03a9","6.42\u03a9","7.6\u03a9","8.4\u03a9","16.0\u03a9"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Calculate the critical angle for light travelling from water to air. (Refractive index of water = 1.33)","options":["36.9\u00b0","41.3\u00b0","48.8\u00b0","49.2\u00b0","51.4\u00b0"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A short chain is usually attached to the rear side of petro tanker trailing behind it to ensure that the","options":["charges generated by friction in the tanker are conducted to the earth","chain vibrates in resonance with the tanker\u2019s engine","heat generated by friction in the engine is conducted to the earth","petrol tanker is balanced on the road","tanker does not exceed a certain speed limit"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A transformer is required to give 120V from a 240V mains supply. If the primary has 5500 turns, how many turns has the secondary?","options":["232","450","550","2750","11000"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The distance between two successive crests of a water wave is 0.5m. If a particle on the surface of the water wave makes two complete vertical oscillations in 1s, calculate the speed of the wave.","options":["0.25ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.50ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.00ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.00ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.00ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"In 90 seconds, the mass of a radioactive element reduces to \\(\\frac{1}{16}\\) of its original value. Determine the half- life of the element.","options":["15.0s","18.0s","22.5s","30.0s","45.0s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the concept of solid friction is NOT true?","options":["It always acts in the direction of motion","It causes wear and tear in car tyres","It depends on the nature of the surfaces in contact","It is independent of the area of the surfaces in contact.","It reduces the efficiency of the machine"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The space surrounding a magnet in which the magnetic force is exerted is","options":["magnetic field","magnetic flux","magnetic point","magnetic pole","magnetic strength"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following scientists postulated that moving particles exhibit wave properties?","options":["Ernest Rutherford","Erwin Schroedinger","Frank Hertz","Louis de Broglie","Werner Heisenberg."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The mode of transference of heat which does not require any material medium is","options":["conduction","convection","evaporation","radiation","transmission"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The area under the curve of a velocity time graph represents","options":["acceleration","distance covered","instantaneous speed","time taken","work done"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A body is launched from the earth\u2019s surface, of radius R, so that it just escapes from the gravitational influence of the earth; If the gravitational constant is G and the mass of the earth is M, what is the escape velocity of the boby.","options":["\\(\\sqrt{2GM}\\) \u00f7 R","\\(\\frac{\\sqrt{2GM}}{R}\\)","\\(\\frac{\\sqrt{2G}}{MR}\\)","\\(\\sqrt{2GMR}\\)","\\(\\frac{\\sqrt{R}}{2GM}\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A ball of mass m moving at velocity u collides with another ball of equal mass at rest. If the two balls move off together after the impact, calculate their common velocity.","options":["\\(\\frac{u}{v}\\)","\\(\\frac{mu}{2}\\)","u","2u","\\(\\frac{u}{m}\\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statement(s) is\/are correct? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. When a liquid expands its density falls <br>\r\nII. When a mercury-in-glass thermometer is placed in a hot liquid, the mercury level first descends and then rises.<br>\r\nIII. The apparent expansion of a liquid is greater than its real expansion.","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and II only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statement(s) is\/are correct about the isotopes of an elements? They have the same <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. chemical properties <br>\r\nII. nucleon number <br>\r\nIII proton number","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","I and III only","I,II and III"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Lenz\u2019s law of electromagnetic induction states that","options":["a force is exerted on a current carrying conductor in a magnetic field","the induced current in a conductor is in such a direction as to oppose the change producing it","the magnitude of the induced electromotive force in a circuit is proportional to the rate of change of the number of lines of force linking the circuit","the magnitude of the induced electromotive force is proportional to the current producing the magnetic flux","whenever there is a change in the magnetic flux linked with the circuit, an electromotive is induced"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"An object is placed 30 cm in front of a concave mirror of focal length 20cm. Calculate the distance between the object and the image.","options":["90cm","40cm","30cm","20cm","10cm"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following properties is NOT exhibited by sound waves?","options":["Diffraction","interference","Polarisation","Reflection","Refraction"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"An evidence of the wave nature of matter is","options":["Browniam motion","Compton effect","diffraction","diffusion","photo electricity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"J.J. Thomson\u2019s model of the atom was abandoned because","options":["it could not explain the scattering of alpha particles","it did not account for the neutron","it did not account for the size of the atom","it was known as plum-pudding model","the model was not similar to any observable phenomena"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Water in an open container boils at a lower temperature when heated at the top of a mountain than at sea-level because at the top of a mountain","options":["pressure is increased","pressure is reduced","the rays of the sun add more heat to the water","the saturation vapour pressure of water is higher than at sea-level","the temperature is lower than at sea-level"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The volume of a given mass of gas is 40cm<sup>3<\/sup> at 27\u00b0 C. What is its volume at 90\u00b0 C if its pressure remains constant?","options":["32.84cm<sup>3<\/sup>","40.02cm<sup>3<\/sup>","48.40cm<sup>3<\/sup>","57.44cm<sup>3<\/sup>","72.84cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is NOT true?","options":["A lead-acid accumulator can deliver a large current because of its very large internal resistance.","A secondary cell can be recharged.","As a lead-acid accumulator is being charged, the density of the acid in it increases.","The chemical action in a primary cell is irreversible.","The conventional current in a circuit rlows from the positive to the negative terminal of the battery."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"A sheet of white paper viewed through blue glass appears blue because","options":["blue is a primary colour","the glass absorbs all colours except the blue colour","the glass reflects blue colour","the paper reflects blue colour only","white light is easily absorbed by the glass"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2003"},{"question":"The force between the molecules of a liquid in contact with that of a solid is","options":["adhesive","cohesive","magnetic","repulsive",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A reservoir is filled with a liquid of density 2000kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>. Calculate the depth at which the pressure in the liquid will equal to 9100Nm<sup>-2<\/sup> [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["0.262m","0.455m","0.664m","0.819m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A solid weight 45N and 15N respectively in air and water. Determine the relative density of the solid","options":["0.33","0.50","1.50","3.00",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"One common characteristics of solids, liquids and gasses is that","options":["all the three has fixed volume","their molecule have the same size","their molecules are always in motion","all the three have the same inter molecular forces",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The magnitude of the force required to make an object of mass, m move with speed, v in a circular of radius r is given by the expression","options":["\\(\\frac{mr}{v}\\)","\\(\\frac{mr^2}{v}\\)","\\(\\frac{mv^2}{r}\\)","\\(\\frac{mv}{r^2}\\)",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A man was moving round a circular path continuously for 4 minutes and covered the following distances in the times stated : <br>\r\nDistance (in metres) 200, 400, 600, 300<br>\r\nTime(in minutes) : 1, 2, 3, 4 respectively. Which of the following statements is correct about the motion of the man?","options":["the man was moving without uniform velocity","the speed was changing constantly","the velocity was uniform","it was an instance of motion in which both speed and velocity are the same",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A car takes off from rest and covers a distance of 80m on a straight road in 10s. Calculate the magnitude of its acceleration","options":["1.25ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","1.60ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","4.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","8.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"An object is released from rest at a height of 25m. Calculate the time it takes to fall to the ground. [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["25.00s","10.00s","2.50s","2.24s",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"An object is acted upon by a system of parallel forces causing the object to be in static equilibrium. Which of the following statements is not correct?","options":["The resultant of the parallel force is zero","the algebraic sum of the moment of the forces is zero","all the parallel forces must be equal in magnitude and in direction","the sum of the forces in one direction must be equal to the sum of forces in the opposite direction",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A spiral spring of natural length 30.0cm and force constant of 20Nm<sup>-1<\/sup> is compressed to 20.0cm. Calculate the energy stored in the spring","options":["0.1J","1.0J","10.0J","100.0J",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following statements correctly defines quantitatively the work done by a force? the product of the force and the distance moved","options":["parallel to the line of action of the force from a reference point","perpendicular to the line of action of the force from a reference point","on a line through the reference point","by the object",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"a load of mass120kg is raised vertically through a height of 2m in 30s by a machine whose efficiency is 100%. Calculate the power generated by the machine. [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["60W","80W","100W","120W",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A block and tackle system has 6 pulleys. If the efficiency of the machine is 60%, determine its mechanical advantages","options":["12.0","10.0","3.6","1.8",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following actions will improve the efficiency of the pulley system?","options":["reducing the mass of the pulley","increasing the friction force between the string and the pulley","increasing the mass per unit length of the string of the pulley","increasing the mass of the pulley",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The ice and steam points of a certain thermometer are -20<sup>o<\/sup> and 100<sup>o<\/sup> respectively. Calculate the Celsius temperature temperature corresponding to 70<sup>o<\/sup> on the thermometer","options":["84.0<sup>o<\/sup>","75.0<sup>o<\/sup>","64.0<sup>o<\/sup>","58.0<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The silver coating on the inside of a vacuum flask reduces heat loss by","options":["conduction","radiation","condensation","convention",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Water of mass 120g at 50<sup>o<\/sup>C is added to 20og of water at 10<sup>o<\/sup>C and the mixture is well stirred. Calculate the temperature of the mixture. [Neglect heat losses to the surrounding]","options":["60<sup>o<\/sup>C","40<sup>o<\/sup>C","25<sup>o<\/sup>C","10<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Calculate the energy required to vapourise 50g of water initially at 80<sup>o<\/sup>C.[specific heat capacity of water = 2260Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>][specific latent heat of vaporisation of water = 2260Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["113,000J","117,200J","234,400J","420,000J",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"What type of motion does the skin of a 'talking' drum perform when it is struck with a drum stick?","options":["Random","Rational","Translational","vibratory",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A slinky spring fixed at one end is placed horizontally on a table. The free end is displaced parallel to the table and then released. The resultimg wavelength is","options":["transverse","longitudinal","stationary","electromagnetic",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A radio wave has a wavelength of 150m. If the velocity of radio waves is free spaces is 3 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the frequency of the radio wave","options":["4.50 x 10<sup>10<\/sup>Hz","5.0 x 10<sup>9<\/sup>Hz","4.5 x 10<sup>9<\/sup>Hz","2.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>Hz",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In the wave equation y = E<sub>o<\/sub>, sin(299t - \\(\\pi\\)), E<sub>o<\/sub> represents the","options":["amplitude","frequency","period","wavelength",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The size of the hole of a pin hole camera is increased. The resultant image formed becomes","options":["sharper","reduced in size","enlarged","blurred",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The refractive index of a medium relative to air is 1.8. Calculate to the nearest degree, the critical angle for the medium","options":["68<sup>o<\/sup>","56<sup>o<\/sup>","34<sup>o<\/sup>","18<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A converging lens of focal length 15cm forms a virtual image at a point 10cm from the lens. Calculate the distance of the object from the lens","options":["10.00cm","6.00cm","5.00cm","1.50cm",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In a compound microscope, the image formed by the objective lens is at a distance of 3.0cm from the eye lens. Calculate the focal length of the eye lens","options":["0.3cm","2.7cm","3.4cm","8.3cm",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A pulse of a sound is transmitted from a ship and the reflection from the sea bed is recorded after 0.2s. Calculate the depth of the sea. [Take speed of sound in sea water = 1560ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["312.0m","156.0m","78.0m","31.2m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"When two notes of nearly equal frequencies are sounded together, a periodic rise and fall in sound intensity can be heard. This phenomenon can be called","options":["beats","diffraction","overtones","resonance",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following instruments is not a wind instrument?","options":["clarinet","saxophone","trumpet","xylophone",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following actions will not cause an increase in the frequency of a vibrating string?","options":["increasing the tension of the string","decrease the mass per unit lengthof the string","decrease the length of the string","increasing the cross sectional area of the string",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following items can be used to compare the relative magnitudes of electric charges on two bodies?","options":["ebonite rod","gold leaf electroscope","proof plane","the electrophorus",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Three capacitors each of capacitance 18\\(\\mu F\\) are connected in series. Calculate the effective capacitance of the capacitors","options":["54.00\\(\\mu F\\)","18.00\\(\\mu F\\)","6.00\\(\\mu F\\)","0.17\\(\\mu F\\)",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Two spheres of masses 100kg and 90kg respectively have their centres separated by a distance of 1.0m. Calculate the magnitude of the force of attraction between them. [G = 6.70 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>kg<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["6.70 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>N","6.70 x 10<sup>-10<\/sup>N","6.03 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>N","6.03 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup>N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The magnitude of the gravitational attraction between the earth and a particle is 40N. If the mass of the particle is 4kg. Calculate the magnitude of the gravitational field intensity of the earth on the particle","options":["10.0N kg<sup>-1<\/sup>","12.6N kg<sup>-1<\/sup>","25.0N kg<sup>-1<\/sup>","160.0N kg<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Local actions is normally prevented in a simple electric cell by","options":["introducing an oxidizing agent in the acid","not drawing current continously for long period","amalgamating the surface of the zinc plate","using a porous pot to isolate the zinc plate from the acid",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The lead-acid accumulator consists of a","options":["lead as the positive electrode","lead ocide as the negative electrode","hydrochloric acid as the electrolyte","tetraoxosulphate(VI) acid as the electrolyte",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following actions will not lead to an increase in the induced e.m.f. in a coil of wire rotating between the poles of a magnet? Increasing the","options":["strength of the magnet","number of turns in the coil","speed of location in the coil","gap between the poles of the magnet",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A transformer has 400 turns and 200 turns in the primary and secondary windings respectively. If the current in the primary and secondary windings are 3A and 5A respectively. calculate the efficiency of the transformer?","options":["85.0%","83.3%","37.5%","30.0%",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A freely-suspended magnet swinging in a horizontal plane comes to rest with its axis pointing approximately","options":["north-south","south-west","north-east","south-east",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In a model of the hydrogen atom, the energy levels W<sub>n<\/sub> are given by the formula W<sub>n<\/sub> = -\\(\\frac{R}{n^2}\\), where n is an integer and R is a constant. Determine the energy released in the transition from n = 3 to n = 2.","options":["\\(\\frac{R}{5}\\)","-\\(\\frac{R}{4}\\)","\\(\\frac{5R}{36}\\)","\\(\\frac{-5R}{36}\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"If a radioactive atom emits a beta particle, Its mass number","options":["increases by one","remains the same","decreases by one","increases by two",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following is usually used to cause fission in an atomic reactor?","options":["Alpha particles","beta particles","electrons","Neutrons",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following materials is used to control the rate of neutron production in a nuclear reactor?","options":["boron rods","concrete shield","graphite rods","uranium rods",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A nuclide X is produced by bombarding a nitrogen(N) nucleus with an alpha(\\alpha\\) particle with the release of heavy hydrogen(D) nucleus as shown by the following nuclear equation, \\(\\alpha + ^{14}_{7}N \\to ^p_qX + ^2_1D\\). Determine the values of p and q in the equation","options":["12 and 6","14 and 7","16 and 8","19 and 8",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In an operating X-ray tube, a high p.d is applied between the cathode and the anode for the purpose of","options":["accelerating the electrons to a very high energy","concentrating electrons on the target","heating the anode","heating the cathode","producing a stream of electrons"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The ability of the eye to focus on objects at various distances is known as","options":["accommodation","astigmatism","eye ring","myopia","presbyopia"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which colour is deviated least when white light passes through a triangular prism?","options":["green","indigo","orange","violet","yellow"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"An electric heater takes 4A when operated on a 250V supply. What is the cost of the electricity consumed at 10k per kWh when the heater is used for 5 hours?","options":["10k","50k","N1.00","N5.00","N10.00"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which is a fundamental unit?","options":["ampere","joule","Newton","ohm","watt"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which device does NOT make use of the magnetic effects of an electric current?","options":["hot-wire ammeter","moving-coil ammeter","moving-coil loudspeaker","moving-iron ammeter","telephone earpiece"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In the normal use of a simple microscope, a person sees an","options":["erect, real and magnified image","erect, virtual and magnified image","inverted, virtual and magnified image","inverted, real and magnified image","inverted and real image the same size as the object"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"What is the escape velocity of a satellite launched from the earth\u2019s surface? (Take g as 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup> and the radius of the earth as 6.4 \u00d7 10<sup>6<\/sup>m)","options":["7.80 \u00d7 10-3ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.13 \u00d7 10-4ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","3.56 \u00d7 107ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.00 \u00d7 107ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.20 \u00d7 108ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A body of mass 4 kg is accelerated from rest by a steady force of 9N. What is its speed when it has travelled a distance of 8m?","options":["6 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","18 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","32 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","36 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","48 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which statement is NOT correct about Rutherford\u2019s model of the atom?","options":["The diameter of the nucleus is of the order of 10-15m","The mass of an atom is concentrated in the nucleus","The model is applicable to atoms with one electron in the outer shell","The nucleus of an atom is positively charged","The nucleus is surrounded by an electron cloud."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In which of the following are the substances arranged in descending order of their thermal conductivities?","options":["aluminium, copper, iron","aluminium, iron, copper","copper, aluminium, iron","copper, iron. aluminium","iron, copper, aluminium"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"What part of the camera corresponds to the iris of the eye?","options":["diaphragm","film","focusing ring","lens","shutter"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A block of ice of mass 10kg at 0\u00b0C absorbs heat energy from its surroundings and changes to water at the same temperature. The heat absorbed is referred to as","options":["heat capacity","latent heat","specific heat","specific heat capacity","specific latent heat."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"In which simple machine is the effort applied between the load and the fulcrum?","options":["claw hammer","nut crackers","pliers","sugar tongs","wheelbarrow"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A body of weight 20N displaces 12N of the liquid in which it is immersed. What is the upthrust of the liquid on the body?","options":["240N","32N","20N","12N","8N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"If the temperature of a resistance wire is gradually increased, its resistance will","options":["decrease gradually","first increase and then decrease","first increase and then remain the same","increase gradually","remain the same"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A man stands in front f a high wall and produces a sound. If he receives the echo of the sound four seconds later, what is his distance from the wall? [The speed of sound in air is 330ms<sup>-1<\/sup>]","options":["1320m","660m","400m","330m","165m"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A negatively charged rod is brought near the cap of an electroscope. The cap is earthed momentarily while the charge is near to it. The rod is then removed. Which statement is correct?","options":["The cap will be positively charged and the will be negatively charged","The cap will be negatively charged and the leaf will be positively changed","The cap and the leaf will be positively charged","The cap and the leaf will be negatively charged","none"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"If the refractive index of water is 1.33, what is the critical angle for a water-air boundary?","options":["36.0 \u00b0","40.2 \u00b0","41.8 \u00b0","48.8 \u00b0","62.7 \u00b0"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The use of electrical fuses in domestic wiring is","options":["to prevent and electrical shock","to supply electricity to all the electrical appliances","to allow electricity to flow easily through the mains to all the circuits","to cut off the mains supply it too high a current flows","to fuse all the circuit into one"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"An object is projected with a velocity of 50ms<sup>-1<\/sup> from ground level at an angle \u03b8 to the vertical. If the total time of flight of the projectile is 5s, what is the value of \u03b8? (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["0\u00b0","30\u00b0","45\u00b0","60\u00b0","90\u00b0"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"What is stored by a dry Leclanh\u00e9 cell?","options":["chemical energy","heat energy","mechanical energy","nuclear energy","solar energy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Lenz\u2019s law of electromagnetic induction states that","options":["e.m.f. is induced in a circuit whenever there is a change in the magnetic flux linked with the circuit","the induced e.m.f. in a circuit is proportional to the rate of change f the number of lines of force linking the circuit","the induced current in a conductor is in such a direction as to oppose the change producing it","a force is exerted in a current-carrying conductor in a magnetic field.","the induced e.m.f. is proportional to the current producing the magnetic flux."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which process will increase the rate of oscillation of a pendulum?","options":["decreasing the amplitude of oscillation of the pendulum","decreasing the length of the pendulum","decreasing the mass of the pendulum","increasing the length of the pendulum","increasing the mass of the pendulum."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"When a current of 1 .0A flows in an electrolyte for 3.0h, a mass of 1 .0g is deposited. What mass will be deposited in 10.0h if a current of 3.0A flows through the electrolyte?","options":["30.0g","24.0g","10.0g","6.0g","0.4g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"An object weighing 0.60N is hung on a spiral spring and caused it to extend by 6.0cm. The object is removed and a black of wood replacing it causes the spring to extend by 10.0cm. What is the weight of the block of wood?","options":["0.10N","0.36N","0.80N","1.00N","3.60N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A body is uniformly accelerated from rest. Which of the following quantities vary\/varies linearly with the square of the time? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. Displacement<br>\r\nII. Velocity<br>\r\nIII. Momentum","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and II only","II and Ill only"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A body of mass M<sub>1<\/sub> moving with a velocity U collides with a stationary body of mass M<sub>2<\/sub> and both move with a common velocity V. If linear momentum is conserved, which expression correctly represents V?","options":["M<sub>1<\/sub> + M<sub>2<\/sub> \u00f7 M<sub>1<\/sub>U","M<sub>2<\/sub>U \u00f7 M<sub>1<\/sub> \u2013 M<sub>2<\/sub>","M<sub>1<\/sub>U \u00f7 M<sub>1<\/sub> \u2013 M<sub>2<\/sub>","M<sub>1<\/sub>U \u00f7 M<sub>1<\/sub>+ M<sub>2<\/sub>","M<sub>2<\/sub>U \u00f7 M<sub>1<\/sub> + M<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"According to the Kinetic Theory, what does NOT occur when the temperature of a constant volume of gas is increased?","options":["a decrease in the mean speed kinetic energy of the molecules","an increase in the mean speed of the molecules","an increase in the momentum change at each collision.","an increase in the number of collisions per second","an increase in the pressure exerted by the gas."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The wavelength of a stationary wave is 36.0cm. What is the distance between a node and the next anti-node?","options":["6.0cm","9.0cm","18.0cm","360cm","72.0cm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"An a.c. generator can be converted into a d.c. generator by replacing","options":["the slip rings with split-ring commutators","the slip rings with armatures","the split-rings with slip rings","the split-rings with brushes","the brushes with slip-ring commutators."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"It is NOT possible to determine exactly and simultaneously the position and momentum of a particle. This statement is known as the","options":["Crompton effect","de Broglie\u2019s laws","Frank-Hertz experimental law","Heisenberg\u2019s uncertainly principle","wave-particle paradox"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A platinum-resistance thermometer has a resistance of 10 \u03c9 at 0\u00b0C and 18 \u03c9 at 100\u00b0C. Assuming that resistance changes uniformly with temperature, what is the resistance of the thermometer when the temperature is 45\u00b0C?","options":["27.8","17.8","13.6","6.4","3.6"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"The phenomenon of photoelectric effect is NOT used in","options":["automatic doors","bimetallic strip thermometers","light meters in cameras","setting off burglar alarms","sound production from film tracks."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following is a percussion instrument?","options":["bell","flute","guitar","piano","organ"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A transformer supplies 12V when connected to a 240V mains. If the transformer takes 0.120A from the mains when used to light a 12V, 24W lamp, what is its efficiency?","options":["57.20%","66.60%","83.30%","92.50%","100%"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following is\/are TRUE of nuclear fission? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. A heavy nucleus is split into two nuclei of comparable masses. <br>\r\nII. Two light nuclei are joined together to form a heavier nucleus. <br>\r\nIII. The total mass of the products is less than that of the reactants.","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and III only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"A converging lens of focal length 5cm forms a virtual image which is 20cm from the lens. How far from the lens is the object?","options":["2.0cm","4.0 cm","6.7cm","20.0cm","25.0cm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2002"},{"question":"Which of the following physical processes cannot be explained by the molecular theory of matter?","options":["evaporation","thermal conduction","radiation of heat","convectional current of fliuds",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A spring balance,which is suspended from the roof of a lift, carries a mass of 1kg  at its free end. If the lift accelerates upwards at 2.5ms<sup>-2<\/sup>, determine the reading on the spring balance. [g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["24.0N","12.5N","7.5N","4.0N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An object weight 10N immersed in a liquid displaces a quantity of the liquid. If the liquid displaced weighs 6N, determine the upthrust of the object","options":["20N","10N","6N","4N",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about pressure is not correct? pressure","options":["increases with an increase in surface area","decreases with an increase in surface area","increases with a decrease in surface area","increases with an increase in the applied force",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The apparent weight of a body fully immersed in water is 32N and its weight in air is 96N. Calculate the volume of the body. [Density of water = 1000kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>, g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>]","options":["8.9 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","6.4 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","3.2 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","3.0 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A block weighing 15N rests on a flat surface and a horizontal force of 3N is exerted on it. Determine the friction force on the block","options":["0.3N","0.5N","3.0N","5.0N",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following equations represents the distance x, travelled by a body moving on a straight road with a constant speed? [The other symbol have their usual meanings]","options":["x = Ut + \\(\\frac{1}{2}t^2\\)","x = Ut","x = \\(\\frac{V^2 - U^2}{2a}\\)","x = -\\(\\frac{1}{2} at^2\\)",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The amplitude of the motion of a body performing simple harmonic motion decreases with time because","options":["friction force dissipate the energy of motion","the frequency of oscillation varies with time","the period of oscillation varies with time","energy is supplied by some external agency",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The amplitude of a particle executing simple harmonic motion in 5cm while its angular frequency is 10 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>. calculate the magnitude of the maximum acceleration of the particle","options":["0.25ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","0.50ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","5.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The time rate of change of momentum is","options":["impulse","force","power","pressure",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about elastic collision is correct?","options":["momentum is lost due to the sound produced","loss of momentim is equal to loss in kinetic energy","both kinetic energy and momentum are conserved","kinetic energy is lost while momentum is conserved",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Electrical resistance is a property of an electrical energy to be converted into","options":["mechanical energy","heat energy","magnetic energy","chemical energy",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A simple machine with an efficiency of 75% lifts a load of 5000N when a force of 500N is applied to it. Calculate the velocity ratio of the machine","options":["10.0","13.3","17.5","25.0",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A screw jack with a Tommy bar of length 12cm is used to raise a car through a vertical height of 25cm by turning the Tommy bar through 50 revolutions. Calculate the approximate velocity ratio of the jack [\\(\\pi = 3.142\\)]","options":["21","38","48","151",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A resistance thermometer has a resistance of 20\\(\\Omega\\) at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 85\\(\\Omega\\) at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C. If its resistance is 52\\(\\Omega\\)in a medium, calculate the corresponding temperature","options":["49.2<sup>o<\/sup>C","60.6<sup>o<\/sup>C","80.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","84.7<sup>o<\/sup>C",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A given mass of an ideal gas has a pressure of 500Nm<sup>-2<\/sup> at -13<sup>o<\/sup>C. If its volume remains constant. Calculate its pressure at 247<sup>o<\/sup>C.","options":["25Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","50Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","500Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","1000Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The volume of an ideal gas at a pressure of 77cmHg and temperature 60<sup>o<\/sup>C is 24cm<sup>3<\/sup>. If the temperature and pressure are increased to 98<sup>o<\/sup>C<br>\r\n and 81cmhg respectively, calculate the new volume of the gas","options":["411.5cm<sup>3<\/sup>","267.1cm<sup>3<\/sup>","254.2cm<sup>3<\/sup>","112.7cm<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The amount of heat given out or absorbed when a substance changes its state at a constant temperature is known as","options":["latent heat","heat capacity","specific latent heat","specific heat capacity",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following physical qualities affects the saturated vapour pressure of a liquid ?","options":["temperature","volume","mass","density",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Humidity is used to describe the amount of","options":["air in water vapour","cloud available in the atmosphere","air in equal volume of cloud","water vapour in the amosphere",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Surface waves travelling in deep water at 15ms<sup>-1<\/sup> are incident at a shallow water boundary. If the angles of incidence and refraction are 45<sup>o<\/sup> and 30<sup>o<\/sup> respectively. Calculate the speed of the waves in shallow water","options":["8.1ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","10.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","10.6ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","22.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An incident ray is reflected normally by a plane mirror onto a screen where it forms a bright spot. The mirror and screen are parallel and 1m apart. If the mirror is rotated through 5<sup>o<\/sup>, calculate the displacement of the spot","options":["8.7cm","10.0cm","15.4cm","17.6cm",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Convex spherical mirrors are preferred to plane mirrors as driving mirrors because","options":["the image produce is upright and clearly visible","it provides a wider field of view","the image produce is errect and diminished","the image produced is not laterally inverted",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An object is placed 20cm from a lens. If an image is formed on a screen 260cm away from the lens, calculate the magnification of the image","options":["28","26","24","13",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A piece of cloth appears green in sunlight. When held in red light, it will appear","options":["green","blue","red","black",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Dispersion of white light by a glass prism occurs because","options":["white light consist of a mixture of seven different colour","the refractive index of glass is different from each constituent colour of white light","the speed of each colour of light in the glass is proportional to the refractive index of glass for each colour","the speed of each colour of light in the glass is proportional to the angle of refraction in he prism",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about sound is correct?","options":["when sound travels from air to a denser medium, it is refracted away from the normal at the point of incidence","sound travels faster in air than in water","the wavelength of sound changes when it travels from to water","the frequency of it travels from air to water",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"If the frequency of the tuning fork at resonance is 256Hz, calculate the frequency of vibration of the wire when the tension in he wire is increased to 196N","options":["130.6Hz","182.9Hz","358.4Hz","501.8Hz",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The magnitude of the gravitational force between two particles 0.10m apart is 10N. If the distance between them is increased to 0.20m, calculate the magnitude of the new force","options":["40.0N","20.0N","5.0N","2.5N",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"As the plates of a charged variable capacitor are moved closer together, the potential difference between them","options":["increased","decrease","remains the same","is doubled",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Three identical lamps each power 100W are connected in parallel across a potential difference of 250V. Calculate the current in the circuit","options":["7.5A","2.5A","1.2A","0.8A",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An electric bulb is rated 60W, 220V. Calculate the resistance of its filament when it is operating normally","options":["296.7\\(\\Omega\\)","400.0\\(\\Omega\\)","512.2\\(\\Omega\\)","806.7\\(\\Omega\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The Earth's magnetic equator passes through Jos in Nigeria. At Jos. the","options":["angle of variation is zero","magnetic declination is 90<sup>o<\/sup>","angle of dip is zero","horizontal component of the Earth's magnetic field is zero",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about magnetic lines of force is not correct?","options":["a magnnetic line of force is an imaginary line which the north pole of a magnet would describe if it is free to moves","magnetic lines of force do not cross one another","magnetic lines of force are closely packed together at neutral point","the presence of magnetic lines of force in a region indicates the presence of a magnetic field",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The material used for constructing the core of an electromagnet is","options":["iron","carbon","copper","steel",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Production of x-ray tube begins with","options":["photo electric emission","collision of electrons","thermionic emission","field emission of electrons",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A nitrogen nucleus bombarded with an alpha particle produces an oxygen nucleus and a proton. The nuclear reaction for this process is \\(^4_2H + ^{14}_2N \\to ^{17}_{8}O + ^1_1H + Q\\). Which of the following statements about the reaction is not correct?","options":["the  bombardment results into a nucleus with greater proton number","it is an induced nuclear reaction","it is a natural radioactive decay","the sum of the final nucleon numbers",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Electrons passing through crystals are diffracted because they","options":["are repelled by the atoms in the crystal","are attracted by the atoms in the crystals","possess wave properties","are particles",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The invisible part of the spectrum of white light consists of","options":["Infra-red and ultra-violet only","Infra-red, ultra-violet and blue only","red, orange and green only","red and violet only","yellow and indigo only"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"50cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air at a pressure of 5Nm<sup>-2<\/sup> is enclosed in a metal tube by a piston. If the piston is pushed in a distance of 10cm, what will the pressure of the air become, if the cross-sectional area of the tube is 2cm<sup>-2<\/sup>? (Assume that the temperature remains constant throughout)","options":["12.5 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","8.7 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","8.3 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","3.8Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","3.0Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which scientist discovered natural radioactivity?","options":["Enrico Fermi","Henri Becquerel","Marie Curie","Micheal Faraday","Niels Bohr"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Totally reflecting prisms are preferred to mirrors in periscopes because<br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. mirror givegive multiple images <br>\r\nII. silvering on mirrors is easy damaged <br>\r\nIII. mirrors reflect less light than totally reflecting prisms","options":["I only","I and II only","I and III only","II and III only","I,II and III"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"What is the energy stored in a 10\u03bc F capacitor if the potential difference between the plates is 40 V?","options":["2.0 \u00d7 10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","8.0 \u00d710<sup>-4<\/sup>J","4.0 \u00d7 10<sup>-3<\/sup>J","8.0 \u00d7 10<sup>-3<\/sup>J","1.6 \u00d7 10<sup>-2<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Notes of the same frequency sounded on a piano and on a flute may differ in<br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. pitch <br>\r\nII. quality <br>\r\nIII. Loudness","options":["I only","II only","I and III only","II and III only","I, II and III"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"What is X in the equation given below? 42He + 94Be \u2192 126C + X","options":["electron","hydrogen","lithium","neutron","proton"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A waterfall is 6.30m high. What is the change in temperature of a quantity of water that falls from the top to the bottom of the waterfall? (Neglect heat losses to the surroundings, take g as 10 ms<sup>-2<\/sup> and specific heat capacity of weather as 4200,J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","options":["0.15\u00b0C","1.50\u00b0C","15.00\u00b0C","21.00 \u00b0C","50.00\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"N.N.P.C. gas cylinder containing 15kg of cooking gas was left open, and the gas emptied in 3.8 minutes, at an average speed of 20 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. What force was exerted on the gas in the cylinder?","options":["132N","13.2N","1.32N","0.132N","0.013N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An object placed 15cm from a converging lens forms a real image whose magnification is 2.0. What is the focal length of the lens?","options":["5.00cm","10.00cm","15.00 cm","18.00 cm","20.00cm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which statement about the concept of temperature is NOT true?","options":["Temperature decides the direction of heat flow between two bodies","Temperature is a measure of coldness of a body","Temperature is a vector quantity","Temperature is a measure of hotness of a body.","Temperature scales include Fahrenheit, Celsius and Kelvin"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which is a stringed Instrument?","options":["drum","flute","piano","saxophone","trumpet"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The statement that the mechanical advantage of a machine is 3 means that the","options":["efficiency is 33\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)%","effort is three times as large as the load","mechanical advantage is 3 times as large as the velocity ratio","ratio of the effort to the load is 1: 3","Velocity ratio is 3"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The wavelength of a stationary wave is 24.0cm. What is the distance between a node and the next antinodes?","options":["6.0cm","12.0cm","18.0cm","24.0cm","48.0cm"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"What gives rise to the line spectra observed in atoms?","options":["change of an electron from a higher to a lower energy level in the atom","disturbed protons in the nucleus","excitation of an electron in the atom","kinetic energy of a moving atom","potential energy of an electron inside an atom"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A lead-acid accumulator is used in preference to a dry battery in a car because","options":["a dry battery cannot supply the necessary high voltage","a dry battery would not operate on a cold frosty morning","the accumulator can give a bigger current and can be recharged","the accumulator can supply a.c","the chemicals used in a dry battery constitute a fire hazard."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A metal has a work function of 3.0 eV. What is the threshold frequency of the metal when electrons are just liberated from the metal.(1 <sub>e<\/sub>V = 1.6 \u00d7 10<sup>-19<\/sup>J; h = 6.6 \u00d7 10<sup>-34<\/sup>Js)","options":["4.8 \u00d7 10<sup>-19<\/sup>Hz","9.3 \u00d7 10<sup>-7<\/sup>Hz","4.8 \u00d7 10<sup>14<\/sup>Hz","7.3 \u00d7 10<sup>14<\/sup>Hz","9.3 \u00d7 10<sup>14<\/sup>Hz"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A body whose initial velocity is u is uniformly accelerated to a final velocity v in t seconds. If the distance travelled is s, and the acceleration is a, which equation is INCORRECT for the motion of the body?","options":["s = ut+\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)at<sup>2<\/sup>","v<sup>2<\/sup> = u<sup>2<\/sup> + 2as","v =u + at","v = u + 2as","s = \\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)(u+v)t"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A cell can supply currents of 0.60 A and 0.30 A through a 2.0 \u03c9 and a 5.0 \u03c9 resistor respectively. What is the internal resistance of the cell?","options":["0.2 \u03c9","0.4 \u03c9","1.0 \u03c9","3.0 \u03c9","9.0 \u03c9"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which statement is a correct consequence of the uncertainly principle?","options":["A particle\u2019s kinetic energy cannot be measured accurately at any time","Both momemtum and energy of a particle can be known with absolute certainly","It is possible to measure exactly both the position and momentum of a particle at the same time","The complete knowledge of the position of a particle implies the complete ignorance of its energy","The uncertainty in our knowledge of energy and the duration taken to measure it, are each less than Planck\u2019s constant."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which statements(s) is\/are NOT true? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. A saturated vapour is one that is in equilibrium with its liquid in a closed space. II. A vapour contains molecules with varying kinetic energy and their distances apart are smaller than those of the molecules of a liquid <br>\r\n III. Relative Humidity = \\(\\frac{\\text{Saturated vapour pressure at dew point}} {\\text{Saturated vapour pressure at air temperature}}\\) x 100% <br>\r\n<br>\r\nIV. The saturated vapour pressure of water increases with temperature","options":["I only","II only","II and III only","III and IV only","II, III and IV only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A 220 V, 60 Hz alternating current supply is connected to an inductor of 3.5H. What is the current passing through the inductor?","options":["0.0167 A","0.1670 A","1.6700 A","16.7000 A","167.0000 A"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The speed of sound travelling in various media increases in the order:","options":["air, iron bar, water","air, water, iron bar","iron, bar water, air","water, air, iron bar","water, iron bar, air"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"The lower and upper fixed points of a mercury-in-glass thermometer are marked X and 180 mm respectively. On a particular day the mercury meniscus in the thermometer rises to 60mm. If the corresponding reading on a Celsius scale is 20 \u00b0 C, what is the value X?","options":["6.0mm","18.0mm","30.0mm","60.0mm","120.0mm"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"When water is heated between 0\u00b0C and 4\u00b0C, it's density","options":["increases for a while and then decreases","decreases for a while and then increases","increases","decreases","remains constant."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"If N.E.P.A. charges 65 kobo per kilowatt-hour for electricity supplied to consumers, what bill would an electric iron rated at 750 watts attract when used for 24 hours?","options":["N9.70","N11.70","N12.40","N15.90","N17.60"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An object is placed 15cm in front of a concave mirror of focal length 20cm. The image formed is","options":["real, inverted and diminished","real, inverted and magnified","virtual, erect and diminished","virtual, erect and magnified","virtual, inverted and magnified"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"When an astronomical telescope is in normal adjustment, the focal length of the objective lens is 50cm and that of the eye piece is 5.0cm. What is the distance between the lenses?","options":["10.0cm","30.0cm","45.0cm","55.0cm","250.0cm"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An object 3.00m high is placed at a distance of 7.50m from a pin-hole camera. If the image height is 6.00 cm, what is the distance of the film from the pin-hole?","options":["3.75cm","7.50cm","15.00cm","30.00cm","150.00 cm"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A transformer is connected to a 250 V a.c. supply. The primary coil has 5000 turns and the secondary voltage is found to be 10 V. What is the number of turns in the secondary coil?","options":["100","150","200","250","300"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which statement is TRUE of a block of stone of mass m, with zero momentum?","options":["The acceleration of the stone is non-uniform","The stone is stationary","The stone moves at a constant velocity","The stone moves with maximum velocity","The stone moves with minimum velocity."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An electron of charge a = 1.6 \u00d7 10<sup>-19<\/sup>C is situated in a uniform electric field of intensity 2.4 \u00d7 105 V m<sup>-1<\/sup>. What is the force on the electron?","options":["1.60 \u00d7 10<sup>-19<\/sup>N","3.84 \u00d7 10<sup>19<\/sup>N","1.92 \u00d7 10<sup>-14<\/sup>N","3.84 \u00d7 10<sup>-14<\/sup>N","7.68 \u00d7 10<sup>-14<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which is NOT one of the laws of solid friction?","options":["The frictional force between two surfaces opposes their relative motion","The ratio of frictional force to the normal reaction varies for two given surfaces","The ratio of frictional force to the normal reaction is constant for two given surfaces","The limiting frictional force is independent of the area of surface in contact.","Dynamic frictional force is independent of the relative velocity of the surfaces in contact."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"What part of a camera functions in a similar way to the retina of the eye?","options":["diaphragm","film","focusing ring","lens","shutter"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An astronaut is walking on the moon where the magnitude of the acceleration due to gravity \"g\u2019 is one-sixth that on earth. Compared with their magnitudes on the earth, his mass and weight on the moon are","options":["both less","less and the same respectively","the same and less respectively","the same as on earth","both greater."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"Which statement is NOT correct about molecules?","options":["The number of molecules in a unit volume of a solid is greater than that in a unit volume of a liquid or gas.","Molecules are made up of atoms","The force of attraction between two molecules of a solid is greater than that between two molecules of a liquid or gas","Molecules of gases are in regular motion","Molecules of a solid vibrate about their mean positions."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"What is the angular velocity of an object in a horizontal circular path of radius 1.5m with a constant speed of 12ms<sup>-1<\/sup>?","options":["1.6 rads<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.0 rads<sup>-1<\/sup>","8.0 rads<sup>-1<\/sup>","16.0rads<sup>-1<\/sup>","32.0 rads<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"A wave is represented by the equation y = 0.5 sin 0.4 \u03a9(X - 60t), where the distance (X) is measured in centimetres and time (t) in seconds. What is the wave length of the wave?","options":["0.2cm","0.4cm","0.8cm","5.0cm","10.0cm"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"In 24 days a radioactive isotope decreases in mass from 128g to 2g. What is the half-life of the radioactive material?","options":["2.54 days","4.00 days","4.80 days","6.00 days","8.00 days"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2001"},{"question":"An iron rod is moved from the earth to the moon. Which of the following properties of the rod would remain unchanged?  i. mass  ii. weight  iii. relative density","options":["i only","ii only","iii only","i and iii only",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A uniform cylindrical hydrometer of mass 20g and cross sectional area 0.54cm<sup>2<\/sup> floats upright in a liquid. If 25cm of its length is submerged, calculate the relative density of the liquid. (Density of water = 1 gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>)","options":["1.54","1.48","1.25","0.80",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The apparent weight of a body wholly immersed in water is 32N and its weight in air is 96N. Calculate the volume of the body. (Density of water = 1000kgm<sup>-3<\/sup>, g = 10ms<sup>-3<\/sup>)","options":["8.9 x 10m<sup>-3<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","6.4 x 10m<sup>-3<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","3.2 x 10m<sup>-3<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","3.0 x 10m<sup>-3<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A wooden block of mass 1.6kg rest on a rough horizontal surface, if the limiting friction force between the block and the surface is 8N. Calculate the coefficient of friction. (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["0.6","0.5","0.3","0.2",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A ball bearing is gently released from rest and allowed to fall through a viscous fluid. Which of the following statements about the motion is correct?","options":["its acceleration decreases before terminal velocity is attained","when terminal velocity is attained the acceleration of the fluid becomes zero","its velocity increases before terminal velocity is attained","there is no resultant force on the ball before it attains terminal velocity",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The driver of a car moving with uniform speed of 40ms<sup>-1<\/sup> observes a truck approaching from the opposite direction with a speed of 20ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Calculate the speed of the car relative to that of the truck","options":[".5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","20.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","60.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A bus travelling at 15ms<sup>-1<\/sup> accelerates uniformly at 4ms<sup>-2<\/sup>, what is the distance covered in 10s?","options":["150m","170m","350m","600m",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A uniform metre rule of mass 90g is provided at the 40cm mark. If the rule is in equilibrium with an unknown mass m placed at the 10cm mark and a 72g mass at the 70cm mark, determine m","options":["72g","102g","298g","504g",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The resultant of two forces acting on an object is maximum when the angle between them is","options":["180<sup>o<\/sup>","90<sup>o<\/sup>","45<sup>o<\/sup>","0<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The bob of a simple pendulum takes 0.25s to swing from its equilibrium position to one extreme end. Calculate its period","options":["0.25s","0.50s","0.75s","1.00s",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The period of oscillation pf a particle executing simple harmonic motion is 4\\(\\pi\\) seconds. If the amplitude of oscillation is 3.0m. Calculate its period","options":["1.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","3.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"An inelastic collision takes place between ball of known masses, just before the collision one of the ball is moving with a known velocity while the other is stationary. Which of the following physical quantities can be determined from the information given?","options":["speed of each of the ball after collision","kinetic energy of each ball after collision","total momentum of the ball after collision","total momentum of the two ball after collision","mutual forces excerted by the balls"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A machine of efficiency 8% is used to raise a body of mass 75kg through a vertical height of 3m in 30s. Calculate the power input. (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["9.4W","60.0W","75.0W","93.8W",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Two bodies P and Q, are in thermal equilibrium, which of the following statements about the bodies is correct?","options":["the temperature of Q is higher than that of P","P and Q have the same heat capacty","P and Q have the same mass","P and Q are at the same temperature",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The cubic expansivity of mercury is 1.8 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup> and the linear expansivity of glass 8.0 x 10<sup>-6<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the apparent expansivity of mercury in a glass container","options":["1.00 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.56 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.72 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.04 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The volume and pressure of a given mass of gas at 27<sup>o<\/sup>C are 76cm<sup>3<\/sup> and 80cm of mercury respectively. Calculate the volume at s.t.p","options":["36.2cm<sup>3<\/sup>","72.8cm<sup>3<\/sup>","100.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>","808.9cm<sup>3<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A piece of metal of mass 50g is cooled from 80<sup>o<\/sup>C to 20<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate the amount of heat lost. (specific heat capacity of the material of metal = 450Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["4.50 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>J","2.25 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>J","1.80 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>J","1.35 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>J",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The mass of water vapour in a given volume of air is 0.05g at 20<sup>o<\/sup>C, while the mass of water vapour required to saturate it at the same temperature is 0.15g. Calculate the relative humidity of the air","options":["3.33%","5.55%","33.33%","55.55%",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The temperature at which the saturated vapour pressure of a liquid is equal to the external atmospheric pressure is known as its","options":["dew point","boiling point","lower fixed point","tripple point",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A periodic pulse travels a distance of 20.0m in 1.00s. If its frequency is 2.0 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>Hz. Calculate the wavelength.","options":["1.0 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>m","1.0 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>m","2.0 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>m","1.0 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A wave has an amplitude equal to 4.0m, angular speed \\(\\frac{1}{3} \\pi\\) rads<sup>-1<\/sup> and phase angle \\(\\frac{2}{3} \\pi\\) rad. The displacement y of the wave particle is given as","options":["y = 4 sin \\(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)(t + 2)","y = 4 sin \\(\\frac{\\pi}{3}\\)(t + \\(\\frac{2}{\\pi}\\)","y = 4 sin \\(\\frac{\\pi}{3} (2t + 1)\\)","y = 4 sin \\(\\frac{\\pi}{3} (t + 2)",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A concave mirror can be used to produce a parallel beam of light if a lighted bulb is placed","options":["between its focus and the pole","at its focus","at its centre of curveture","between its focus and centre of curvature",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A simple microscope forms an image 10cm from an eye close to the lens. If the object is 6cm from the eye, calculate the focal length of the lens","options":["3.75cm","4.00cm","15.00cm","16.00cm",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"When white light passes through a triangular glass prism, there is dispersion because of","options":["diffraction of light","polarisation of light","the difference in speed of the components of light","the interference of light waves in glass",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"In which of the following media does sound travel faster?","options":["water","brass","air","wood",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A turning fork of frequency 600Hz is sounded over a closed resonance tube. If the first and second resonant positions are 0.140m and 0.413m respectively, calculate the speed of sound in air","options":["508.4ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","480.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","339.6ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","169.8ms<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"loudness increases as a vibrating tuning fork is brought nearer the end of a pipe containing air column due to","options":["resonance","echo","reverberation","diffraction",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"the factor which enables the ear to distinguish between a note played on different instruments is the","options":["pitch","speed","harmonics","loudness",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"An object is situated within the Earth's gravitational field. Which of the following factor does not affect the acceleration of free fall g?","options":["the distance of the object from the centre of the earth","the latitude of the earth on which the object is situated","rotation of the earth","the mass of the object",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The capacitance of a parallel-plate capacitor is increased by making the area of the plates","options":["small and their seperation large","large and their seperation small","and their seperation small","and their seperation equal",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"An immersion heater is rated 120W. How long does it take the heater to raise the temperature of 1.2kg of water by 15<sup>o<\/sup>C. (Assuming heat lost to the surrounding is negligible. Specific heat capacity of water = 4200 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>C)","options":["65.0 minutes","60.0 minutes","52.5 minutes","10.5 minutes",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The region around a magnet in which the magnetic influence is experienced is called","options":["magnetic flux","magnetic field","magnetic meridian","magnetic declination",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A device used to prevent wearing away of the make and-brake contacts of an induction coil is called a\\an","options":["fuse","electroscope","resistor","capacitor",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"If a bar magnet is accidentally broken into three pieces as shown in the diagram above, the polarities of P and Q respectively are","options":["S and S","N and S","N and N","S and N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"An inductor of inductance 10H carries a current of 0.2A. Calculate the energy stored in the inductor","options":["0.1J","0.2J","1.0J","2.0J",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"calculate the inductance of an inductor whose reactance is one ohm at 50 Hz.","options":["2.00 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>H","6.36 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>H","3.18 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>H","4.55 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>H",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Borh's theory provides evidence for the","options":["structure of the atom","positive charge of an electron","existence of energy level in the atom","positive charge on a proton",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A nuclide \\(^{202}_{84} Y\\) emits in succession an \\(\\alpha-particle\\) and a \\(\\beta-particle\\). The atomic number of the resulting nuclide is","options":["198","83","82","80",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The half life of a radioactive substance is 14 days. If 48g of this substance is stored, after how many days will 1.5g of the original substance remain?","options":["84 days","70 days","56 days","40 days",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A material of mass 1.0 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>kg undergoes a fission process which decreases its mass by 0.02 percent. Calculate the amount of energy released in the process. (c = 3.0 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["1.8 x 10<sup>20<\/sup>J","1.8 x 10<sup>13<\/sup>J","1.8 x 10<sup>11<\/sup>J","1.8 x 10<sup>10<\/sup>J",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Absorption line spectra exhibited by atoms is a result of","options":["change in the kinetic energy of a movimg atom","instability of the nucleons","excitation of an electron in the atom","transition of an electron from a higher to a lower energy level",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"In which of the following transitions is the largest quantum of energy liberated by an hydrogen atom when the electron changes energy levels? [n is the quantum number]","options":["n = 2 to n = 1","n = 1 to n = 2","n = 2 to n = 3","n = 3 to n = 2",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A proton of wavelength \\(\\lambda_o\\) is emitted when an electron in an atom makes a transition from a level of energy 2E<sub><\/sub>. If the electron transits from \\(\\frac{4}{3}E_k\\) to E<sub><\/sub> level, determine the wavelength of the photon that would be emitted","options":["3\\(\\lambda_o\\)","2\\(\\lambda_o\\)","\\(\\frac{3}{4}\\)\\(\\lambda_o\\)","\\(\\frac{1}{3}\\)\\(\\lambda_o\\)",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The nucleon number and the proton number of a neutral atom of an element are 23 and 11 respectively. How many neutrons are present in the atom?","options":["11","12","23","34",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"In a nuclear reactor, electricity can be generated through the following processes. Arrange the processes in the correct order.  i. The steam is used to drive turbines.  ii. The heat energy released is removed by passing water through the reactor.  iii. The turbines in turn generate electricity.  iv. The water then passes through some form of heat exchanger to produce steam","options":["ii, iv, i and iii","i, ii, iii and iv","iii, i, iv and ii","iv, i, iii and ii",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The duality of matter implies that matter","options":["exists as a particle of dual composition","has momentum and enrgy","has both wave and particle properties","is made up of dual materials",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A particle of charge q and mass m moving with a velocity v enters a uniform magnetic field B in the direction of the field. The force on the particle is","options":["Bqv","Bq\\(\\frac{v}{m}\\)","Bqvm","mv\\(\\frac{B}{q}\\)","\\(\\frac{mv}{Bq}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"When a metal is heated to a high temperature, electrons are emitted from its surface. The process is known as","options":["photoelectric effect","thermionic emission","field emission","secondary emission","radioactive emission"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A piece of stone weights 180 N in air and 150 N in a beaker containing 160 N of methylated spirit. What is the up thrust exerted on the stone?","options":["50N","40N","30N","20N","10N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The half-life of a radioactive substance is 2 seconds. Calculate the decay constant.","options":["2.890 s<sup>-1<\/sup>","1 .445 s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.576 s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.347s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.152 s<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Which of the following is used in a nuclear reactor to slow down fast moving neutrons?","options":["graphite rods","carbon dioxide gas","liquid sodium metal","concrete shield","boron rods"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"What is the coefficient of static friction between a load of mass 2kg and a horizontal surface, if the limiting frictional force is 10N? (g = 10 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["0.2","0.5","2","5","8"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The specific heat of a substance in the solid state is C<sub>1<\/sub>; its specific beat in the liquid state is C<sub>2<\/sub> and its latent heat of fusion is L. If a mass M of the substance is changed from the solid state at temperature T, to the liquid state, also at temperature T, the amount of heat required will be","options":["M(C<sub>1<\/sub> \u00f7 C<sub>2<\/sub>) x T","ML","L","M(C<sub>1<\/sub> + C<sub>2<\/sub>) \u00d7 T \u00f7 ML","ML(C<sub>1<\/sub> + C<sub>2<\/sub> \u00f7 2) \u00d7 T"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"An element of nuclear number A and proton number Z emits an alpha particle from its nucleus. The nucleon number and the proton number of the new element formed are respectively","options":["(A \u2013 2) and (Z \u2013 2)","(A + 4) and (Z + 2)","(A\u2013 4) and (Z+2)","(A+ 4) and (Z \u2013 2)","(A \u2013 4) and (Z \u2013 2)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The force exerted on a charged body in an electric field depends on <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. the charge on the body <br>\r\nII. the electric field intensity <br>\r\nIII. the square of the mass of the body","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","I and III only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"400g of cold water is added to 200g of water at 70\u00b0C. If they are properly mixed and the temperature of the mixture is 300\u00b0C. calculate the initial temperature of the cold water. (Neglect the heat absorbed by the container)","options":["10\u00b0C","15\u00b0C","20\u00b0C","30\u00b0C","40\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The heat from a fire in a closed room reaches someone far away in the room, mainly by","options":["reflection","diffusion","conduction","radiation","convection"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A solid weights 5.0 N in air, 4.2 N in water and 4.4 N in liquid Y. Calculate the relative density of liquid Y.","options":["0.75","0.88","0.95","1.13","1.33"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Two forces forming a couple are separated by a distance of 25cm. If one of the forces equals 40N, what is the moment of the couple?","options":["1000 Nm","500 Nm","10 Nm","5 Nm","1.6 Nm"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A radioactive substance has a half-life of 3 minutes. After 9 minutes, the count rate was observed to be 200. What was the count rate at zero time?","options":["200","1200","1600","2400","4800"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT part of an a.c generator?","options":["Commutator","Armature","Field magnet","Carbon brushes","Slip rings"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"In a simple pendulum experiment, a boy observed that the times for 30 oscillations are 70.0s, 72.0s and 67.0s respectively. Calculate the mean period of oscillation of the pendulum.","options":["0.14s","0.43s","2.32s","2.40s","6.97s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The clinical thermometer differs from other mercury-in-glass thermometers because it has <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. a constriction <br>\r\nII. a wide range<br>\r\nIII. a short range<br>\r\nIV. a narrow bore. <br>\r\n<br>\r\nWhich of the above are correct?","options":["I and II only","I and III only","III and IV only","I,II and III only","I, III and IV only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"If a positively charged glass-rod is used to charge an electroscope X by contact and an electroscope Y by induction, then","options":["X and Y will be negatively charge","X and Y will be positively charged","X will be negatively charged and Y positively charged","X will be positively charged and Y negatively charged","X will be positively charged and Y will remain uncharged"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A wave travels a distance of 20 cm in 3s. The distance between successive crests of the wave is 4cm. What is the frequency of the wave?","options":["0.60Hz","1.67Hz","7.50Hz","15.00Hz","26.67Hz"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The unit of inductance is","options":["Weber","Telsa","Hertz","Henry","Farad"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A man at the back of a crowd watches a parade by holding a plane mirror just above his head. The parade passes 6 metres behinde his head and the mirror is 0.25m in front of the man. How far does the image in the mirror appear to be from the man?","options":["6.50m","6.25m","6.00m","5.75m","5.50m"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"To keep a lorry moving at a constant speed v, requires power p, from the engine. The force provided by the engine is","options":["\\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)v","pv","\\(\\frac{p}{v}\\)","pv<sup>2<\/sup>","\\(\\frac{p}{v^2}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"An electric iron rated 250 V has a coil of resistance 125\u03a9. What is the cost of using it for I hour at 10k per kWh?","options":["1.25k","2.50k","5.00k","10.00k","20.00k"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Two 2.0\u03a9 resistors can be combined circuit to give an overall resistance of","options":["0.5\u03a9 only","1.0 \u03a9 only","either 0,5\u03a9 or 1.0 \u03a9","either 1.0\u03a9 or 4.0 \u03a9","either 0.5\u03a9, 1.0\u03a9 or 4.0\u03a9"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"An astronomical telescope which is being used to view a very distant object is said to be in normal adjustment if","options":["the final image is at the near-point","the image formed by the objective is before the focus of the eye piece","the angular magnification is the ratio of the focal length of the eye-piece lens to that of the objective","the foci dl the objective and the eye-piece coincide between the lenses","the distance between the objective lens and the eye-piece is equal to the difference between their focal lengths."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A man standing 510m away from a wall sounds a whistle. The echo from the wall reaches him 3s later. Calculate the velocity of sound in air.","options":["170 ms-1","340 ms-1","680 ms-1","765 ms-1","1530 ms-1"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The image is a plane mirror is","options":["inverted, real with a magnificant of \\(\\frac{1}{2}\\)","inverted, virtual with a magnification of 1","inverted, real with a magnification of 2","upright, virtual with a magnificent of 1","upright, real with a magnification of 2"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Which of the following is\/are TRUE of nuclear fission? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. A heavy nucleus is split into two nuclei of comparable masses <br>\r\nII. Two light nuclei are joined together to form a heavier nucleus <br>\r\nIII. The total mass of the products is less than that of the reactants","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and III only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"Which of the following is\/areNOT affected by a magnetic field? <br>\r\n<br>\r\nI. Alpha particle<br>\r\nII. Cathode rays<br>\r\nIII. Neutrons","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and II only","I,II & III"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The smallest unit on the sleeve of a micrometer screw gauge is 0.5mm. There are fifty divisions on the thimble of the screw gauge. <br>\r\nWhat is the smallest length that can be measured with this instrument?","options":["0.05cm","0.01cm","0.005cm","0.001cm","0.0001cm"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A boy moving with a velocity of 3 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>  is brought to rest by a constant force after travelling 15m. Calculate the retardation.","options":["0.15ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","0.30ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","0.60ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","3.33ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","6.66ms<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"I. A scalar quantity has only magnitude<br>\r\nII. A scalar quantity has both magnitude and direction<br>\r\nIII. A vector quantity has both magnitude and direction<br>\r\nIV. A vector quantity has only magnitude.<br>\r\n<br>\r\nWhich of the above statement is\/are correct?","options":["I only","l and II only","l and III only","II and III only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"An electric bell operated within an evacuated bell jar enables us to infer correctly that","options":["light waves require a medium for transmission","sound waves do not require a medium for transmission","light waves do not require a medium for transmission but sound waves do","light waves travel much faster than sound waves","light waves and sound waves travel at the same speed"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"A boy ran a distance of 200m in 24s. His average speed was 8.3ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Which of the following is correct about the units in which the statements above are expressed?","options":["All the units are fundamental.","All the units are derived","All the units except one are S.I units","Two of the units are fundamental and one derived.","None of the units is S.I units."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2000"},{"question":"The force between molecules of the same substance is termed","options":["elastic force","repulsive force","cohesive force","adhesive force",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A net force of magnitude 0.6N acts on a body of mass 40g, initially at rest. Calculate the magnitude of tire resulting acceleration.","options":["90ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","60ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","30ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","15ms<sup>-2<\/sup>.",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Palm oil from a bottle flows out more easily after it as been heated because the","options":["molecules are given potential energy during the heating","friction between oil layers is reduced","oil molecules force each other out","adhesion between the oil molecules and those of the bottle is increased",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A body weighing 10N moves with a speed of 5ms<sup>-1<\/sup> in a horizontal circular path of radius 5m. Calculate the . magnitude of the centripetal force acting on the body. (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["10N","50N","75N","100N",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A motorcyclist, passing a road junction, moves due west for 8 s at a uniform speed of 5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. He then moves due north for another 6 s with the same speed. At the end of the 6s his displacement from the road junction is 50m in the direction of","options":["N53<sup>o<\/sup>E","N37<sup>o<\/sup>E","N53<sup>o<\/sup>W","N37<sup>o<\/sup>W",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The time rate of change of displacement is known  as","options":["speed","velocity","impulse","acceleration",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A stone of mass 0.7kg is projected vertically , upwards with a speed of 5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Calculate the maximum height reached. (Take g as 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup> and neglect air resistance)","options":["1.00m","1.25m","1.50m","3.75m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"If the force of attraction between the sun and the 1 planets is removed; the planets will","options":["fall towards the sun","scatter and stop moving","continue to move at tangent to their original orbits","continue to move perpendicular to their original orbits. '",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A pendulum bob executing simple harmonic motion has 2cm and 12Hz as amplitude and frequency respectively. Calculate the period of the motion.","options":["2.00s","0.83s","0.08s","0.60s",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A trolley of mass 4kg moving on a smooth horizontal platform with a speed of 1.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup> collides perfectly with a stationary trolley of the same mass on the same platform. Calculate the total momentum of the two trolleys immediately after the collision.","options":["0.5Ns","1.0Ns","4.0Ns","8.0Ns",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The ice point of an ungraduated mercury-in-glass thermometer is X, while its steam point is 90<sup>o<\/sup>. This thermometer reads 60<sup>o<\/sup> when the true temperature is 40<sup>o<\/sup>C Calculate the value of X.","options":["60<sup>o<\/sup>","48<sup>o<\/sup>","40<sup>o<\/sup>","30<sup>o<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Iron at 30<sup>o<\/sup>C feels colder to the hand than wood at 28<sup>o<\/sup>C because","options":["their linear expansivities are not equal.","the temperature of the iron is higher than that of the wood","iron is a better radiator of heat than wood","iron conducts heat more quickly from the hand than wood",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"An iron rod of length 50m and at a temperature of 60<sup>o<\/sup>C is heated to 70<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate its new length. (Linear expansivity of iron = 1.2 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["50.006m","50.060m","51.600m","51.200m",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The heat capacity of a substance is the energy","options":["required to raise the temperature of a unit mass of the substance by one degree.","required to raise the temperature of the substance by one degree","absorbed by the substance at constant temperature","lost by a unit mass of the substance.",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The temperature of a piece of metal of mass 9 g is raised from 10<sup>o<\/sup>C to 110<sup>o<\/sup>C when it absorbs 108J of heat energy. Determine the specific heat capacity of the metal in J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","options":["1.2","12.0","120.0","1200.0",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct?","options":["A sea breeze is due to convection in air","Cotton materials are better than woollen ones for use in hot weather","Convectional currents play an important role in the cooling of the engine of a motor car","The vacuum space in a flask helps to reduce heat loss by radiation.",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Calculate the heat energy required to change 0.1kg of ice at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C to water boiling at 100<sup>o<\/sup>C. (Specific heat capacity of water = 4200 J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>) (Specific latent heat of fusion of ice = 336,000 J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["75,600J","336,000J","340,200J","378,000J.",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about evaporation is not correct?","options":["The rate of evaporation of a liquid varies with temperature","The molecules of an evaporating liquid have an average speed","Evaporation occurs when faster molecules escape from the surface of a liquid","Evaporation takes place inside a liquid.",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Calculate the power rating of an immersion heater used for 10 minutes to increase the temperature of 10kg of water by 15K. (Specific heat capacity of water = 4200 J l<g<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["1,050W","16,800W","18,060W","20,160W",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A ray of light is incident on 'a plane mirror at an angle of 20<sup>o<\/sup>. This mirror is rotated through, twice this angle, In this new position the angle between the incident ray and the reflected ray is","options":["20<sup>o<\/sup>","40<sup>o<\/sup>","80<sup>o<\/sup>","120<sup>o<\/sup>.",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The air column in a resonance tube is set into resonance by a vibrating tuning fork. The resultant waves in the air column will be","options":["mechanical and transverse","progressive and longitudinal","stationary and transverse","stationary and longitudinal.",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The image of an object is located 6cm behind a convex mirror. If its magnification is 0.6, calculate the focal length of the mirror","options":["3.75cm","6.60cm","10.00cm","15.00cm",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The refractive index of glass for yellow light is greater than that for red light because yellow light","options":["has a greater amplitude than red light","is more intense than red light","travels more slowly than red light","deviates less than red light",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The real image of an object formed by a converging lens of focal length 15cm, is three times the size of the object. Calculate the object distance","options":["60cm","30cm","20cm","15cm",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct about long sight?","options":["A Iong-sighted person can see distant objects clearly","ight from a nearby object is focused behind the retina.","The eyeball is too short","The defect is corrected by using a diverging lens.",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The amplitude of a wave is the","options":["distance between two successive troughs of the wave","separation of two adjacent particles vibrating in phase","maximum displacement of the wave particle from the equilibrium position","distance travelled by a wave in a complete cycle of its motion",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"ln order to obtain a sound note of a high pitch from a wire stretched by a constant tension, the wire must be","options":["short and thick","short and thin","long and thick","long and thin",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"If the position of resonance in a resonance tube is 16.50cm from open end of the tube, calculate the distance from the open end to the next position where resonance occurs. (Neglect end-correction)","options":["24.75cm","33.00cm","41.25cm","49.50cm",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Thunder is usually heard some seconds after lightning is observed because","options":["the human eye is more sensitive to light than the ear to sound","sound and light travel in different media","thunder occurs after lightning","light travels faster than sound",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The parts of a bar magnet at which the magnetic effect is strongest are called the","options":["poles","neutral points","magnetic declinations","magnetic meridians",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A resistance wire of length 2 m and of uniform cross-sectional area 5.0 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup> m<sup>2<\/sup> has a resistance of 2.2 \u03a9 Calculate its resistivity","options":["1.8 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup>\u03a9m","5.5 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup>\u03a9m","1.8 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup>\u03a9m","5.8 x 10<sup>7<\/sup>\u03a9m",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Magnetic flux density is defined as the","options":["total number of magnetic lines of force surrounding a magnet","number of magnetic lines of force per unit area normal to the magnetic field","strength of the magnetic field surrounding a current-carrying conductor","magnetic force exerted on a unit magnetic pole",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The voltage and current in the primary of a transformer are 200V and 2Arespectively. lf the transformer is used to light ten 12 V, 30 W bulbs, calculate its efficiency.","options":["100%","90%","75%","50%",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"In a uniform electric field, the magnitude of the force on a charge of 0.2 C is 4N. Calculate the electric field intensity","options":["20 N C<sup>-1<\/sup>","8 N C<sup>-1<\/sup>","5 N C<sup>-1<\/sup>","2 N C<sup>-1<\/sup>",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A 10- \u03a9 coil takes 21 s to melt 10g of ice at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C. Assuming no heat losses, determine the current in the coil. (Specific latent heat of fusion of ice = 336 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["16A","5A","4A","3A",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A point charge of magnitude 2\u03bcC is moved through a distance of 0.02 m against uniform field of intensity 25 Vm<sup>-1<\/sup> Calculate the work done on the charge","options":["5.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>J","1.0 x10<sup>-6<\/sup>J","5.0 x10<sup>-7<\/sup>J","1.0 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>J",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Bohr\u2019s atomic model proves most successful for the explanation of the. I. structure of the hydrogen atom; II. line spectra of the hydrogen atom; III. Multi-electron atoms. Which of the statements above is\/are correct?","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","I and III only",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"I. All elements emit and absorb characteristic spectra. II. Spectral analysis is an important method of identifying environmental pollutants. III. The chemical composition of stars could be determined using spectral analysis. Which of the statements above are correct?","options":["I, II and III","II and III only","I and III only","I and II only",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A metal has work function of 4.375 eV Calculate its threshold frequency. (h = 6.6 x 10<sup>-34<\/sup>Js; 1eV = 1.6 x 10<sup>-19<\/sup>J)","options":["2.01 X 10<sup>15<\/sup>Hz","1.06x10<sup>15<\/sup>Hz","6.30 x 10<sup>14<\/sup>Hz","1.60 x 10<sup>14<\/sup>Hz",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The half-life of a radioactive substance is","options":["its average life time","one-half the value of its decay constant.","the length of time needed by the substance to decay completely","the length of time during which the activity of the substance reduces by 50%.",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"The half-life of a radioactive element is 5 Calculate its decay constant","options":["0.113s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.436 s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.139 s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.193 s<sup>-1<\/sup>.",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"A sheet of paper is placed in the path of the following radiations: I. Alpha particles II. Beta particles III. Gamma rays. Which of the radiations will pass through the sheet of paper?","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","II and III only",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following are the essential parts of an atomic bomb?","options":["Uranium and neutrons","Radium and polonium","Nitrogen and neutrons","ranium and \u03b1 - particles.",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a safety precaution in a nuclear station?","options":["Radioactive materials are stored in glass casings","Radioactive materials are handled with remote-controlled tongs","Technicians in nuclear stations wear radio-sensitive badges which are checked regularly.","Radioactive materials are kept in thick-walled lead containers",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1999"},{"question":"which of the following pairs of physical quantities comprises vectors?","options":["capacitance and inductance","force ratio and velocity ratio","friction and momentum","energy and power","electric field potential and electric field intensity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A piece of stone attached to one end pf string is whirled round in a horizontal circle. When the string is  suddenly cut, the stone will","options":["move towards te centre of the circle","stop moving immediately","move along a circular path of smaller radius","fly off in a direction tangential to the circular path","acquire greater centripetal force"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The term torque means","options":["the moment","the resultant of several forces acting on a body in equilibrum","two equal and oposite forces whose lines of action do not coincide","two coplaner forces at right angles to each other","the equilibrant of two concurrent forces"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"An object is protected with a velocity of 100m<sup>-1<\/sup> at an angle of 60<sup>o<\/sup> to the vertical. Calculate the time taken by the object to reach the highest point (Take g as 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","options":["5.0s","8.7s","10.0s","17.3s","20.0s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The earth is not a perfect sphere because its equatorial axis is longer than the polar axis. where on the earth's surface would an object have its greatest weight?","options":["half way between the equator and the north pole","near the equator","half way between the equator and the south pole","at either pole","at the equator"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"a ball of mass 5.0kg hits a smooth vertical wall normally with a speed of 2m<sup>-1<\/sup> and rebounds with the same speed. Determine the impulse experienced by the ball","options":["20.0kgm<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.0kgm<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.3kgm<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.0kgm<sup>-1<\/sup>","10.0kgm<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The lower and upper fixed points of a mecury-in-glass thermometer are marked Y and 180mm respectively. On a particular the mecury meniscus in the thermometer rises to 45mm. If the corresponding reading on a scale is 10<sup>o<\/sup>, calculate the value of Y.","options":["4mm","18mm","30mm","135mm","450mm"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A piece of brass of mass 170kg has its temperature raised from 0<sup>o<\/sup>C to 30<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate its increase in volume, given the density of brass at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C as 8.5 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>kgm<sup>3<\/sup> and its cubic expansivity as 5.7 x 10<sup>-1<\/sup>k<sup>1<\/sup>","options":["3.4 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","4.3 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","3.4 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","3.4 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","3.4 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"How much heat is emitted when a body of mass 200g cools from 37<sup>o<\/sup>C to 31<sup>o<\/sup>C? (specific heat capacity of the body = 0.4Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>,)","options":["4800J","1200J","480J","202J","80J"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"If the cubic expansivity of brass between 27<sup>o<\/sup>C and 100<sup>o<\/sup>C is 5.7 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>, What is its linear expansivity?","options":["2.85 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.90 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.86 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.70 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.63 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Air at temperature 527<sup>o<\/sup>C and pressure 30 atmospheres is admitted into the cylinder of an engine. Calculate the pressure of the gas when it has expanded to 5 times its volume and cooled to 127<sup>o<\/sup>C as it leaves the engine","options":["1.5 atmospheres","2.5 atmospheres","3.0 atmospheres","12.8 atmospheres","15.0 atmospheres"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The inside of a vacuum flak is usually coated with silver to reduce heat loss by","options":["evaporation","radiation","conduction","convention","condensation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Dry oxygen is trapped by a pellet of mercury in a uniform capillary tube which is sealed at one end. The length of the column of oxygen at 27<sup>o<\/sup>C is 50cm. if the pressure of the oxygen is constant, at what temperature will the length be 60cm?","options":["360.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","240.6<sup>o<\/sup>C","237.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","87.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","36<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A waterfall is 1.260m high. Calculate the change in temperature of a quantity of water that falls from the top to the bottom of the waterfall. (Neglect heat losses to the surroundings, take g as 10m<sup>-2<\/sup> and specific heat capacity of water as 4200Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["0.3<sup>o<\/sup>C","3.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","33.3<sup>o<\/sup>C","42.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","100.0<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A piece of metal is heated until it becomes red-hot, it is then quickly transferred into a beaker containing boiling water. What effect will this have on the boiling water?","options":["the boiling water rises slightly","the boiling point rises sharply","the rate of vaporisation of the boiling water increases","the boiling point first rises and then falls","neither the boiling point nor the rate of vaporisation increases"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A 90-W immersion heater is used to supply energy for five minutes. The energy supplied is used to completely melt 180g of a solid at is melting point. Neglecting energy losses to the surroundings, calculate the specific latent heat of fusion of the solid","options":["0.5Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.5Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","15.0Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","450.0Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","150Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"If an ebonite rod is rubbed with fur","options":["both the ebonite rod and the fur will be negatively charged","the ebonite rod will be positively charged while the fur will have no charge","there will be electron transfer only if the ebonite rod is earthed","the ebonite rod will be negatively charged while the fur will be positively charged","the ebonite rod will be positively charged while the fur will be negatively charged"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"An eclipse of the sun by the moon occurs when the sun, the moon and the earth are in a straight line and the","options":["earth casts a shadow on the moon","moon casts a shadow on the sun","moon is between the sun and the earth","earth is between the sun and the moon","sun is between the moon and the earth"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"What is the image distance of an object placed at a distance of 2f from a converging lens of focal length f?","options":["f\/4","f\/2","f","2f","4f"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The images formed by diverging lenses are always","options":["diminished, virtual and inverted","diminished, virtual and errect","diminished inverted and real","magnidied, virtual and errect","magnified, real and inverted"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A converging lens of focal length 5cm is used as a magnifying glass by a man whose nearpoint is 35cm. Calculate the magnification given by the lens","options":["8","7","6","5","4"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"An astronomical telescope having an objective of focal length 100cm and an eyepiece of focal length 10cm is used in normal adjustment, calculate the separation of the lenses","options":["0.10m","0.90cm","1.10m","1.80m","2.20m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A lantern gives an image of 3m square of a slide 7.62cm square on a screen. If the screen is 10m from the projection lens of the lantern, calculate the focal length of the lens","options":["40.3cm","26.1cm","24.8cm","0.7cm","0.3cm"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"the shortest length of the air column in a resonance tube at resonance is 0.12m and the next resonance length is 0.37m. calculate the frequency of vibration given that the speed of sound in air is 340m<sup>-1<\/sup>","options":["1360Hz","694Hz","680Hz","34Hz","340Hz"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A sonometer wire under a tension of N10N, produces a frequency of 250Hz when plucked. Keeping the length of the wire constant, the tension is adjusted to produce a new frequency of 350Hz. Calculate the new tension","options":["39.2N","19.6N","14.2N","7.4N","5.1N"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Calculate he wavelength of a note which is one octave lower than a note of 256Hz in a medium in which the speed of sound is 352ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","options":["0.69m","1.38m","2.75m","5.50m","9.30m"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Which of the following are both mechanical and transverse?","options":["infra-red rays","gamma rays","sound waves","water waves","micro waves"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The gravitational force of the moon is one-sixth that of the earth. If a body weighs 6.0N on the moon. Calculate its weight on the earth","options":["36.0N","12.0N","6.0N","2.0N","1.0N"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"In the electrical method of magnetisation, the polarity of the magnet depends on the","options":["amount of current passed","direction of current","magnetic material used","size of the magnetic material","orientation of the magnetic material in space"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A cell of e.m.f. 1.5v is connected in series with a resistor of 3\\(\\Omega\\). A high resistance voltmeter connected across the cell registers only 0.9v. Calculate the internal resistance of the cell","options":["5.0\\(\\Omega\\)","4.5\\(\\Omega\\)","2.4\\(\\Omega\\)","2.0\\(\\Omega\\)","1.8\\(\\Omega\\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Calculate the resistance of the filament of lamp rated at 240V 60W","options":["240\\(\\Omega\\)","360\\(\\Omega\\)","960\\(\\Omega\\)","144\\(\\Omega\\)","2880\\(\\Omega\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Lenz's law of electromagnet states that","options":["the induced charge is constant for a fixed change of force","a force is exerted on a current-carrying conductor in a magnetic field","the magnitude of the induced e.m.f in a circuit is proportional to the rate of change of the number of lines of force linking the circuit","the induced current in a conductor is in such a direction as to oppose the change producing it","e.m.f. is induced in a circuit whenever there is a change in the magnetic flux linked with the circuit"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A proton of charge 1.6 x 10<sup>19<\/sup>C is projected into a uniform magnetic field of flux density with a constant speed of 1.6 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the magnitude of the force exerted on it by the field","options":["0.0N","2.0 x 10<sup>-21<\/sup>N","1.3 x 10<sup>-17<\/sup>N","5.1 x 10<sup>-14<\/sup>N","2.3 x 10<sup>13<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Use the following data to determine the length L of a wire when a fore of 30N is applied, assuming Hooke's law is obeyed<br>\r\n\\(\\begin{array}{c|c}\\text{Force applied\/N} & 0 & 5 & 10 & 30\\\\ \\hline \\text{length of wire\/mm} & 500.0 & 500.0 & 501.0 & L \\end{array}\\)","options":["3.0mm","3.5mm","503.00mm","503.5mm","506.0mm"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Which of the following explains the concave meniscus of water in a clean glass tube? the","options":["adhension between water and glass molecules is greater than the sdhension between water molecules","cohension between water molecules is greater then the adhension between glass and water molecule","molecules of water near the glass move faster than the molecules at the centre of the tube","molecules of water at the water-air boundary are often attracted to the centre of the tube","weight of the water pulls the centre part of the surface down"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"An electron is accelerated from rest through a potential difference of 70kV in a vacuum. Calculate the maximum speed acquired by the electron (electronic charge = -1.6 x 10<sup>-19<\/sup>; mass of an electron = 9.1 x 10<sup>-31<\/sup>kg)","options":["3.00 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.46 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.57 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.32 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.11 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"When light from a source is sent through a gas.  i. certain wavelengths are absorbed.  ii. a dark line is left. Which of the following is\/are correct?","options":["i only","iii only","i and ii only","i and iii only","ii and iii only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"The process of increasing the energy of an atom via inelastic collision with an electron is known as","options":["ionization","excitation","field emission","photoemission","thermonic emission"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"A radioactive nuclide of proton number X emits a \\(\\beta\\)-particle to form a new nuclide to proton number Y. The correct equation relating X and Y is","options":["X = Y - 1","X = Y + 1","X = 1 - Y","X = \\(\\frac{1}{y}\\)","X = Y"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"Two radioactive elements X and Y have half-lives of 100 and 50 years respectively. Samples of X and Y initially contain equal number of atoms. What is the ratio of the number of the remaining atoms of X to that of Y after 200 years?","options":["4:1","3:1","1:1","1:2","1:4"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"It is always not possible to determine exactly and simultaneously the position and momentum of a particle. This statement is known as the","options":["De broglie's law","Heisenberg's uncertainty principle","Compton effect","Frank-Hertz experimental law","Wave particle paradox"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1998"},{"question":"An object of mass 0.40 kg attached to the end of a string is whirled around in a horizontal circle of radius 2.0m with a constant speed of 8\\(ms^{-1}\\). Calculate the angular velocity of the object","options":["0.8rad\\(s^{-1}\\)","2 rad\\(s^{-1}\\)","4 rad\\(s^{-1}\\)","8 rad\\(s^{-1}\\)","16 rad\\(s^{-1}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"An object falls freely from a height of 25m onto the roof a building 5m high. Calculate the velocity with which the object strikes the roof (g=10\\(ms^{-2}\\)","options":["17.3\\(ms^{-2}\\)","20\\(ms^{-2}\\)","24.5\\(ms^{-2}\\)","125\\(ms^{-2}\\)","200\\(ms^{-2}\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A ball of mass 0.1kg approaching a tennis player with a velocity of 10\\(ms^{-1}\\),is hit back in the opposite direction with a velocity of 15\\(ms^{-1}\\). If  the time of impact between the racket and the ball is 0.01s, calculate the magnitude of the force with which the ball is hit","options":["5000N","500N","250N","50N","25N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Two blocks of the same dimension, one steel and the other wooden are dropped simultaneously from the same height. If they fall freely neglecting air resistance the","options":["Two blocks hit the ground simultaneously because they have the same acceleration","Two blocks reach the ground at the same time because their dimensions are the same","Wooden block being lighter than the steel block reaches the ground first","Steel block reaches the ground first because it is denser than the wooden block","Steel block takes half as much time as the wooden block to reach the ground because it is more massive than the wooden block"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Two forces 3N and 4N act on a body in directions due north and due east respectively. Calculate their equilibrant","options":["5N 53\u00b0 east of North","5N 53\u00b0 west of the south","5N 37\u00b0 north of east","7N 37\u00b0 west of North","7N 37\u00b0 south of west"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A missile weighing 400N on the earth surface is shot into the atmosphere to an altitude of 6.4 x \\(10^{-6}\\)m. Taking the earth as a sphere of radius 6.4 x \\(10^{-6}\\)m and assuming the inverse-square law of  universal gravitation, what would be the weight of the missile at that altitude?","options":["100N","200N","400N","800N","1600N"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A solid plastic cube of side 0.2m is submerged in a liquid density of 0.8kg\\(m^{-3}\\). Calculate the upthrust of the liquid on the cube (g=10\\(ms^{-2}\\)","options":["0.064N","0.025N","0.016N","0.008N","0.003N"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Steel bars each of length 3m at 28\u00b0C are to be used for constructing a rail line. If the linear expansitivity of the steel is 1 x \\(10^{-5}K^{-1}\\),what is the safety gap that must be left between the successive bars if the highest temperature expected is 40\u00b0C?","options":["1.2x \\(10^{-1}cm\\)","7.2x\\(10^{-1}cm\\)","6x\\(10^{-1}cm\\)","3.6x\\(10^{-1}cm\\)","1.8x\\(10^{-1}cm\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Which of the following explains why a thick glass cup cracks when boiling water is poured into it?","options":["Unequal expansion of the exterior and interior walls of the cup","Anomalous expansion of the water","Greater specific latent capacity of water compared with that of glass","Large increase in the heat capacity of the cup","High density of the water"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"When white light is incident on a glass prism the spectrum produced on a screen placed beyond the prism is due to?","options":["Diffraction","Reflection","Refraction","Polarisation","Interference"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"At what distance from a simple microscope must an object be placed so that the image 5 times the size of the object is produced 20cm from the lens?","options":["2cm","3.3cm","4cm","5cm","15cm"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A solid material of volume 100\\(cm^{-3}\\) is heated through a temperature difference of 40\u00b0C. Calculate the increase in the volume of the material if its linear expansitivity is 2 x \\(10^{-6}K{-1}\\)","options":["2.4 x\\(10^{-2}cm^{-3}\\)","1.6 x\\(10^{-2}cm^{-3}\\)","8 x\\(10^{-2}cm^{-3}\\)","5 x\\(10^{-2}cm^{-3}\\)","4 x\\(10^{-2}cm^{-3}\\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Calculate the quantity of heat released when 100g of steam at 100\u00b0C condenses to water(Take the specific latent heat of vaporization of water as 2.3x \\(10^6Jkg^{-1}\\))","options":["2.3x\\(10^{1}J\\)","2.3x\\(10^{2}J\\)","2.3x\\(10^{4}J\\)","2.3x\\(10^{5}J\\)","3.3x\\(10^{7}J\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A fixed mass of gas occupies a volume of 20\\(cm^3\\) at a fixed pressure of 700mmHg. Assuming that the temperature remains constant, what will be the volume of the gas at 750mmHg?","options":["2.5\\(cm^3\\)","15.5\\(cm^3\\)","18.7\\(cm^3\\)","21.4\\(cm^3\\)","72.5\\(cm^3\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A converging lens of focal length 15cm is used to obtain a real image magnified  \\(1\\frac{1}{2}\\) times. Calculate the distance of the image from the lens?","options":["37.5cm","22.5cm","15cm","7.5cm","3.3cm"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A cup containing 100g of pure water at 20\u00b0C is placed in a refrigerator. If the refrigerator extracts heat at a rate of 840J per minute, calculate the time taken for the water to freeze. Neglect the heat capacity of the material of the cup. (Specific heat capacity of water =4.2J\\(g^{-1}K^{-2}\\))((Specific latent heat fusion of water =336J\\(g^{-1}\\)","options":["15minutes","20 minutes","42 minutes","50 minutes","84 minutes"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about kinetic theory of matter is not correct?","options":["The molecules of matter are always in motion","When a body is heated the average kinetic energy of its molecules decreases","Molecules of a liquid move more freely than those of a solid","Matter is made up of very tiny particles called molecules","The molecules of a gas move more freely than those of a liquid"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Which of the following is not correct about the Rutherford\u2019s model of an atom?","options":["The mass of an atom is concentrated around the nucleus","The nucleus of an atom is positively charged","The nucleus is surrounded by the electron cloud","The model is applicable to atoms with only one electron in the outer shell","The diameter of the nucleus is \\(10^{-15}m\\)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not true of nuclear fission?","options":["Mother nucleus is broken into two daughter nuclei of roughly equal parts","Neutron is normally used in bombarding heavy nucleus","Two light nuclei are made to combine to form a heavy nucleus","Very enormous energy is released","There is an apparent loss of mass"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"When a paint brush is removed from clean water, the bristles of the brush are pulled together because of","options":["The viscosity of the surrounding air","The low density of water","Surface tension forces","The weight of the brush bristles","The mass of the brush bristles"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The odor of a leaking gas is perceived at a distance from the source. This is made possible by the process of","options":["Sublimation","Diffusion","Osmosis","Evaporation","Capillarity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The current in the primary coil of a transformer is 2.5A. If the coil has 50 turns and the secondary250 turns, calculate the current in the secondary coil. Neglect energy losses in the transformer","options":["0.2A","0.5A","2.5A","5A","12.5A"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"In a photocell, light energy is converted to","options":["Electrical energy","Chemical energy","Heat energy","Mechanical energy","Kinetic energy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Two identical waves traveling in the same direction are superimposed. What should be the phase difference between the waves for maximum destructive interference to occur?","options":["20\u00b0","45\u00b0","180\u00b0","225\u00b0","270\u00b0"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"When a resistor of resistance R is connected across a cell, the terminal p.d of the cell is reduced to three quarters of its e.m.f. The internal resistance of the cell is expressed as","options":["R\/4","R\/3","R\/2","3R\/4","3R"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A pipe open at both ends, produces a fundamental note. If the velocity of sound in air is V and L the length of the pipe, which of the following expresses the frequency of the note? Neglect end correction","options":["2V\/L","V\/2L","V\/3L","V\/4L","V\/5L"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A progressive wave has a wavelength of 50cm. calculate the phase difference between two points at a distance of 20cm apart.","options":["10\/3\u03c0","5\/2 \u03c0","4\/5 \u03c0","2\/3 \u03c0","\u03c0\/3"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"An alternating current with a peak value of 5A passes through a resistor of resistance 10\u2126. Calculate the rate at which energy is dissipated in the resistor","options":["250W","125W","50W","35.4W","12.5W"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"Which of the following is not true of the similarities between a camera and the human eye?","options":["Both the camera and the human eye have light proof interiors","Both the camera and the human eye have light sensitive screens","Inverted images are formed on the screen in both","The distance between the lens and the screen is fixed in both","The amount of light entering both the eye and the camera can be adjusted"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The magnification produced with a converging lens is 5. If the object is a square wire gauze of side 2cm, calculate the area of the image","options":["100\\(cm^3\\)","40\\(cm^3\\)","20\\(cm^3\\)","10\\(cm^3\\)","4\\(cm^3\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"The current in a series R-L-C circuit attains its maximum value when the","options":["Impedance is greater than the capacitive reactance","Inductive reactance is equal to the capacitive reactance","Inductive reactance is greater than the capacitive reactance","capacitive reactance  is less than resistance","Inductive reactance is greater than the capacitive reactance"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A charge of 1 x \\(10^{-5}\\)C experiences a force of 40N at a certain point in space. What is the magnitude of the electric field intensity at the point in Newton and couloumb","options":["8 x \\(10^{6}\\)","4 x \\(10^{6}\\)","3 x \\(10^{-4}\\)","2 x \\(10^{-4}\\)","5 x \\(10^{-7}\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A capacitor of capacitance 25\u00b5F is connected to an a.c power source of frequency 200\/\u03c0Hz. Calculate the reactance of the capacitor","options":["0.01\u2126","0.02\u2126","50\u2126","100\u2126","150\u2126"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"During the electrolysis of copper (II) tetraoxosulphate (VI) solution, an ammeter shows a steady reading of 1A for 30minutes while 6.6 x \\(10^{-4}\\)kg of copper is liberated. Calculate the error in the ammeter  The electrochemical equivalent of copper is 3.30 x \\(10^{-7}kgC{-1}\\)","options":["0.001A","0.011A","0.111A","1A","1.1A"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"In a nuclear reaction, the mass defect is 2 x \\(10^{-6}\\)g. Calculate the energy released given that the velocity of light is 3 x \\(10^{8}ms^{-1}\\)","options":["9 x \\(10^{7}\\)J","1.8 x \\(10^{8}\\)J","1.8 x \\(10^{9}\\)J","9 x \\(10^{-10}\\)J","3.6 x \\(10^{11}\\)J"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"An atom radiates 1.5 x \\(10^{-19}\\)J of energy when an electron jumps from one energy level to another. What is the wavelength of the emitted radiation? (Planck\u2019s constant =6.6 x \\(10^{-34}\\)Js. Speed of light in air=3 x \\(10^{8}ms^{-1}\\)","options":["1.32 x \\(10^{-6}\\)m","2.98 x \\(10^{-6}\\)m","3.32 x \\(10^{-6}\\)m","6.82 x \\(10^{-6}\\)m","8.01 x \\(10^{-6}\\)m"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1997"},{"question":"A loaded test-tube which floats upright in water is carefully and slightly depressed and then released. Which of the following best describes the sub-sequent motion of the test-tube?","options":["Circular","Rotational","Random","Oscillatory","Translational"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The diagram above illustrates the velocity-time graph of the motion of a body. Calculate the total distance covered by the body","options":["50m","65m","175m","225m","300m"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A ball of mass 5.0kg hits a smooth vertical wall normally with a speed of 2ms<sup>-1<\/sup> and rebounds with the same speed. Determine the impulse experienced by the ball","options":["20.0kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","10.0kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.0kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.3kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.0kg ms<sup>-1<\/sup>."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A rocket is launched from the surface of the earth. If the radius of the earth is 6.4 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>m and the acceleration of free fall due to gravity is 1Oms<sup>-1<\/sup> calculate the escape velocity of the rocket.","options":["2.53 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.13 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>ms","8.00 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.23 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.41 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The velocity ratio and efficiency of a system of pulleys are 6 and 80% respectively. How much effort is required to lift a load of mass 120kg with this system? (g=10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["25N","90N","96N","250N","960N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Two spanners X and Y of lengths 15cm and 20cm respectively are used in turn to give a screw of pitch 2mm one complete rotation. If Rx and Ry are the respective velocity ratios of the spanners then the ratio Rx : Ry is","options":["1 : 50","3 : 20","3:4","4:3","20:3"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The magnitude of the force required to make an object of mass M move with speed V in a circular path of radius R is given by the expression.","options":["mr\/v","(mr) <sup>2<\/sup>\/v","mv<sup>2<\/sup>\/r","mv\/2","mv\/r"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A body of mass 4.2kg moving with velocity 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup> due east, hits a stationary body of mass 2.8kg. If they stick together after collision and move with velocity V due east, calculate the value of V","options":["3ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","6ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","7ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","15ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","17ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A body of mass 2kg is suspended from the ceiling of a lift with a light inextensible string. lf the lift moves upwards with acceleration of 2ms<sup>-2<\/sup>, calculate the magnitude of the tension in the string (g = 1Oms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["24N","20N","16N","4N","0N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A stationary object of mass 4kg is set in motion by a net force of 5ON. If the object attains is speed of 5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>  in time. Calculate the value of t.","options":["0.20s","0.40s","0.63s","0.80s","1.30s"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Two simple pendula x and y make 400 and 500 oscillations respectively in equal time. If the period of oscillation of x is 1.5 seconds, what is the period of oscillation of y?","options":["0.53s","0.83s","1.20s","1.50s","1.88s."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A platinum-resistance thermometer has a resistance of 59 at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C and 9\u03a9 at l00<sup>o<\/sup>C. Assuming that resistance changes uniformly with temperature, calculate the resistance of the thermometer when the temperature is 45<sup>o<\/sup>C","options":["13.9 \u03a9","8.9 \u03a9","6.8 \u03a9","3.2 \u03a9","1.8 \u03a9"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The linear expansivity of a metal P is twice that of another metal Q. When these materials are heated through the same temperature change, their increase in length is the same. Calculate the ratio of the original length of P to that of Q.","options":["1:4","1:2","2:1","4:1","6:1"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The pressure of a fixed mass of gas is 2.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup> at a known temperature. Assuming that the temperature remains constant, what will be the pressure of the gas if its volume is halved?","options":["1.0x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","2.0X10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","3.0x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","4.0 x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","5.0 x10<sup>5<\/sup>Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct?","options":["Heat energy can be transformed into mechanical energy","That total heat content of a body is the sum of the kinetic energies of its molecules","lf a body is heated, its molecules move faster.","lf a body is cooled, molecular movement remains constant.",""],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A 400W immersion heater is used to heat a liquid of mass 0.5kg. lf the temperature of the liquid increases by 2.5<sup>o<\/sup>C in one second, calculate the specific heat capacity of the liquid (Neglect heat losses to the surroundings)","options":["80 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","320Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","500Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","1200J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>","2000J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The heating element in an electric kettle is usually located near the bottom of the kettle because","options":["water is a good conductor of heat","heat can be more quickly radiated to all parts of the water","no heat can be lost to the surroundings","the convectional currents which are set up can carry heat to all parts of the water","the molecules of the heating element can carry heat to all parts of the water."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The inside of a vacuum flask is usually coated with silver to reduce heat lost by","options":["convection","conduction","radiation","absorption","evaporation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The saturated vapour pressure of a liquid increases as the","options":["volume of the liquid increases","volume of the liquid decreases","temperature of the liquid increases","temperature of the liquid decreases","mass of the liquid decreases"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Cloud formation is the direct result of","options":["precipitation","vaporization","fusion","sublimation","condensation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"In which of the following media would sound waves travel fastest?","options":["Kerosine","Alcohol","Water","lron","Air"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A ray of light strikes a plane mirror at a glancing angle of 50<sup>o<\/sup>. Calculate the angle between the incident and reflected rays","options":["20<sup>o<\/sup>","40<sup>o<\/sup>","50<sup>o<\/sup>","80<sup>o<\/sup>","100<sup>o<\/sup>."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"When a ray of light is incident normally on an air- glass interface, its angle of refraction is","options":["0<sup>o<\/sup>","42<sup>o<\/sup>","45<sup>o<\/sup>","60<sup>o<\/sup>","90<sup>o<\/sup>."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"When a ray of light is incident normally on an air- glass interface, its angle of refraction is","options":["0<sup>o<\/sup>","42<sup>o<\/sup>","45<sup>o<\/sup>","60<sup>o<\/sup>","90<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The refractive index of a medium relative to air is 1.8. Calculate the critical angle for the medium to the nearest degree.","options":["18<sup>o<\/sup>","34<sup>o<\/sup>","45<sup>o<\/sup>","68<sup>o<\/sup>","90<sup>o<\/sup>."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Which of the following instruments produces sound by the vibration of air column?","options":["Piano","Guitar","Flute","Hand bell","Talking drum"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The walls and ceilings of many standard auditoria are covered with perforated pads to","options":["increase the intensity of sound waves","increase the loudness of sound waves","reduce the effect of reverberations of sound waves","increase the interference effect of sound waves","decrease the frequency of sound waves."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A string of length 1.0 m vibrates in 10 loops. If the total mass of the string is 1.0 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup> kg and the tension in it is 10N, calculate the frequency of the vibration.","options":["50Hz","100Hz","250Hz","400Hz","500Hz"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The distance between two successive crests of a water is 1m. lf a particle on the surface of the water makes two complete vertical oscillations in 1 second, calculate the speed of the wave","options":["0.5 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","3.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A sound wave of velocity 350 ms<sup>-1<\/sup> is directed towards the surface of water. lf the ratio of the wavelength of sound in water to that in air is 425:100, calculate the velocity on the wave in water","options":["82.4ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","148.8ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","350.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1487.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","3500.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The speed of sound in air is 330ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. How far from the centre of a storm is an observer who hears a thunder clap 2s after the lightning flash? (Neglect the time taken by light to travel to the observer)","options":["1320m","660m","600m","330m","165m"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"CalcuIate the power delivered by a 3-phase line if its voltage and current at 132KV and 60A respectively.","options":["2.38 x 10<sup>7<\/sup>W","7.92 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>W","3.96 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>W","2.64 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>W","7.92 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>W"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The main function of the mouth of a telephone is to convert sound energy into","options":["heat energy","light energy","chemical energy","electrical energy","mechanical energy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a component of a d.c. electric motor?","options":["Commutator","Field magnets","Slip rings","Armature","Carbon brushes"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A wire of length 100cm and cross-sectional area of 2.0 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>cm<sup>2<\/sup> has a resistance of 0.10 \u03a9. Calculate its electrical conductivity.","options":["5.0 x 10<sup>7<\/sup>\u03a9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>\u03a9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>\u03a9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>\u03a9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>\u03a9<sup>-1<\/sup>cm<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Lenz's law of electromagnetic induction states that","options":["e.m.f. is induced in a circuit whenever there is a change in the magnetic flux linked with the circuit.","the induced current in a conductor is in such a direction as to oppose the change producing it","the magnitude of the induced e.m.f. in a circuit is proportional to the rate of change of the number of lines of force linking the circuit","a force is exerted on a current-carrying conductor in a magnetic Held","the induced charge is constant for a fixed change of flux."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"A cell of e.m.f. 1.5V is connected in series with a resistor of resistance 39. A high-resistance voltmeter connected across the cell registers only 0.9V. Calculate the internal resistance of the cell","options":["1.85\u03a9","2.0\u03a9","2.4\u03a9","4.5\u03a9","5.0\u03a9"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Soft iron is used in making the armature of an electric bell because it","options":["retains its magnetism for a longtime","Loses its magnetism readily","Produces permanent magnets","is not easily magnetised","decreases the magnetic effect of a direct current"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Calculate the amount of heat generated in an external load of resistance 89 if an alternating current of peak value 5A is passed through for 100s.","options":["20,000J","10,000J","5,000J","4,000J","200J"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"What is the decay constant of a radioactive element whose half-life is 3 seconds","options":["0.132s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.23s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.347s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.693s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.924s<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Which of the following substances is most viscous at room temperature?","options":["Water","Alcohol","Petrol","Palm oil","Kerosine"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Which of the following is not part of the electromagnetic spectrum?","options":["Radio wave","Gamma ray","Infra-red ray","Alpha particle","X-ray."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Which of the following is used in a nuclear reactor to slow down fast-moving neutrons?","options":["Carbondioxide gas","Liquid sodium metal","Concrete shield","Graphite rods","Boron rods"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Which of the following particles\/rays do not originate from the nucleus of an atom?","options":["Alpha particles","Beta particles","Neutrons","Gamma rays","X-rays"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"The count rate of an alpha-particle source is 400 per minute. If the half-life of the source is 5 days, what would be the count rate per minute after 15 days?","options":["20","25","50","200","400"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1996"},{"question":"Which of the following is a fundamental quantity?","options":["Heat capacity","Electric current","Torque","Reactance","Density"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A boy cycles continuously through a distance of 1.0 km in 5 minutes. Calculate his average speed","options":["0.3ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","3.3ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","16.6ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","20.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","200.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A student found out from a simple pendulum experiment that 20 oscillations were completed in 38 seconds. What is the period of oscillation of the pendulum?","options":["8.0s","3.8 s","2.0 s","1.9 s","0.5s"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A body of mass 7.5 kg is to be pulled up along a plane which is inclined at 30<sup>o<\/sup> to the horizontal. If the efficiency of the plane is 75%, what is the minimum force required to pull the body up the plane?<br>\r\n(g = 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["5.0 N","20.0 N","50.0 N","75.0 N","200.0 N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The angular speed of an object describing a circle of radius 4m with a linear constant speed of 10 ms<sup>-1<\/sup> is","options":["40.00 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>","14.00 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.50 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.58 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.40 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"At what angle to the horizontal must the nozzle of a machine gun be kept when firing to obtain a maximum horizontal range for the bullets?","options":["0.0<sup>o<\/sup>","22.5<sup>o<\/sup>","30.0<sup>o<\/sup>","45. 0<sup>o<\/sup>","90.0<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following will reduce the frequency of oscillation of a simple pendulum?","options":["Increasing the mass of the bob","Decreasing the mass of the bob","Increasing the length of the string","Decreasing the length of the string","Decreasing the amplitude of oscillation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A car travelling at a uniform speed of 120km h<sup>-1<\/sup> passes two stations in 4 minutes. Calculate the distance between the two stations.","options":["8km","15km","22km","30km","60km"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A machine has an efficiency of 60%. If the machine is required to overcome a load of 30 N with a force of 20 N calculate its mechanical advantage?","options":["0.7","0.9","1.5","2.5","10.0"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A body weighing 10 N in air is partially immersed in water. It displaces water of mass 0.3 kg. What is the upthrust on the body? (g = 10 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["13.0 N","7.0 N","3.3N","3.0N","0.3 N."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A brass rod is 2 m long at a certain temperature. Calculate the linear expansion of the rod for a temperature change of 100K. (Take the linear expansivity of brass as 1.8 x 10'5K\").","options":["0.3600 m","0.1800 m","0.0360 m","0.0036m","0.0018 m"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A body of specific heat capacity 450J kg<sup>-1<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup> falls to the ground from rest through a vertical height of 20m. Assuming conservation of energy, calculate the change in temperature of the body on striking the ground level. (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["0<sup>o<\/sup>C","2\/9<sup>o<\/sup>C","4\/9<sup>o<\/sup>C","9\/4<sup>o<\/sup>C","9\/2<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Hot water at a temperature of t is added to twice that amount of water at a temperature of 30<sup>o<\/sup>C. If the resulting temperature of the mixture is 50<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate t","options":["90<sup>o<\/sup>C","80<sup>o<\/sup>C","50<sup>o<\/sup>C","40<sup>o<\/sup>C","30<sup>o<\/sup>C."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"An air bubble of volume 2 cm* is formed 20 m under water. What will be its volume when it rises to just below the surface of the water if the atmospheric pressure is equivalent to a height of 10 m of water?","options":["6cm<sup>3<\/sup>","4cm<sup>3<\/sup>","3cm<sup>3<\/sup>","2cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The pressure of a given mass of gas changes from 200 Nm<sup>2<\/sup> to 100 N m<sup>2<\/sup>, while its temperature drops from 127<sup>o<\/sup>C to - 73<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate the radio of the final volume of the gas to its initial volume.","options":["2.4:1","2.0:1","1.2:1","1.0:1","1.0:2"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The temperature of glass vessel containing 100cm3 of mercury is raised from 10<sup>o<\/sup>C to 100<sup>o<\/sup>C. Calculate the apparent cubic expansion of the mercury. (Real cubic expansivity of mercury = 1.82 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>) (Cubic expansivity of glass = 2.4 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["0.52cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.42cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.87cm<sup>3<\/sup>","5.22cm<sup>3<\/sup>","14.22cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"An iron rod of mass 2kg and at a temperature of 280<sup>o<\/sup>C is dropped into some quantity of water initially at a temperature of 30<sup>o<\/sup>C. lf the temperature of the mixture is 70<sup>o<\/sup>C, calculate the mass of the water. (Neglect heat losses to the surroundings). Specific heat capacity of iron = 460 J kg<sup><\/sup>K<sup><\/sup>) (Specific heat capacity of water = 4200 Jkg <sup><\/sup>K<sup><\/sup>)","options":["0.58kg","0.77kg","1.15kg","1.50kg","2.04kg"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"How much heat is required to convert 20 g of ice at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C to water at the same temperature? (Specific latent heat of ice = 336 J g<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["1.35 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>J","5.38 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>J","6.72 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>J","7.06 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>J","8.06 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"When two objects P and Q are supplied with the same quantity of heat, the temperature change in P is observed to be twice that in Q. lf the masses of P and Q are the same, calculate the ratio of the specific heat capacities of Q to P.","options":["4 : 1","2 : 1","1 : 1","1 : 2","1 : 4."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The image of any real object formed by a diverging lens is always","options":["inverted","magnified","erect","real","the same size as the object"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following is not self-luminous?","options":["Incandescent electric bulb","Incandescent fluorescent tube","Lighted candle","The moon","The sun"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Sixty complete waves pass a particular point in 4s. lf the distance between three successive troughs of the waves is 15m, calculate the speed of the waves,","options":["300.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","225.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","112.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","75.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","16.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following wave characteristics can be used to distinguish a transverse wave from a longitudinal wave?","options":["Reflection","Refraction","Diffraction","Polarization","Interference"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A sound note of frequency 250 Hz and wavelength 1.3m is produced at a point near a hill. If the echo of the sound is received 1 second later at the point, how far away is the hill from the point?","options":["131.3m","162.5m","248.7m","251.3m","325.0m."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The period of a wave is 0.02 second. Calculate its wavelength if its speed is 330 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","options":["6.6m","5.0m","4.0m","3.3m","2.0m"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"An alternating voltage with a frequency of 50Hz has a period of","options":["0.02s","0.05s","0.20s","0.50 s","50.00s"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"What is the escape velocity of a body on the surface of the earth of radius R if the gravitational constant is G and the mass of the earth is M? (Neglect energy losses to the surroundings)","options":["2GR","2G\/R","2GR<sup>2<\/sup>","2GM\/R",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A charge of 1.6 x 10<sup>-10<\/sup>C is placed in a uniform electric field of intensity 2.0 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>NC<sup>-1<\/sup>. What is the magnitude of the electric force exerted on the charge?","options":["3.2 x10<sup>5<\/sup>N","1.8 x10<sup>5<\/sup>N","3.2 x10<sup>-5<\/sup>N","1.8 x10<sup>-5<\/sup>N","4.0X10<sup>-6<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A balloon containing 546cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air is heated from 0<sup>o<\/sup>C to 10<sup>o<\/sup>C. If the pressure is kept constant, what will be its volume at 10<sup>o<\/sup>C?","options":["526cm<sup>3<\/sup>","546cm<sup>3<\/sup>","556cm<sup><\/sup>","566cm<sup>3<\/sup>","819cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Calculate the electric potential at a distance of 20.0cm from a point charge of 0.015C placed in air of permittivity (Take 1\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub> as 9.0 x 10<sup>9<\/sup> Nm<sup>2<\/sup>C<sup>2<\/sup>)","options":["3.40x10<sup>6<\/sup>V","6.75x10<sup>5<\/sup>V","6.75x10<sup>12<\/sup>V","3.40x10<sup>5<\/sup>V","8.30 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>V"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A capacitor of capacitance 25\u03bcF is connected to an a.c. power source of frequency 200 Hz. Calculate the reactance of the capacitor","options":["0.01","0.02","50.00","100.00","200.00."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"The energy stored in a capacitor of capacitance 5\u03bcF is 40J. Calculate the voltage applied across its terminals?","options":["4000V","200V","16V","6V","4V"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Calculate the quantity charge flowing through a conductor if a current of 10A passes through the conductor for 10s.","options":["100C","20C","15C","10C","1C"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following is a wind instrument?","options":["Guitar","Organ","Violin","Piano","Harp"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A cell of e.m.f 1.5V and internal resistance 2.552 is connected in series with an ammeter resistance 0.50 and a load of resistance 7.00. Calculate the current in the circuit","options":["0.15A","0.20A","2.1OA","3.00A","6.67A"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A radioactive nuclide of mass 6.09 has a half-life of 8 days. Calculate the time during which 5.25g of the nuclide would have decayed","options":["1 day","2 days","8 days","24 days","42 days."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"A moving-coil meter with an internal resistance of 100\u03a9 has a full-scale deflection when a current of 10m2 flows through it. What value of resistance would convert it to read 10V at full- scale deflection?","options":["20","100","600","900","1000"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following are emitted from a radioactive substance without altering either the nucleon number or the proton number of the substance?","options":["Protons","Neutrons","Gamma rays","Beta particles","Alpha particles"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a product of nuclear fission?","options":["Alpha particle","Beta particle","Gamma ray","X-ray","Neutron"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"Which of the following cannot be explained by the molecular theory of matter?","options":["Conduction","Radiation","Convection","Evaporation","Expansion"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1995"},{"question":"In which of the following simple machines is the effort applied between the load and the fulcrum?","options":["Scissors","Pliers","Wheel barrow","Sugar tongs","Nutcrackers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The ice and steam points on a mercury in glass thermometer are found to be 90mm apart. What temperature is recorded in degree Celsius when the length of the mercury thread is 33.6mm above the ice point mark?","options":["33.6\u00b0C","35.0\u00b0C","37.3\u00b0C","52.7\u00b0C","62.7\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A gas occupies a certain volume at 27\u00b0C. At what temperature will its volume be three times the original  volume assuming that its pressure remains constant?","options":["81\u00b0C","162\u00b0C","354\u00b0C","627\u00b0C","900\u00b0C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"When two objects P and Q are supplied with the same quantity of heat,the temperature change in P is observed to be twice that in Q. If the masses of P and Q are the same,calculate the ratio of the specific heat capacities of P and Q","options":["1:1","1:3","1:4","1:2","4:1"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The instrument used in the measurement of atmospheric pressure is?","options":["Hydrometer","Ratemeter","Barometer","Photometer","Manometer"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A tap supplies water at 30\u00b0C while another supplies at 86\u00b0C. If a man wishes to bath with water at 44\u00b0C, calculate the ratio of mass of hot water to that of cold water required","options":["1:3","3:1","3:7","7:3","15:8"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A steam trap is a component of apparatus used in determining the specific latent heat of vaporization of steam. In the steady state, the steam trap","options":["stores the steam for future use","prevents the steam from escaping","ensures that only dry steam gets into the calorimeter","allows condensed steam to go into the calorimeter","determines the quantity of steam used"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A hygrometer is an instrument used to measure","options":["Dew point","Temperature","Relative density","Relative humidity","Vapour pressure"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A simple magnifying glass is used to view an object. At what distance from the lens must the object be placed so that an image 5 times the size of the object is produced 20cm from the lens?","options":["2cm","4cm","15cm","25cm","100cm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The inability of the eye to focus near objects is known as","options":["Long sight","Astigmatism","Presbyopia","Glaucoma","Short sight"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following are transverse waves? I. Ripples on water II. Sound waves in air III. Light waves from the sun","options":["II only","I and II only","II and III only","I and II only","I, II and III"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following has the shortest wavelength?","options":["Infrared rays","Gamma rays","Ultra violet rays","Radio waves","Visible light"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The electrical energy supplied by a Leclanche cell is obtained from the","options":["Nuclear energy","Magnetic energy","Solar energy","Chemical energy","Mechanical energy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a part of an A.C generator?","options":["Carbon brushes","Slip rings","Commutator","Field magnet","Armature"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following scientists postulated that moving particles exhibit wave properties?","options":["Niels Bohr","Ernest Rutherford","Werner Heisenberg","Louis de Broglie","Erwin Schroedinger"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A battery of e.m.f 10V an internal resistance 2\u2126 is connected to a resistance of 6\u2126. Calculate the p.d","options":["8.75V","7.50V","5V","2.50V","1.25V"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A rectangular coil can rotate in a magnetic field. The two ends of the coil are soldered respectively to the two halves of a commutator. Two carbon brushes are made to press lightly against the commutator and when these are connected in a circuit with a battery and a rheostat, the coil rotates. This is a description of","options":["a moving coil ammeter","a D.C generator","a D.C electric motor","An induction coil","An A.C generator"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A particle of charge q and mass m moving with a velocity v enters a uniform magnetic field of strength B in the direction of the field. The force on the particle is","options":["qvB","mqvB","qvB\/m","mvB\/q",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A lamp marked 100W, 250V is lit for 10 hours. If it operates normally and 1KWh of electrical energy costs 2k, what is the cost of lighting the lamp?","options":["1k","2k","5k","10k","20k"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following is a stringed instrument?","options":["Flute","Trumpet","Piano","Drum","Organ"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A transformer with 5500 turns in its primary winding is used between a 240V a.c supply and 120V kettle. Calculate the number of turns in the secondary winding","options":["11000","2750","460","550","232"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Beta particles are","options":["electrons","protons","neutrons","helium nuclei","tritium nuclei"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following substances is not an insulator?","options":["Aluminium","Glass","Plastic","Clay","Cork"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"When an atom loses or gains a charge, it becomes an","options":["ion","an electron","a neutron","a proton","a deuteron"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"In 24 days a radioactive isotope decreases in mass from 64g to 2g. What is the half life of the radioactive material","options":["0.75 days","2.58 days","4 days","4.80 days","6 days"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The nucleon number and the proton number of a neutral atom of an element are 238 and 92 respectively. What is the number of neutrons in the atom?","options":["330","238","146","119","73"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The wave function of a metal is 8.0 x \\(10^{-19}\\)J. Calculate the wavelength of its threshold frequency. (Speed of light in a vacuum = 3 x \\(10^8ms^{-1}, Planck's constant = 6.6 \\times 10^{-34}\\)Js)","options":["0.8 x \\(10^{-7}\\)m","1 x \\(10^{-7}\\)m","2.3 x  \\(10^{-7}\\)m","3.8 x  \\(10^{-7}\\)m","12.4 x  \\(10^{-7}\\)m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A cell of e.m.f. 1.5V and internal resistance of 2.5\u2126 is connected in series with an ammeter of resistance 0.5W and a resistor of resistance of 7.0\u2126. Calculate the current in the circuit.","options":["0.15A","0.20A","2.10A","3A","6.6A"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A ball is dropped from a height of 45m above the ground. Calculate the velocity of the ball just before it strikes the ground. (Neglect air resistance and take g as \\(10ms^{-2}\\)","options":["21.2\\(ms^{-1}\\)","30\\(ms^{-1}\\)","300\\(ms^{-1}\\)","450\\(ms^{-1}\\)","900\\(ms^{-1}\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A body accelerates uniformly from rest at \\(2ms^{-2}\\). Calculate the velocity after traveling 9m","options":["36\\(ms^{-1}\\)","18\\(ms^{-1}\\)","6\\(ms^{-1}\\)","4.5\\(ms^{-1}\\)","4.24\\(ms^{-1}\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"500g of water is heated so that its temperature rises from 30\u00b0C to 72\u00b0C in 7 minutes. calculate the supplied per minute. (Specific heat capacity of water is 4200J\\(kg^{-1}K^{-1}\\)","options":["9000J","12600J","21000J","25200J","88200J"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"An electric kettle rated 1500W boils away 0.3kg of a liquid at its boiling point every 300s. Calculate the specific latent heat of the vaporisation of the liquid","options":["1.5 x \\(10^6Jkg^-1\\)","1.35 x \\(10^6Jkg^-1\\)","1.5 x \\(10^5Jkg^-1\\)","4.5 x \\(10^2Jkg^-1\\)","3 x \\(10^2Jkg^-1\\)"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"\\(500cm^{-3}\\) of a gas is collected at 0\u00b0C and at a pressure of 72cm of mercury. What is the volume of the the gas at the same temperature and at a pressure of 76cm of the same mercury?","options":["\\(\\frac{76\\times500}{72}cm^3\\)","\\(\\frac{72\\times500}{76}cm^3\\)","\\(\\frac{72\\times76}{500}cm^3\\)","\\(\\frac{76}{72\\times500}cm^3\\)","\\(\\frac{72}{76\\times500}cm^3\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The pressure of air in a tire is \\(22.5Nm^{-2}\\) at 27\u00b0C. If the air in the tyre heats up to 47\u00b0C, calculate the new pressure of the air, assuming that no air leaks out and that the change in volume of the air can be neglected.","options":["\\(21.10Nm^{-2}\\)","\\(24Nm^{-2}\\)","\\(39.07Nm^{-2}\\)","\\(45Nm^{-2}\\)","\\(97.25Nm^{-2}\\)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Calculate the time taken to heat 2kg of water from 50\u00b0C to 100\u00b0C in an electric kettle taking 5A, from a 210V supply. (Specific heat capacity of water = 4200\\(kg^{-1}K{-1}\\)","options":["2.5 minutes","5.7 minutes","6.7 minutes","7.5 minutes","9.5 minutes"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"A light wave travels from air into a medium of refractive index 1.54. If the wavelength of the light in air is \\(5.9\\times10^{-7}\\)m, calculate its wavelength in the medium","options":["\\(2.5\\times10^{-7}\\)m","\\(3.8\\times10^{-7}\\)m","\\(4.6\\times10^{-7}\\)m","\\(5.2\\times10^{-7}\\)m","\\(6.1\\times10^{-7}\\)m"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The density of a body is \\(5\\times10^3kgm{^-3}\\) and it weighs 1N in air. Calculate the apparent weight of the body when totally immersed in water. (Density of water =\\(10^3kgm{-3}, g= 10ms^{-2}","options":["0.02N","0.08N","0.20N","0.80N","1N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"The density of water is 1g\\(cm^3\\) while that of  ice is 0.9\\(cm^3\\), calculate the volume change when 90g of ice is completely melted","options":["0\\(cm^3\\)","9\\(cm^3\\)","10\\(cm^3\\)","90\\(cm^3\\)","100\\(cm^3\\)"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1994"},{"question":"Which of the following is not an example of a force?","options":["Tension","Weight","Friction","Mass","Thrust"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A body moves along a circular path with uniform angular speed of 0.6 rad s<sup>-1<\/sup> and at a constant speed of 3.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. Calculate the acceleration of the body towards the centre of the circle.","options":["25.0ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","5.4 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","5.0ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","1.8 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","0.2ms<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following is a derived unit?","options":["Ampere","Kilogramme","Second","Ohm","Kelvin"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A body timed 20 oscillations of a certain pendulum three times and obtained 44.3s, 45.5s and 45.7s respectively. Calculate the mean period of oscillation of the pendulum","options":["0.13s","2.22s","2.26s","44.30s","45.17s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A body of mass M1 moving with a velocity U collides with a stationary body of mass M2 and both move with a common velocity V lf linear momentum is conserved, which of the following expressions correctly represents V?","options":["<div class=\"eq-c\"><div class=\"fraction\"><span class=\"fr_num\">M<sub>1<\/sub> U<\/span><span class=\"bar\">\/<\/span><span class=\"fr_den\">M<sub>1<\/sub> + M<sub>2<\/sub><\/div><\/div>","<div class=\"eq-c\"><div class=\"fraction\"><span class=\"fr_num\">M<sub>2<\/sub> U<\/span><span class=\"bar\">\/<\/span><span class=\"fr_den\">M<sub>1<\/sub> + M<sub>2<\/sub><\/div><\/div>","<div class=\"eq-c\"><div class=\"fraction\"><span class=\"fr_num\">M<sub>1<\/sub> + M<sub>2<\/sub><\/span><span class=\"bar\">\/<\/span><span class=\"fr_den\">M<sub>1<\/sub> U<\/div><\/div>","<div class=\"eq-c\"><div class=\"fraction\"><span class=\"fr_num\">M<sub>1<\/sub> - M<sub>2<\/sub><\/span><span class=\"bar\">\/<\/span><span class=\"fr_den\">M<sub>1<\/sub> U<\/div><\/div>","<div class=\"eq-c\"><div class=\"fraction\"><span class=\"fr_num\">M<sub>1<\/sub> U<\/span><span class=\"bar\">\/<\/span><span class=\"fr_den\">M<sub>1<\/sub> - M<sub>2<\/sub><\/div><\/div>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A particle starts from rest and moves with a constant acceleration of 0.5 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>? Calculate the time taken by the particle to cover a distance of 25m.","options":["25s","7.1s","10.0s","50.0s","100.0s."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A block of material of volume 2 X 1O<sup>-5<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup> and density 2.5 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup> kgm<sup>-3<\/sup> is suspended from a spring balance with half volume of the block immersed in water. What is the reading of the spring balance? (Density of water =1.0x10<sup>3<\/sup> kg m<sup>-3<\/sup> g = 10 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>).","options":["0.10N","0.25N","0.30N","0.40N","0.50N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"An object is projected with a velocity of 100 ms<sup>-1<\/sup> from the ground level at an angle 0 to the vertical. If the total time of flight of the projectile is 10 s, calculate \u03b8. (g = 10 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>).","options":["0<sup>o<\/sup>","30<sup>o<\/sup>","45<sup>o<\/sup>","60<sup>o<\/sup>","90<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"How far will a body move in 4 seconds if uniformly accelerated from rest at the rate of 2 ms<sup>-2<\/sup>?","options":["32m","24m","16m","1.2m","5m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"If the temperature of water is gradually increased from 0<sup>o<\/sup> to 4<sup>o<\/sup>C, the density of the water within this range","options":["increases for a while and then decreases","decreases for a while and then increases","increases gradually","decreases gradually","remains the same"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The expansion of solids can be considered a disadvantage in the","options":["fire alarm system","thermostat","riveting of steel plates","balance wheel of a watch","fitting of wheels on rims."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A solid metal cube of side 10 cm is heated from<br>\r\n10<sup>o<\/sup>C to 60<sup>o<\/sup>C. lf the linear expansivity of the metal is 1.2 x 10<sup>5<\/sup>K<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the increase in its volume.","options":["0.6cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.2 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","1.8 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","3.6 cm<sup>3<\/sup>","6.0cm<sup>3<\/sup>."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A gas has a volume of 546 cm<sup>3<\/sup> at O<sup>o<\/sup>C. What is the volume of the gas at- 100<sup>o<\/sup>C if its pressure remains constant?","options":["346cm<sup>3<\/sup>","446cm<sup>3<\/sup>","546cm<sup>3<\/sup>","646cm<sup>3<\/sup>","746 cm<sup>3<\/sup>."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following are correct of plane- polarized light? I. Plane polarization of light is the formation of hydrogen bubbles on the particles of light. II. Plane polarization of light is the splitting of light into its spectral components III. Plane-polarized light vibrates in one plane only. IV. Polarization is characteristic of transverse waves.","options":["I and II only","I and IV only","II and III only","III and IV only","I and III only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Longitudinal waves cannot be","options":["diffracted","retracted","polarized","reflected","superposed"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"An image which cannot be formed on a screen is said to be","options":["inverted","real","virtual","erect","blurred"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The images formed by a diverging lens are always","options":["diminished, virtual and inverted","diminished inverted and real","diminished, virtual and erect","magnified, virtual and erect","magnified, real and inverted."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"In the normal use of a simple microscope, a person sees an","options":["inverted, virtual and magnified image","erect, virtual and magnified image","erect, real and magnified image","inverted, real and magnified image","inverted and real image the same size as the object."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"An object is placed between two mirrors which are inclined at an angle of 120\u00b0 and facing each other. Determine the number of images observed in the two mirrors","options":["1","2","3","4","5"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"In a ripple tank experiment, a vibrating plate is used to generate ripples in the water. If the distance between two successive troughs is 3.5 cm and the wave travels a distance of 31.5 cm in 1.5 s, calculate the frequency of the vibrator","options":["3.0Hz","6.0Hz","12.0Hz","27.0Hz","73.5Hz"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A man stands in front of a tall wall and produces a sound. If he receives the echo of the sound two seconds later, calculate his distance from the wall. (The speed of sound in air is 330ms<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["600m","400m","330m","328m","165m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following is correct about light and sound waves?","options":["Both of them are associated with energy transfer","Both of them need material media for propagation","they are both longitudinal waves","their velocities in air are equal","Both of them can be polarized"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The quality of a note produced by a vibrating string is determined by the","options":["pitch of the note","tension of the string","material of the string","presence of overtones","thickness of the string"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following is a percussion instrument?","options":["Flute","Organ","Bell","Piano","Sonometer"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A short chain is usually attached to the back of a petrol tanker and trailing behind it so that the","options":["petrol tanker is balanced on the road","heat generated by friction in the engine can be conducted to the earth","charges generated by friction in the tanker are conducted to the earth","tanker can move slowly as the chain touches the road surface","chain can produce sound in resonance with the noise from the tanker\u2018s engine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following indicates the correct sequence of steps taken in charging a gold-leaf electroscope by induction? l. Removing the ebonite rod ll. Bringing a negatively charged ebonite rod close to the cap III. Earthing the cap IV. Disconnecting the earthing","options":["III, II, I and IV","II, I, III and IV","III, IV II and I","II, III, IV and I","III, IV, I and II."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following instruments can be used to compare the relative magnitude of similar charges on two given bodies?","options":["Electrophorus","Ebonite rod","Proof plane","Gold-leaf electroscope","Capacitor"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The unit of inductance is","options":["farad","henry","hertz","weber","tesla"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A household refrigerator consumes electrical energy at the rate of 200 W. lf electricity costs 5 k per kWh, calculate the cost of operating the appliance for 30 days.","options":["N7.20","N12.00","N30.00","N33.33","N72.00"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Calculate the escape velocity of a satellite launched from the earth\u2019s surface (Take g as 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup> and the radius of the earth as 6.4 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>m)","options":["8.00 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.13 x10<sup>4<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","3.58x10<sup>2<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.59 x10<sup>-2<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","3.95x10<sup>-2<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"What is the gravitational potential due to a point mass m at a distance from it? (G = gravitational constant)","options":["-Gm<sup>2<\/sup>\/r<sup>2<\/sup>","-Gm<sup>2<\/sup>\/r","\u2013Gm\/Gr<sup>2<\/sup>","\u2013Gm\/r","\u2013Gm\/2"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"In a series R - C circuit, the resistance of the resistor is 4 \u03a9 and capacitive reactance is 3 \u03a9. Calculate the impedance of the circuit","options":["1\u03a9","4\u03a9","5\u03a9","7\u03a9","12\u03a9"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The vector diagram shown below represents the resistance R, the capacitive reactance X<sub>c<\/sub>, the inductive reactance X<sub>c<\/sub> and the impedance, Z in an R-L-C circuit. The current in the circuit will be maximum when","options":["X<sub>c<\/sub> = X<sub>c<\/sub>","X<sub>L<\/sub> = X<sub>L<\/sub>","R = X<sub>L<\/sub>","R =X",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"In a purely resistive a.c. circuit, the current I = I<sub>o<\/sub> sin wt and voltage, V = V<sub>o<\/sub> sin wt. Calculate the instantaneous power dissipated in the circuit in time t.","options":["I<sub>o<\/sub> V<sub>o<\/sub>","2I<sub>o<\/sub> V<sub>o<\/sub>sin wt","(I<sub>o<\/sub> V<sub>o<\/sub>)\/2","I<sub>o<\/sub> V<sub>o<\/sub> sin<sup>2<\/sup>wt","I<sup>2<\/sup><sub>o<\/sub> V<sup>2<\/sup><sub>o<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A point charge of 1.0 x 10<sup>-7<\/sup> C experiences force of 0.01 N in a uniform electric field. Calculate the magnitude of the strength of the field","options":["10<sup>6<\/sup> Vm<sup>-1<\/sup>","10<sup>5<\/sup> Vm<sup>-1<\/sup>","10<sup>-5<\/sup> Vm<sup>-1<\/sup>","10<sup>2<\/sup> Vm<sup>-1<\/sup>","10<sup>9<\/sup> Vm<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The potential difference between two points A and B situated at a distance d apart is V. Which of the following expresses the magnitude of the electric field intensity between the two points assuming the field is uniform?","options":["Vd","dV<sup>-1<\/sup>","Vd<sup>-1<\/sup>","V<sup>2<\/sup>d","d<sup>2<\/sup>V"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following have the greatest penetrating power?","options":["Beta rays","Alpha rays","Gamma rays","Electrons","Neutrons"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A particle of charge 5C moves perpendicularly to a magnetic Held of magnitude C.01 T. If the velocity of the charge is 1.5ms'2, calculate the magnitude of the force exerted on the particle","options":["0.050 N","0.075N","0.0300N","3.300N","0.000N"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The function of the magnanese (IV) oxide in a leclanche cell is to","options":["decrease the e.m.f. of the cell","prevent local action in the cell","prevent polarization in the cell","increase the density of the electrolyte","increase the resistance of the cell."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Electrical resistance is the property of an electrical conductor that causes electrical energy to be converted into","options":["mechanical energy","solar energy","heat energy","magnetic energy","chemical energy."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a conductor of electricity?","options":["Human body","Glass","Silver","Earth","Copper"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"When a potential difference, V is applied across the ends of a resistor of resistance, R a Current, l passes through the resistor. The heat generated in the resistor in time, t is given by the expression","options":["V<sup>2<\/sup>lt","I<sup>2<\/sup>t\/R","l<sup>2<\/sup>Rt","lR<sup>2<\/sup>tR","V<sup>2<\/sup>Rt"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Electric motor primarily converts","options":["electrical energy into chemical energy","electrical energy into heat energy","kinetic energy into potential energy","electrical energy into mechanical energy","mechanical energy into light energy"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"What amount of current would pass through a 10 \u03a9 coil if it takes 21s for the coil to just melt a lump of ice of mass 10g at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C if there are no heat losses? (Latent heat of fusion of ice = 336 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>).","options":["16.00A","4.00 A","0.50A","0.25A","0.06 A"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"How long does it take a 750 W heater operating at full rating to raise the temperature of 1 kg of water from 40<sup>o<\/sup>C to 70<sup>o<\/sup>C? (Take the specific heat capacity of water as 4200 J kg<sup>-1<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup> and neglect heat losses).","options":["84s","112s","168s","280s","616s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"<table><tr><th>24 Na \u2192 <\/th><th>24 mg<sup>4<\/sup> + X + energy <\/th><\/tr><tr><th>11 &nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp<\/th><th>2 &nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp&nbsp<\/th><\/tr><\/table><br>\r\nThe equation above represents a nuclear decay of sodium isotope. What is X?","options":["Alpha particle","Beta particle","Gamma ray","X-ray","Neutron"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"lf Einstein\u2019s photoelectric equation is represented by hf - W = \u03a6 where h is Planck\u2019s constant, f the frequency of incident radiation and W the work function of the material, what does the symbol \u03a6 up stand for?","options":["Energy of the photons","Maximum Kinetic energy of the ejected electrons","Threshold frequency of the photons","Stopping potential of the electrons","Velocity of the electrons"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"The phenomenon of radioactivity was first discovered by","options":["Marie Curve","Sir J.J Thomson","Henn Becquerel","Niels Bohr","Enrico Fermi"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"A radioactive substance has a half-life of 20 hours. What traction of the original radioactive nuclide will remain after 80 hours?","options":["1\/32","1\/16","1\/8","\u00bc","1\/2"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"According to the kinetic theory of gases the collision<br>\r\nof the molecules of a gas with the wall of the container<br>\r\nis mainly responsible for the l. temperature of the<br>\r\ngas ll. viscosity of the gas Ill. pressure of the gas<br>\r\nWhich of the statements above is\/are correct?","options":["I only","II only","III only","II and III only","I, II and III."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Eight or - particles and size B - particles are emitted from an atom of <sub>92<\/sub><sup>238<\/sup>U before it achieves stability. What is the nucleon number of the final product in the chain reaction?","options":["206","234","238","240","252"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"When an atom is in the ground state, it is said to be","options":["grounded","excited","stable","ionized","radiating"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following are emitted from a radioactive substance without altering either the nucleon number or the proton number of the substance?","options":["Gamma rays","Alpha particles","Beta particles","Protons","Neutrons"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1993"},{"question":"Which of the following  is a scalar quantity?","options":["Momentum","Acceleration","Displacement","Distance","Force"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"What change in velocity would be produced on a body of mass 4kg if a constant force of 16 N acts on it for2 s?","options":["0.5 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","8.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","32.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","128.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about solid friction is\/are correct? I. Friction depends on the nature of the surfaces in contact II. Friction depends on the area of contact III. Friction always acts in the direction of motion.","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and II only","I,II and III"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following has the same unit as the moment of a force?","options":["Force","Power","Work","Momentum","Impulse"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Solid weighs 0.040 N in air and 0.024 N when fully immersed in a liquid of density 800 kg m<sup>-3<\/sup>. What is the volume of the solid? (g = 1Oms<sup>2<\/sup>)","options":["2.0 x 10<sup>-6<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","2.5x10<sup>-6<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","3.0x10<sup>-6<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","2.0x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>","3.0 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>m<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following will reduce the frequency of oscillation of a simple pendulum?","options":["Increasing the mass of the bob","Decreasing the mass of the bob","Increasing the length of the string","Decreasing the length of the string","Increasing the amplitude of oscillation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A force of 20 N applied parallel to the surface of a horizontal table, is just sufficient to make a block of mass 4kg move on the table. Calculate the coefficient of friction between the block and the table. (g = 10ms<sup>2<\/sup>)","options":["0.05","0.20","0.50","0.80","2.00"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A barometer can be used in determining the I. height of a mountain II. depth of a mine III. dew point. Which of the following is\/are correct?","options":["I, II and III","II and III only","I and III only","I and II only","III only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A body of mass 5kg falls from a height of 10m above the ground. What is the kinetic energy of the body just before it strikes the ground? (Neglect energy losses and take gas 10ms<sup>2<\/sup>)","options":["5J","25J","250J","500J","625J"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Steel bars, each of length 3.0 m at 28\u00b0C, are to be used for constructing a rail line. If the linear expansivity of steel is 1.0 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>\u00b0C, what is the safety gap that must be left between successive bars if the highest temperature expected is 40<sup>o<\/sup>C?","options":["1.2 x 10<sup>-1<\/sup>cm","8.4 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>cm","7.2 x10<sup>-2<\/sup>cm","3.6 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>cm","1.8 x 10<sup>-2<\/sup>cm"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is\/are correct? I. Pure water freezes at 0<sup>o<\/sup>C under normal pressure ll. Water has its highest density at 4<sup>o<\/sup>C. III. The volume at 4<sup>o<\/sup>C,","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","I and III only","II and III only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A given mass of gas at a temperature of 30\u00b0C is trapped in a tube of volume V. Calculate the temperature of the gas when the volume is reduced to two-third of its original value by applying a pressure twice the original value.","options":["71<sup>o<\/sup>C","40<sup>o<\/sup>C","131<sup>o<\/sup>C","313<sup>o<\/sup>C","404<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following colours of surfaces will radiate heat energy best?","options":["Red","White","Black","Yellow","Blue"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A gas which obeys Charles\u2019 law exactly has a volume of 283cm<sup>3<\/sup> at 10<sup>o<\/sup>C. What is its volume at 30<sup>o<\/sup>C?","options":["142cm<sup>3<\/sup>","293cm<sup>3<\/sup>","303cm<sup>3<\/sup>","566cm<sup>3<\/sup>","849cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following best explains why a person suffers a more severe burn when his skin is exposed to steam than when boiling water pours on his skin?","options":["Steam is at a higher temperature than boiling water","Steam possesses greater heat energy per unit mass than boiling water","Steam spreads more easily over a wider area of the skin man boiling water","Steam penetrates more deeply into the skin than boiling water","the specific latent heat of vaporization is released in changing from boiling water to steam"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A metal of mass 1.5 kg was heated from 27<sup>o<\/sup>C to 47<sup>o<\/sup>C in 4 minutes by a boiling ring of 75 W rating. Calculate the specific heat capacity of the metal, (Neglect heat losses to the surrounding)","options":["2.5 X10<sup>3<\/sup>J kg<sup>-10<\/sup>C<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.0 X10<sup>2<\/sup>J kg<sup>-10<\/sup>C<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.5 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>J kg<sup>-10<\/sup>C<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.4 X10<sup>2<\/sup>J kg<sup>-10<\/sup>C<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.0 x 10<sup>2<\/sup>J kg<sup>-10<\/sup>C<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Images formed by a convex mirror are always","options":["inverted, real and diminished","inverted, virtual and diminished","erect, virtual and diminished","erect, real and magnified","erect, virtual and magnified"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct for a light ray passing through a rectangular glass block which is surrounded by air? It","options":["suffers a displacement at the point of emergence","emerges parallel to the incident ray","is partly reflected at the point of incidence","is deviated at the point of emergence","is reflected in the block"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The image of a pin formed by a diverging lens of focal length 10cm is 5cm from the lens. Calculate the distance of the pin from the lens","options":["-3.3cm","3.3cm","10.0cm","15.0cm","20.0cm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A real image of an object fom1ed by a converging lens of focal length 15cm is three times the size of the object. What is the distance of the object from the lens?","options":["30cm","25cm","20cm","15cm","10cm"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"When an astronomical telescope is in normal adjustment, the focal length of the objective lens is 50cm and that of the eyepiece is 2.5om. What is the distance between the lenses?","options":["20.0cm","47.5cm","50.0cm","52.5cm","125.0cm."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following is used for controlling the amount of light entering the eye?","options":["Cornea","Pupil","Iris","Optic nerve","Ciliary muscle"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The angle of deviation of light of various colours passing through a glass prism decreases in the order of","options":["blue orange and red","red, blue and orange","blue, red and orange","red, orange and blue","orange, blue and red"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The change of the direction of a wavefront as a result of a change in the velocity of the wave in another medium is called","options":["refraction","reflection","diffraction","polarization",""],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following radiations have the highest frequency?","options":["Radio waves","Light waves","X-rays","infra-red rays","Ultraviolet rays"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"How far from a cliff should a boy stand in order to hear the echo of his clap 0.9s later? (Speed of sound in air = 330 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["36.67m","74.25m","148.50m","297.00","366.67m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following waves are longitudinal waves? l. Ripples on the surface of water II. Waves produced by a tuning fork vibrating in air III. Light waves<br>\r\nIV. Waves produced by a flute","options":["I and II only","I and III only","II and III only","II and IV only","III and IV only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not true?","options":["Musical notes consist of the combination of sounds of regular frequency","The combination of overtones produced by an instrument determines the quality of the sound","the loudness of sound is determined by its frequency","the pitch of a note depends on the frequency of vibration of the source","Noise can be produced by a combination of sounds of irregular frequency"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A pipe closed at one end is 1.0m long. The air in the pipe is set into vibration and a fundamental note of frequency 85Hz is produced. Calculate the velocity of sound in the air. (Neglect end correction).","options":["340.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","33Oms<sup>-1<\/sup>","170ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","85.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","42.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A negatively charged rod is brought near the cap of a gold-leaf electroscope. The cap is earthed momentarily while the rod is near to it. The rod is then removed. Which of the following is correct?","options":["The cap will be positively charged and the negatively charged leaves will diverge","The cap will be negatively charged and the positively charged leaves will diverge","The cap and the leaves will be positively charged","The cap and the leaves will be negatively charged.","The leaves will not diverge because the cap has been earthed."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a consequence of hydrogen bubbles covering the copper plate of a primary cell?","options":["Polarization","Local action","Formation of hydrogen electrode","Increase in the resistance of the cell","Generation of less current by the cell"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Calculate the length of a constantan wire of cross- sectional area 4 \u03c0 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>m<sup>2<\/sup> and resistivity 1.1 x 10<sup>-6<\/sup> \u03a9 m required to construct a standard resistor of resistance 21 \u03a9. [Take \u03c0 = 22\/7]","options":["0.42m","2.40 m","6.25 m","183.75 m","590.00 m"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"In a domestic circuit, electrical appliances and lamps are arranged in parallel across the mains so as to enable the","options":["same current to flow through the electrical appliances and the lamps","maximum energy to be consumed at least cost","same fuse to be used for the electrical appliances and the lamps","voltage across the appliances not to be affected when the lamps are switched on and off","heat losses to be minimized"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Calculate the time in which 4.8 kJ of energy would be expended when an electric heater of resistance 1.8 x 10<sup>3<\/sup>\u03a9 is used on a 240 V mains supply. (Neglect heat losses to the surrounding).","options":["150.0s","90.0s","36.0s","20.0s","2.7s."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Lenz\u2019s law of electromagnetic induction states that","options":["electromotive force is induced in a circuit whenever there is a change in the magnetic flux linked with the circuit","the induced current in a conductor is in such a direction as to oppose the change producing it","the induced e.m.f. in a circuit is proportional to the rate of change of number of lines of force linking the circuit","a force is exerted on a current carrying conductor in a magnetic field","the induced e.m.f. is proportional to the current producing the magnetic flux."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct?","options":["A magnetic Held is a region where a magnetic force can be detected.","Magnetic fields are scalar quantities.","The magnitude of the magnetic force experienced by a moving charge depends on the speed on the charge.","the angle between the direction of the earth\u2019s magnetic held and the horizontal is called the angle of dip.","Iron filings can be used to trace out the magnetic field around a bar magnet."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Calculate the energy stored in 20\u03bcF capacitor if the potential difference between the plates is 40 V.","options":["3.2 x10<sup>-2<\/sup>J","1.6x10<sup>2<\/sup>J","8.0x10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","4.0x10<sup>-4<\/sup>J","2.0x10<sup>-4<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"What is the electric potential at a point distance r from a proton of charge q placed in a medium of permittivity \u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>?","options":["q<sup>2<\/sup>\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>r<sup>2<\/sup>","q\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>r<sup>2<\/sup>","q<sup>2<\/sup>\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>r","qr\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>","4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>q<sup>2<\/sup>r"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following gives rise to the line spectra obtained from atoms?","options":["Kinetic energy of a moving atom","Potential energy of an electron inside an atom","Change of an electron from a higher to a lower energy level in the atom","Disturbed proton in the nucleus","Excitation of an electron in the atom"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"When the nucleus of a uranium atom is split into two fragments of nearly equal mass the sum of the masses of the fragments is less than the mass of the original nucleus. This difference is a measure of the","options":["experimental error in calculating the separate masses","change of momentum of each fragment","potential energy lost","nuclear energy released","kinetic energy lost"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"A sheet of paper is placed in the path of a beam of radiations from a radioactive source. Which of the following radiations will pass through the paper?I. Alpha rays II. Beta rays III. Gamma rays","options":["I only","II only","III only","II and III only","I, II and III"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"The process by which a metal, heated to high temperature, gives off electrons from its surface is known as","options":["photoelectric emission","thermionic emission","radioactive emission","Held emission","secondary emission"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"An electric string of length l is elastically stretched through a length e by a force F. The area of cross- section of the string is A and its Young\u2019s modulus is E. Which of the following expressions is correct?","options":["F = EA\/eI","F = EAI\/e","F = EAe\/l","F = EAe",""],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1992"},{"question":"Which of the following is a fundamental quantity?","options":["speed","density","lenght","impulse","energy"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A body moves with a constant speed but has an acceleration. this process if it","options":["moves in a straight line","moves in a circle","is oscillating","is in equilibrum","has a varrying acceleration"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A ball is projected horizontally from the top of a hill with a velocity of 20m<sup>-1<\/sup>. If it reaches the ground 4 seconds later, what is the height of the hill? (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["20m","40m","80m","160m","200m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A body moving with uniform acceleration has two points(5, 15) and (20, 60) on the velocity-times graph of its motion. Calculate","options":["0.25ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","3.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","4.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","9.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>","16.00ms<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"An orange fruit drops to the ground from the top of a tree 45m tall. How long does it takes to reach the ground? (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["3.0s","4.5s","6.0s","7.5s","9.0s"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The product PV where P is pressure and V is volume has the same unit as","options":["power","work","acceleration","impulse","force"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A boatman facing north wants to cross a flowing river to a point directly opposite its position at the other bank. If the river is flowing eastwards, in what direction should he row his boat?","options":["west","east","north-west","north-east","south-west"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A wire, 20m long is heated from a temperature of 5<sup>o<\/sup>C to 55<sup>o<\/sup>C. If the change in length is 0.020m, calculate the linear expansivity of the wire","options":["1.0 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup>k<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0  x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>k<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0  x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>k<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.0  x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>k<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0  x 10<sup>-6<\/sup>k<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A water fall is 420m high. Calculate the difference in temperature of the water between the top and bottom of the water fall. Neglect heat loses(g = 10.0m<sup>-2<\/sup> specific heat capacity of water = 4.20 x 10<sup>-3<\/sup> JKg<sup>-1<\/sup> K<sup>-1<\/sup>)","options":["0.1<sup>o<\/sup>C","1.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","42<sup>o<\/sup>C","100<sup>o<\/sup>C","4.20<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A fixed mass of gas of volume 600cm<sup>3<\/sup> at a temperature of 27<sup>o<\/sup>C is cooled at constant pressure to a temperature of 0<sup>o<\/sup>C. What is the change in volume?","options":["54cm<sup>2<\/sup>","273cm<sup>2<\/sup>","300cm<sup>2<\/sup>","546cm<sup>2<\/sup>","600cm<sup>2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The boiling point of a liquid depends on the following except the","options":["nature of the liquid","external pressure","volume of the liquid","impurities present in the liquid","degree of it's molecular cohesive force"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A team trap is a component of the apparatus used in determining the specific latent heat of vaporisation of steam. In the steady steady state, the steam trap","options":["stores the steam for future use","prevents the steam from escaping","ensures that only dry steam gets into the calorimeter","allows condensed steam to go into the calorimeter","determine the quantity of steam used"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"a tap supplies water at 26<sup>o<\/sup>C while another supplies water at 82<sup>o<\/sup>C. If a man wishes to bathe with water at 40<sup>o<\/sup>C the ratio of hot mass of hot water to that of cold water required is","options":["1:3","3:1","3:7","7:3","15:8"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Melting ice cools an orange drink far better than the same mass of ice-cold water because","options":["melting ice is lower temperature than ice-cold water","water has a higher specific heat than ice","ice floats and cools the air above the drink","ice absorbs latent heat during melting","ice makes better thermal contact than water"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The saturation vapour of a liquid depends on its","options":["volume","temperature","mass","density","pressure"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A ray of light is incident at an angle of 30<sup>o<\/sup> on a glass prism of refractive index 1.5. Calculate the angle through which the ray is minimally deviated in the prism. (The medium surrounding the prism is air)","options":["10.5<sup>o<\/sup>","19.5<sup>o<\/sup>","21.1<sup>o<\/sup>","38.9<sup>o<\/sup>","40.5<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following are true of plane-polarised right?  i. Plane polarisation of light is the formation of hydrogen bubbles on the particle of light.  ii. Plane components.  iii. A plane polarised light vibrates in one plane.  iv. Polarisation of light is characteristic of transverse vibration","options":["i and ii only","i and iv only","ii and iii only","i and ii only",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"At which of the following distances from the lens should a slide be placed on a slide projector if f is the focal length of the projector length?","options":["less than f","greater than f but less than 3f","equal to f","equal to 2f","greater than 2f"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"what part of the camera corresponds to the iris of the eye?","options":["shutter","film","lens","diaphram","focusing ring"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a mechanical wave?","options":["wave propagatd in stretched string","wave in closed pipe","radio waves","water waves","sound waves"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following remains unchanged as light travels from one medium to the other?  i. speed.  ii. wavelength.  iii. frequency.","options":["i only","ii only","iii only","i and ii only","i and ii only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"What type of motion does  the skin of a talking drum perform when its being struck with the drum stick?","options":["random","rational","vibratory","translational","circular"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The sound from a bell in an enclosed jar gradually faints away while the jar is being evacuated. Which of the following explains this observation?","options":["the pressue is reduced","the sound waves are pumped out","the waves are absorbed in the inner walls","There is no more material medium","the air is disturbed"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A man standing 300m away from the wall sounds a whistle. The echo from the wall reaches him 1.8sec. later, calculate the velocity of sound in air","options":["540.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","333.3ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","270.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","166.7ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","83.3ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"In which of the following is a stationary wave produced?  i. A vibrating turning fork held near the end of a resonance tube closed at one end.  ii. A string tightly stretched between two points and plucked at its middle.  iii. The tuning fork vibrating in air","options":["i only","ii only","i and ii only","ii and iii only","i, ii and iii"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A particle of charge q and mass m moving with a velocity v enters a uniform magnetic field b in the direction of the field. The force on the particle is","options":["qvB","mqvB\/m","mvB\/q","O",""],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Two objects of masses 80kg and 50kg are separated by a distance of 0.2m. If the gravitational constant is 6.6 x 10<sup>-11<\/sup>Nm<sup2<\/sup> kg, calculate the gravitational attraction between them.","options":["4.9 x 10<sup>-9<\/sup>N","1.3 x 10<sup>-6<\/sup>N","6.6 x 10<sup>-8<\/sup>N","6.6 x 10<sup>-6<\/sup>N","2.6 x 10<sup>-9<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A 90W immersion heater is used to supply energy for 5 minutes. The energy supplied is used to completely melt 160g of a solid at its melting point. Calculate the specific latent heat of the solid.","options":["2.81jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.25Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","8.89Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","168.75Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","5333.33Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"A house is supplied with a 240V a.c mains. To operate a door bell rated at 8v, a transformer is used if the number of turns in the primary coil of the transformer is 900. calculate the number of turns in the secondary coil of the transformer","options":["30","240","248","450","1248"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The unit of stress is","options":["Nm","N","Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","Nm<sup>2<\/sup>","Nm<sup>1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following statements above viscosity are correct? when a ball falls through a viscous liquid  i. viscosity opposes the gravitational force on the ball.  ii. viscosity opposes the upthrust on the ball.  iii. viscosity is in the same direction as the upthrust on the ball.  iv. as the ball falls faster the more viscous the liquid is","options":["i and iii only","i and ii only","ii and iv only","iii and iv only","i, ii and iv only"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct? Isotopes of an element have","options":["the same number of electric charges on the nucleus","the same chemical properties","different nucleon numbers","different proton numbers","different atomic masses"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"An electron charge 1.6 x 10<sup>-19<\/sup>C is accelerated in vacuum from rest at zero volt towards a plate at 40k V. Calculate the kinetic energy of the electron","options":["4.0 x 10<sup>-26<\/sup>J","4.0 x 10<sup>-21<\/sup>J","6.4 x 10<sup>-20<\/sup>J","3.2 x 10<sup>-15<\/sup>J","2.5 x 10<sup>-20<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The half-life  of a radioactive substance is 2 seconds. Calculate the decay constant","options":["0.035s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.151s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.347s<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.576s<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.386s<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"The work function of a metal is 4.65ev and the metal is illuminated with a radiation of 6.86ev. What is the kinetic energy of the electrons ejected from the surface of the metal?","options":["1.48ev","2.21ev","4.42ev","5.75ev","11.51ev"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following has the highest surface tension?","options":["cold water","soapy water","warm water","oily water","salty water"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1991"},{"question":"Which of the following instruments is suitable for making the most accurate measurement of the internal diameter of a test tube?","options":["metre rule","A pair of callipers","A micrometer screw gauge","A tape rule","A set square"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A particle of mass 2.5 x 10<sup>-6<\/sup>kg revolving around the earth has a radial acceleration of 4 X 10<sup>7<\/sup> ms<sup>-2<\/sup>. What is the centripetal force of the particles?","options":["6.25 x 10<sup>-14<\/sup>N","1.60 x10<sup>-13<\/sup>N","5.00 x 10N","1.00x10<sup>2<\/sup>N","2.00x1O<sup>2<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following are contact forces? I. Force of tension II. Force of fiction, III. Magnetic force III Force of reaction.","options":["I,II and III only","I,  II and IV only","I, III and IV only","II, III and IV only","l and IV only."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A plane inclined at an angle at 30<sup>o<\/sup> to the horizontal has an efficiency of 50%. The force parallel to the plane required to push a load of 120 N uniformly up the plane is","options":["40\u221a3N","60N","120N","200N","240N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A girl whose mass is 55kg stands on a spring - weighing machine inside a lift. When the lift starts to ascend, its acceleration is 2ms1. What will be the reading on the machine? (Take g = ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["66 kg","55 kg","44 kg","22 kg","11 kg"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A simple pendulum makes 50 oscillations in one minute. What is its period of oscillation?","options":["0.02s","0.20s","0.83s","1.20s","50.00s"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"An object weighs 10.0 N in air and 7.0 N in water. What is its weight when immersed in a liquid of relative density 1.5?","options":["4.50N","4.67N","5.50N","6.67N","8.50N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The absolute zero temperature is defined as the temperature at which","options":["thermal motion ceases","the temperature of a gas is 273<sup>o<\/sup>C","ice melts","the volume of a real gas is maximum","the pressure of a real gas is maximum"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Dry hydrogen is trapped by pellet of mercury in a uniform capillary tube closed at one end. If the length of the column of hydrogen at 27\u00b0C is 1.0m, at what temperature will the length be 1.20m?","options":["22.5<sup>o<\/sup>C","32.4<sup>o<\/sup>C","77.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","87.0<sup>o<\/sup>C","360.0<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Two solids P and Q of equal mass are heated to the same temperature and dropped simultaneously into two identical containers X and Y containing equal volumes of water at room temperature. The temperature of X will rise higher than that of Y only if the","options":["volume of P is greater than that of Q","specific heat capacity of P is higher than that of Q","density of P is greater than that of Q","density of P is lower than that of Q","specitic heat capacity of P is lower than that of Q."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"lf the temperature of a small quantity of water in a closed container is gradually increased from 0<sup>o<\/sup> to 40<sup>o<\/sup>C then the density of the water within this range","options":["increases for a while and then decreases","decreases for a while and then increases","increases gradually","decreases gradually","remains the same"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"How much heat is given out when a piece of iron of mass 50g and specific heat capacity 460 Jkg<sup>-1<\/sup>k<sup>-1<\/sup> cools from 85<sup>o<\/sup>C to 25<sup>o<\/sup>C?","options":["1.38 x 10<sup>6<\/sup> J","2.53x10<sup>4<\/sup>J","7.66x10<sup>3<\/sup>J","1.38x10<sup>3<\/sup>J","1.27 X10<sup>3<\/sup>J"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Heat transfer by convection in a liquid is due to the","options":["translatory motion of the molecules of the liquid","increased vibration of the molecules of the liquid about their mean positions","expansion of the liquid as it is heated","latent heat of vaporization of the liquid","ability of the liquid to evaporate at all temperatures"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a suitable method for reducing loss of heat from a piece of hot iron?","options":["Wrapping it in cotton wool","painting it black","Placing it in a vacuum","Placing it on rubber supports","Keeping it in a closed wooden box"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"When the direction of vibration of the particles of a medium is perpendicular to the direction of travel of a wave the wave transmitted is known as","options":["sound wave","transverse wave","longitudinal wave","stationary wave","mechanical wave"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A bat emits a sound wave at a speed of 1650.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup> and receives the echoes 0.15s later. Calculate the distance of the bat from the reflector","options":["8.75m","16.50m","87.75m","123.75m","330.00m"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A tuning fork sounds louder when its stem is pressed against a table top than when held in air because","options":["a larger mass of air is set vibrating by the table top","the whole table vibrates in resonance","the whole table has acquired a larger frequency","the fork and table have the same frequency","the amplitude of the vibrating fork is increased."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following is\/are characteristics of sound? I Pitch II. Loudness III. Quality IV Noise","options":["I only","II only","I and II only","l, II and III only","I, II, III and IV"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following is\/are necessary for the production of interference with two wave trains? I. The sources must be close to each other. II The waves must have the same frequency. III. The waves must have the same amplitude. IV. The waves must travel with the speed of light.","options":["I, II and III only","I and II only","II, III and IV only","II, III and IV only","l, II and IV only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A stone is dropped into the middle of a pool of water. Which of the following statements is\/are correct? I, Spherical waves are set up in the water. II. The water moves outwards to the sides of the pool. III. Energy is transmitted outwards from the centre of disturbance","options":["I only","II only","III only","I and III only","II and III only."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A concave mirror of radius of curvature 20cm has a pin placed at 15cm from its pole. What will be the magnification of the image formed?","options":["4.00","2.00","1.33","1.50","0.25"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A parallel beam of light is to be obtained from the headlamp ofa car. At which of the following positions should the source of light be placed from the pole of its spherical minor?","options":["At the focal point","At the centre of curvature","Beyond the centre of curvature","Between the focal point and the pole","Between the focal point and the center of curvature"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A simple microscope forms an image twice the size of the object. If the focal length of the lens of the microscope is 20m, how far is the object from the lens?","options":["10m","20m","30m","40m","60m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Given that the gravitational constant is 7 X 10<sup>-11<\/sup> Nm2kg<sup>-2<\/sup>, what is the force of attraction between 10<sup>6<\/sup>kg mass of lead hanging one metre away from a 10<sup>3<\/sup>kg mass of iron?","options":["7 x10<sup>-20<\/sup>N","7 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup>N","7x10<sup>-2<\/sup>N","7x10<sup>3<\/sup>N","7x10<sup>0<\/sup>N"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"What is the electric potential energy between two protons each of charge q and at a distance of r apart? (Permittivity of free space = \u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>)","options":["4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>q<sup>2<\/sup>r","qr\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>","q\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>r","q<sup>2<\/sup>\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>r","q<sup>2<\/sup>\/4\u03c0\u03b5<sub>o<\/sub>r"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A work of 30 joules is done is transferring 5 millicoulombs of charge from a point B to a point A in an electric Held. The potential difference between B and A is","options":["1.7 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>V","3.4x10<sup>-4<\/sup>V","1.5x10<sup>-1<\/sup>V","6.0 x10<sup>3<\/sup>V","1.2 x10<sup>4<\/sup>V"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A charge of 1.0 x 10<sup>-5<\/sup> Coulombs experience force of 40N at a certain point in space. What is the electric field intensity?","options":["8.00 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.00 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","4.00 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.00 x 10<sup>-4<\/sup>NC<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.50 x 10<sup>-1<\/sup>NC<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Calculate the resistance of the filament of a lamp rates 240 V, 40 W","options":["240\u03a9","360\u03a9","720\u03a9","1440\u03a9","2880\u03a9"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Birds can perch safely on overhead electric power cables without being electrocuted because","options":["birds can withstand high p.d. of the electric power cables","any accumulated charge on the birds is quickly dissipated","the feet of the birds are well insulated","the current is a.c. and has particular direction","there is no p.d between the birds and the cables"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A cell of e.m.f. 1.5 V and internal resistance of 2.59 is connected in series with an ammeter of resistance 0.59 and a resistor of resistance 7.09. Calculate the current in the circuit.","options":["0.15 A","0.20 A","0.60A","3.00A","6.67 A."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A rectangular coil of wire can rotate in a magnetic field. The ends of the coil are soldered to the two halves of a split ring. Two carbon brushes are made to press lightly against the split ring and when these are connected in circuit with a battery and rheostat, the coil rotates. This is a description of","options":["a suspended- coil vanometer","a moving-cell ammeter","a d.c generator","an electric motor","an induction coil,"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"How long will it take to heat 3 kg of water from 28<sup>o<\/sup>C to 88<sup>o<\/sup>C in an electric taking a current of 6 A from an e.m.f. source of 220V?","options":["96s","1.20s","570s","600s","1200s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following reduce(s) the effect of the back e.m.f. generated in the primary coil of an induction coil? The capacitor in the circuit II. The make and break contact in the circuit III. The ratio of turns in the secondary to that in the primary","options":["l only","II only","I and II only","II and III only","I, II and III."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"When the pressure of the gas in a discharge tube is gradually lowered. I. there is a violet glow in the tube II. the glow in the tube splits into bands which get further apart. III, the glow and the bands eventually disappear and there is a green fluorescence in the tube. IV. the tube breaks into pieces. Which of the following are correct?","options":["I and II only","I and III only","I and IV only","I, II and III only","I, II III and IV"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following statements about the atom is\/are correct? I. Energy is needed to remove electrons from an atom II. Particles in the nucleus of an atom are bound together by strong forces. III. A large amount of energy is required to separate the particles in the nucleus of an atom. IV. When the nucleus of a uranium atom is split, the energy released accounts for the difference in the masses of the products and the parent nucleus","options":["I only","I and II only","I and III only","II and IV only","I, II, III and IV"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"The nucleon number and the proton number of a neutral atom of an element are 238 and 92 respectively. What is the number of neutrons in the atom?","options":["330","165","146","119","73"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Water does not drip through an open umbrella of silk material unless the inside of the umbrella is touched. Which of the following phenomena is responsible for this?","options":["Surface tension","Hydrostatic upthrust","Viscosity","Diffusion","Osmosis"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A radioactive substance has a half-life of 20 hours. What fraction of the original radioactive nuclei will remain after 80 hours?","options":["1\/32","1\/16","1\/8","1\/4","1\/2"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"A metal is illuminated with a radiation of energy 6.88eV If the kinetic energy of the emitted electrons is 1.5OeV, calculate the work function of the metal.","options":["0.22eV","4.59eV","5.38eV","8.38eV","10.32eV"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following is not crystal?","options":["Sodium chloride","Lead","Copper (II) tetraoxosulphate (VI)","Glass","Germanium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"What is the difference between a crystalline and an amorphous solid? A crystalline solid","options":["has cubic structure while amorphous solid has hexagonal structure","has regularly-repeating pattern while an amorphous solid has not","is white while amorphous solid is yellow","is always hard while amorphous solid is always soft","melts on heating while an amorphous solid sublimates on heating."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following is not an evidence of the particle nature of matter?","options":["Diffusion","Brownian motion","Diffraction","Crystal structure","Photoelectricity"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1990"},{"question":"Which of the following is NOT a vector quantity?","options":["momentum","force","velocity","temperature","displacement"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a consequence of a force field?","options":["wieght","surface tension","gravitational pull","magnetic force","electric force"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A boy pulls a nail from the wall with a string tied to the nail. The string is inclined at an angle of 60<sup>o<\/sup> to the wall. If the tension in the string is 4N, what is the effective force used in pulling the nail?","options":["2\u221a3 N","4 N","4\u221a3 N","8 N","2 N"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following is used to determine the relative density of the acid in a car battery?","options":["Hypsometer","Hygrometer","Manometer","Hydrometer","Spectrometer"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A block of material of volume 20cm<sup>-3<\/sup> and density 2.5gcm<sup>-3<\/sup> is suspended from a spring balance with half the volume immersed in water. What is the reading of the spring balance? (Density of water = 1.0gcm<sup>-3<\/sup>).","options":["8g","25g","30g","40g","50g"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A piece of cork floating on water is acted upon by the forces of...","options":["Weight and viscosity","weight and upthrust","upthrust and viscosity","weight only","upthrust only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A stone tied to a string is made to revolve in a horizontal circle of radius 4m with an angular speed of 2 rad per sec. With what tangential velocity will the stone move off the circle if the string is cut?","options":["16.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","8.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","2.0 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.5 ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The motion of the prongs of the sounding tuning fork is","options":["random","translational","rotational","vibratory","vibratory and rotational"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following is a derived unit?","options":["Metre","Coulomb","Kilogram","Second","Ampere"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"An engine raises 1000kg of water through a height of 60m in 20s. What is the power of the engine? (Take g = 10ms<sup>-2><\/sup>).","options":["120,000 W","30,000 W","333 W","300 W","30 W"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following surfaces will radiate heat energy best?","options":["Red","White","Black","Yellow","Blue"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Water in an open container boils at a lower temperature when heated at the top of a mountain than at sea-level because at the top of a mountain the","options":["relative humidity is higher than at sea-level","rays of the sun adds more heat to the water","temperature is lower than that at sea-level","pressure is lower than that at sea-level","pressure is more than that at sea-level"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following substance is not a good conductor of electricity?","options":["Human body","Glass","Aluminium","Earth","Copper"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Calculate the heat energy required to vapourize 50g of water initially at 80<sup>o<\/sup>C if the specific heat capacity of water is 4.2Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>K (specific latent heat of vapourization of water is 2260Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>).","options":["533000J","230000J","117200J","113000J","4200J"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A block of ice at its melting point is left on a table in the atmosphere and observed to melt gradually. Which of the following statements is true about the melting process?","options":["the reaction force of the table on the ice breaks the ice into water molecules","heat extracted from the ice block makes the ice block cold","the ice block absorbs heat from the atmosphere and its temperature rises","the atmosphere absorbs  heat from the ice block and its temperature falls","the ice block absorbs heat from the atmosphere and its temperature remains constant as it melts"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"All the heat generated by a current of 2A passing through a resistor of 6\u03a9 for 2.5s is used to evaporate 5 g of a liquid at its boiling point. What is the specific latent heat of the liquid?","options":["60 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","120 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","300 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","360 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>","1500 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following instruments can be used to compare the relative magnitudes of charges on two given bodies?","options":["The electrophorous","Ebonite rod","Proof plane","Gold leaf electroscope","Capacitor"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A short chain is usual attached to the back of a petrol tanker trailing behind it to ensure that the","options":["petrol tanker is balanced on the wh eel","heat generated by friction in the engine can be conducted to the floor","charges generated by friction in the tanker can be conducted to the earth","the tanker moves slowly as the chain touches the floor","chain produces sound for the resonance of the tanker engine"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A ray of light is incidence on a plane mirror at an angle of 35<sup>o<\/sup>. What is the angle by the reflected ray with the surface of the mirror?","options":["125<sup>o<\/sup>","70<sup>o<\/sup>","65<sup>o<\/sup>","55<sup>o<\/sup>","35<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The image in a pine-hole camera is always","options":["diminished","enlarged","upright","inverted","blurred"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The refractive index of a given transparent medium is 1.4. Which of the following is the minimum internal angle for total internal reflection to take place in the medium?","options":["30<sup>o<\/sup>","36<sup>o<\/sup>","44<sup>o<\/sup>","46<sup>o<\/sup>","54<sup>o<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"The distance between a node and an anti-node for a transverse wave is equal to","options":["the wavelength","thrice the wavelength","one-half of the wavelength","one-quater of the wavelength","three quaters of the wavelength"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following is a stringed instrument?","options":["flute","trumpet","piano","drum","saxophone"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A sound pulse sent vertically downwards into the earth is reflected from two different layers of the earth such that echoes are heard 1.2s and 1.4s. Assuming speed of the pulse is 2000ms<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the distance between the layers.","options":["200 m","400 m","2400 m","2600 m","2800 m"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"In a wave the maximum displacement of particles from their equilibrium positions is called.","options":["frequency","amplitude","period","wavelength","wave velocity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"A string is stretched between two points 50cm apart. It is then plucked at its center and the velocity of the wave produced is 300m\/s. Calculate the number of vibrations made by the string in 1s.","options":["3","6","150","300","600"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the following is not a property of longitudinal waves?","options":["compression","reflection","refraction","polarization","diffraction"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"What is the gravitational potential due to a molecule of mass, m and at a distance, r from it? (G = gravitational constant).","options":["Gm<sup>2<\/sup>\/r<sup>2<\/sup>","Gm\/r","Gm<sup>2<\/sup>\/r","G<sup>2<\/sup>m<sup>2<\/sup>\/r","m<sup>2<\/sup>\/Gr<sup>2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Calculate the escape velocity for a rocket fired from the earth's surface at a point where the acceleration due to gravity is 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup> and the radius of the earth is 6 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>m.","options":["7.8 x 10<sup>6<\/sup>ms<sup>-12<\/sup>","1.1 x 10<sup>4<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","3.5 x 10<sup>7<\/sup>ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","6.0 x 10<sup>7<\/sup> ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","1.2 x 10<sup>8<\/sup>ms<sup>2-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1989"},{"question":"Which of the units of the following physical quantities are derived? I. Area II. Thrust III. Pressure IV. Mass","options":["I, II, III & IV","I, II, III only","I, II, IV only","I, & III only","I & IV only"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The slope of a striaght line displacement time graph indicates the","options":["Distance travelled","Uniform velocity","Uniform acceleration","Instantaneous acceleration","Uniform speed"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"When three coplanar and non-parallel forces are in equilibrium, <br>\r\nI. they can be represented in magnitude and direction by the three sides of a triangle taken in order. <br>\r\nII. their lines of action meet at a point.<br>\r\nIII. the magnitude of anyone equals the magnitude of the resultant of the other two.<br>\r\nIV. any one force is the equilibrant of the other two.<br>\r\n<br>\r\n<i>Which of the following statements above are correct?<\/i>","options":["I & II only","II & III only","II, III & IV only","I, II, III & IV","I, III & IV only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A ball of mass 0.5kg moving at 10ms<sup>-1<\/sup> collides with another ball of equal mass at rest. If the two balls move off together after the impact, calculate their common velocity.","options":["0.2ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","0.5ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","5.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","10.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>","20.0ms<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A body is projected into space with an initial velocity V<sub>0<\/sub> at an angle, \u03b8 to the horizontal. Which of the following statements is\/are correct about its motion?<br>\r\nI. The total time of flight is (V<sub>0<\/sub> Cos\u03b8)\/g.<br>\r\nII. The maximum height is (V<sub>0<\/sub> Sin 2\u03b8)\/2g.<br>\r\nIII. The range is (V<sub>0<\/sub><sup>2<\/sup> Cos<sup>2<\/sup>\u03b8)\/g.","options":["I & II only","I & III only","II & III only","II only","III only"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A ball is thrown vertically upwards from the ground with an initial velocity of 50ms<sup>-1<\/sup>. What is the total time spent by the ball in the air? (g = 10ms<sup>-2<\/sup>)","options":["2.5s","5.0s","10.0s","15.0s","20.0s"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following correctly gives the relationship between linear speed V and angular speed \u03c9 of a body moving uniformly in a circle of radius r?","options":["V = \u03c9r","V = \u03c9<sup>2<\/sup>r","V = \u03c9r<sup>2<\/sup>","V<sup>2<\/sup> = \u03c9r","V = \u03c9\/r"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The motion of a body is simple harmonic if the","options":["Acceleration is always directed towards a fixed point","path of motion is a striaght line","Acceleration is directed towards a fixed point and proportional to its distance from the point","Acceleration is proportional to the square of the distance from a fixed point","Acceleration is constant and directed towards a fixed point"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following statments about the gaseous state of matter is not correct? The molecules of a substance is in gaseous state","options":["are in constant state of motion","have different speed","have a temperature which is an average measure of the kinetic energy","have no molecular attractive force","have a pressure which is determined by the number of molecules present"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following cannot be used to measure the temperature of a substance?","options":["variation of pressure with temperature","expansivity of a liquid","change in resistance of a conductor","thermometric effect","change in color with temperature"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The clinical thermometer is characterized by having a","options":["wide range of temperature","wide bore","long stem","constriction","narrow bore"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A given mass of gas has a pressure of 80Nm<sup>-2<\/sup> at a temperature of 47<sup>o<\/sup>C. If the temperature is reduced to 27<sup>o<\/sup>C with the volume remaining constant, the new pressure is","options":["46.0 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","75.0 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","80.0 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","85.3 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>","139.4 Nm<sup>-2<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following is a reason why a concrete floor feels colder to the bare feet than a mat on the same floor during the rainy season?","options":["A mat if s better conductor of heat than the feet","Mat losses heat to the bare feet at a faster rate than concrete floor","Mat losses heat to the bare feet while the concrete floor extracts heat from them","Concrete floor is a better conductor of heat than the mat","Mat is a better conductor of heat than the floor"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following best explains a person suffers more severe burns when his skin is exposed to steam than when boiling water is poured onto his skin?","options":["steam is at a higher temperature than boiling water","steam posses greater heat energy per unit-mass than boiling water","steam spreads more easily over a wider area of the skin than boiling water","steam panetrates more easily over a wider area of the skin than boiling water","the specific latent heat of vaporization is released in changing from boiling water to steam"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following statments about radiant heat is\/are correct?<br>\r\nI. radiant heat cannot travel through a vaccum<br>\r\nII. rough surfaces emit radiant heat more than polished surfaces<br>\r\nIII. Dark surfaces absorb radiant heat more than bright surfaces","options":["I only","II only","III only","I & II only","II & III only"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"0.5kg of water at 10<sup>o<\/sup>C is completely converted to ice by extracting 188000J of heat from it. If the specific heat capacity of water is 4200J kg<sup>-1<\/sup>C<sup>-1<\/sup>, calculate the specific latent heat of fusion of ice.","options":["9.0 KJ kg<sup>-1<\/sup>","84.0 KJ kg<sup>-1<\/sup>","168.0 KJ kg<sup>-1<\/sup>","334.0 KJ kg<sup>-1<\/sup>","336.0 KJ kg<sup>-1<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The temperature at which the water vapour present in the air is just sufficient to saturate it is called the","options":["ice point","boiling point","steam point","dew point","saturation point"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following will affect the saturation vapour pressure of a liquid?","options":["Temperature of the liquid","Humidity of air","Volume of vapour","Volume of the liquid","mass of the liquid"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is\/are not correct about image formed by a plane mirror?<br>\r\nI. The magnification produced is 1<br>\r\nII. The image distance is same as the object distance<br>\r\nIII. The image is real<br>\r\nIV. The image is laterally inverted","options":["I only","II only","III only","I & II only","II & IV only"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A transparent rectangular block 5.0cm thick is placed on a black dot. The dot when viewed from above is seem 3.0cm from the top of the block   calculate the refractive index of the material of the block.","options":["2\/5","3\/5","3\/2","5\/3","5\/2"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The velocities of light in air and glass are 3.0 x108ms-1 respectively. Calculate the sine of the angle of incidence that will produce an angle of refraction of 30 for a ray of light incident on glass.","options":["1.2","1.0","0.8","0.6","0.3"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"An object is placed 36cm from a converging lens of focal length 24cm.If a real image which is 4cm high is formed, Calculate the height of the object.","options":["2.0cm","4.0cm","6.0cm","8.0cm","10.0cm"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The ability of the eye to focus objects at different distances is called","options":["power","accommodation","normal vision","persistence of vision","long sight"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The change of the direction of a wave-front because of a change in the velocity of the wave in another medium is called","options":["refraction","reflection","diffraction","interference","dispersion"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A boy standing a distance from the foot of a tall cliff claps his hands and hears an echo 0.5s later. If the speed of sound is 340ms1, how far is he from the cliff?","options":["17m","34m","85m","170m","680m"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A sounding tuning fork is brought near the end of a pipe containing an air column and the loudness of the sound increases. This effect is due to","options":["diffraction","an echo","resonance","interference","reverberation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A transformer with 55500 turns in its primary is used between a 240V a. c supply and a 120V kettle. Calculate the number of turns in the secondary","options":["11000","2750","460","232","10"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Local action is normally prevented from taking place in a simple electric cell by","options":["introducing an oxidising agent into the acid","not drawing current continuously for long periods","amalgamating the surface of the zinc plate","using a porous pot to isolate the zinc plate from the acid","using dilute sulphuric acid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A cell can supply current of 0.8A and 0.4A through a 2\u03a9 and a 3\u03a9 resistors respectively. Calculate the internal resistance of the cell.","options":["0.2\u03a9","0.4\u03a9","-1.0\u03a9","3.0\u03a9","9.0\u03a9"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A battery of emf 24V and internal resistance 4\u03a9 is connected to a resistor of 32\u03a9. What is the terminal p.d of the battery?","options":["24.0V","21.3V","16.0V","2.7V","2.0V"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"A lamp is marked 220V 60 W. Calculate the energy it would consume when connected to a 220V source for 1 hour.","options":["216000J","13200J","3600J","864J","220J"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"What is the effect of using split-rings in a simple d.c motor?","options":["The direction of rotation of the coil is reversed","The current in the coil flows in the same direction","The current in the coil becomes alternating","The direction of the force on the coil is reversed","The contact with the voltage is cut-off"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following statement is not correct about loaded spiral spring?","options":["The extension is proportional to the load applied, provided the elastic limite is not exceeded","If the elsatic limit is not exceeded, the contraction is proportional to the load removed.","Up to the yield limit, extension is no longer proportional to the applied load.","Beyond the elsatic limit, extension is no longer proportional to the applied load.","If the string regains its shape or form after deformation, it is said to be elastic."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Calculate the resistivity of a wire of length 2m and cross-sectional area 0.004cm<sup>2<\/sup> if the resistance is 3.0 \u03a9.","options":["0.0000267\u03a9cm","0.006\u03a9cm","0.26700\u03a9cm","0.27500\u03a9cm","0.060000\u03a9cm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following particles of ray has the highest penetrating power?","options":["Beta particles","Alpha particles","Gamma particles","Electrons","Neutrons"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following explains the concave meniscus of water in a glass tube?","options":["The adhesion between water and glas is greater than the cohesion between water molecules","The cohesion between water molecule is greater than the adhesion between glass and water","The molecules of water in the glass are moving faster than the molecules in the other parts","The molecules of water at the water-air boundary are often attracted to the center of the tube","The weight of the water pulls the central part of the surface down"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"The unit of inductance is the","options":["farad","henry","hertz","ampere","coulomb"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following is\/are not correct about isotopes of an element? The have","options":["the same neutron number","the same proton number","same number of electrons","same chemical properties","different physical poperties."],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following is\/are not affected by a magnetic field?<br>\r\nI. Neutrons<br>\r\nII. Cathode rays <br>\r\nIII. Alpha particles","options":["I only","II only","III only","I & III only","I, II & III"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"An electron of charge 1.6 x 10<sup>19<\/sup>C is accelerated in vacuum from rest at zero volt towards a plate of 40KV. Calculate the kinetic energy of the electron.","options":["4 x 10 <sup>25<\/sup>J","4 x 10<sup>21<\/sup> J","6.4 x 10<sup>20<\/sup> J","6.4 x 10<sup>-15<\/sup> J","2.5 x 10<sup>20<\/sup> J"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Which of the following is not an electromagnetic radiation?","options":["X-ray","Radio waves","Sunlight","Sound waves","Infra-red radiation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"Two radioactive elements A and B have half-lives of 100 and 50 years respectively. Samples of A and B initially contain equal amounts\/number of atoms. What is the ratio of the number of the remaining atoms of A to that of B after 200 years?","options":["4 : 1","2 : 1","1 : 1","1 : 2","1 : 4"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"1988"},{"question":"During the same interval, it is observed that a train travels the same distance as does a lorry. The two vehicles therefore have the same","options":["uniform accelation","instateneous velocity","initial velocity","average speed","average velocity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"1988"}]